The Erstwhile Manor

We got to see Caledwich from the sky, laid out in all its glory. The city predated Uther by hundreds of years, and had probably been settled by humans for thousands of years before it was a city, but when he’d become king, Caledwich had become his home, and the combination of a clear vision and nearly limitless resources had allowed him to reshape the place to his liking. Beyond that, the Apocalypse Demon had wreaked havoc on the city, which was exactly the sort of thing that allows for the bypass of eminent domain issues (not that such a thing existed in a monarchy like Anglecynn’s, though you had to be conscious of the lower classes revolting).

Back on Earth, D&D games had a tendency to drift into things that weren’t even remotely related to adventuring. Sometimes the party just wanted to parlay their gold into a spice trading company, and we would spend a session with me trying to desperately graft rules and dice rolls onto whatever it was they were doing. Reimer was always the one to focus most on that aspect of things, but Arthur was, somewhat predictably, about the big picture, with grand ideas that he wanted put into place. Over the years, I learned that there were a few things that were catnip for my friends, and if I needed a break from running a combat or narrative focused campaign, I could just throw some property their way, or better, a ship, and have them spend a few hours entertaining themselves and arguing at length about how things should look or function. Arthur had always loved castles, cities, and country estates, going so far as to make architectural drawings that he would bring in next session (but, you know, the kind that you do in high school, nothing rigorous).

Caledwich wasn’t purely the creation of the boy I’d known in high school, but I could see echoes of conversations we’d had and things he’d idly put on paper. The city had grand, sweeping avenues radiating out from its port, with traffic smoothly flowing around tall buildings, and green spaces never too far from each other. It was all done almost exclusively in white, which made it look similar to Minas Tirith, always one of Arthur’s favorite fantasy cities. Some of the buildings I recognized straight away, like the reconstructed Greychapel, and the Caledwich Castle, places that I had either read about or heard of from Amaryllis. There was a huge library with iconic minarets, and Caledwich’s own version of Grand Central Station, where a huge number of rail lines converged from all over the world. Other buildings were large and interesting looking, but I had no idea what they were, or if they were important at all.

“It’s breathtaking,” I said to Amaryllis.

“Uther had a flair for design,” said Raven. “Caledwich has had very few changes in the past five hundred years.”

“Yes, but some of that is due to the laws,” replied Amaryllis. “There have been restrictions on new buildings above a certain height, restrictions on buildings which don’t pass the Cultural Commission’s strict guidelines, and a number of other ways in which the city has been artificially limited from natural growth.”

“I’m not sure that’s fair,” replied Raven. “Part of his design philosophy was that a city has wants, and should be built so as to force those wants down constructive pathways. ‘We shape our cities; thereafter they shape us.’”

“Yes,” said Amaryllis. “He had the same philosophy toward government. It’s a fine philosophy, as it goes, but he simply didn’t have the foresight to keep the whole city together without his vision and guidance, such as they were. The same goes for the kingdom, which, I don’t think I have to tell you, reached a point of near civil war between his two sons shortly after he left. Unless there’s some hidden aspect to that which makes it all sensible and completely vindicates Uther?” Her voice was sharp and pinched, words too fast.

“You’re stressed, I understand that,” said Raven. “We can talk later, when it would be more productive.”

“Shit,” said Amaryllis after Raven had gone away. The ship was circling some tall buildings, angling toward the train station, whose roof was dotted with other modes of aerial conveyance, including a few helicopters. “I guess I owe her an apology.”

“We all know Uther wasn’t perfect,” said Pallida. “That was known in his lifetime, in case there was any doubt.”

“There’s still a time and a place,” I said. “I do want to hear from Raven how things went down with Uther’s sons, if she knows. It was the very first story that I heard when I got to Aerb.”

“There’s a lot of magic down there,” said Grak, who was watching the ground a lot closer than the rest of us. “People. A welcome party.”

“Shit,” said Amaryllis, looking to the ground. The ship had found a spot, and a man on the ground was waving flags to help get it into position, a process that apparently took quite a bit of shouting from our captain, though I gave her a little assistance with vibration magic. The sails had been furled as we’d passed the border of the city, and I had manipulated the weather with a combination of air and water to make it perfectly calm for us. It was probably the best and easiest flight that the captain of our ship would ever have.

Grak pointed, and I could see the people he’d been talking about. They were walking toward where our ship was landing. Even from a distance, I could see that they were coated in magic, just from the colors and cut of their clothes. There were three of them, not officials, unless I had completely missed the mark. With a small mental push, I looked at them using soul sight, and saw not just the color of their souls, but the colors of the entads they were wearing. The only real thing that revealed to me was that they were wearing mostly their own entads, with only a few whose colors marked them as having been loaned.

“Friend or foe?” I asked Amaryllis.

“That’s not the right question,” she replied. “The question is whose side they’re on. We don’t have friends or foes here, just … sides.” She bit her lip and waited as we got close enough to see their faces. “That’s Aster, Heath, and … Basil, maybe. They were in Rosemallow’s faction a few months ago.”

“That’s good,” I said. “We wanted to see Rosemallow.”

“Wanted is a strong word,” replied Amaryllis.

The ship landed, and we waited for the officials to come on board, as they’d done at the border. We answered their questions, had them look at our papers, and were finally released. Captain Bonny was much friendlier about the goodbye than I’d thought she would be, given the grief we had caused her by way of a looming dragon, but we were getting out of her hair, and she’d gotten her hazard pay and then some for basically nothing.

The three Penndraigs waiting for us on the tarmac (if it could be called that) were all talking amongst themselves, right up to the point when Amaryllis stepped off. I didn’t know if security was super lax around this place, or if they were allowed right up next to a few landed ships because they were royalty, but they were right there, waiting. They seemed to all come from the same mold, all on the taller side (though I had at least two inches on all of them), all with fair skin and red hair. I was pretty sure that I was going to get sick of how much the Penndraigs looked like each other.

“Our disgraced cousin returns!” said the one on the left. I didn’t know enough to put the names to the faces, but this one had a metal pail at his hip that was full of shurikens, so I mentally tagged him as Shuriken Bucket, surely the most distinctive thing about him.

The three princes gave a brief round of applause to Amaryllis, which they escalated to a rapid series of bows, which were surely sarcastic.

“You’re back much sooner than anyone thought you’d be,” said the middle one when they were done bowing. His sword was so ridiculously big that I dubbed him Monkey Grip. It was taller than him, and it seemed more like he was leaning against the sheath than the other way around.

“Everyone is very eager to hear the story of how you didn’t die,” said the one on the right. He was the least magically endowed of the three of them, without any armor on, though the holstered pistol at the side of his hip was definitely magical, as was the crown of moss and twigs. I was trying to think of a more clever shorthand than ‘Mosshead’ when Amaryllis deigned to respond.

“Cousin Heath, Cousin Aster, Cousin Basil, it’s good to see the three of you again,” she said, giving nods to each of them in turn, which helpfully let me know their actual names. “I’ve clearly missed much in my time away from Anglecynn, and I look forward to hearing from you or others what’s been happening in my absence.”

Heath (Shuriken Bucket) stood up a little bit taller. “Aunt Rosemallow is requesting an audience with you. She’s missed you terribly and wants to see you, before you go through with whatever asinine deal it is you’ve made with Aunt Hyacinth.”

“She’d be Cousin Hyacinth,” said Aster (Monkey Grip). Heath looked at him for a moment, then nodded. The way that the Penndraigs used ‘cousin’ and ‘aunt’ were more like honorifics than actual maps of familial relationship, which was confusing, because sometimes they meant the actual relationship. I’d noticed it when Amaryllis and Lisi were talking.

“We should get going soon,” said Heath. “It’s not clear why Hyacinth doesn’t have her own welcome party here, but let’s assume that’s our lovely aunt’s doing, shall we, and not risk a confrontation.”

“Araluen got bumped up to Chief of the Guards of Caledwich,” said Basil (Mosshead), “And you know that she was a right bitch even when we were all younger.”

“I barely remember her,” said Amaryllis. “And obviously I wouldn’t want to run afoul of either Hyacinth or Araluen, given that I’m in legal trouble at the moment. Hyacinth offered me a deal, and I intend to take it.”

“So what do you need to hear to come with us?” asked Heath. “That you don’t have a choice? Fine then, you don’t have a choice, if you don’t come with us, we’ll, I don’t know,” he looked at me, the first time he’d given me more than a glance. “Fuck, is he human? Tall, for a human. What have you been feeding him?”

“This is Juniper Smith,” said Amaryllis. “We met in the Risen Lands. Show him some respect.”

“Well,” said Heath, laughing just a bit as he squared his shoulder. “Cousin Amaryllis, Mister Juniper, come with me, or I’ll have to get violent, and nevermind that you have us outnumbered five to one.” His shoulders slumped. “There, was that properly threatening for you? You can say that you came with us to avoid a confrontation. Say that we put you between a rock and a hard place, which is true.” He looked at the collection of people standing around the ship. “Maybe we don’t need all twenty of your people to come with us though.”

Amaryllis turned back, looking at the ten tuung that we’d brought with us. “Rebecca, set up at the Hotel Delzora with the rest of the tuung. Gemma, Solace, you’ll be with them. Pallida, you’re the local guide. Grak, set up defenses.” I wasn’t too comfortable leaving Grak behind, given that a warder was an incomparable asset, but I had to trust Amaryllis on this. The Anglecynn thing was her show, after all.

“It’s been some time since I’ve been through Caledwich,” said Pallida. “But I’ll manage, I’m sure. Will you?”

Amaryllis nodded, then turned back to the three princes. “It’ll be the three of us then, myself, Juniper, and this is Raven Masters.”

“Named after the Knight?” asked Basil.

“Something like that,” replied Raven.

“Then come on, let’s get going,” said Heath. He hefted his bucket of shurikens so that it was behind his back and smiled at us.

“Seems as though you’ve amassed a great deal of power in a very short time, cousin,” said Heath as we walked through the train terminal. People were avoiding us, and the station guards, dressed in identical heavy armor that was almost certainly entad-made, stoically held their gaze anywhere but where we were. “We’ll have to talk about that on the ride over.”

“I’ll talk to Rosemallow when I see her,” said Amaryllis.

“How good is your intelligence service in the Republic of Miunun?” asked Heath. “Middling to poor, I’m guessing, unless you’re feeding at the teat of the Empire. Given that you’re being press-ganged into a ride with us, perhaps it would behoove you to spend the time getting up to speed. All we want is the scoop, the scuttlebutt, the hot gossip, whatever you can tell us about the most talked about girl in all of Anglecynn.”

“It’s not actually so bad,” said Basil. “In case you were wondering. There’s been a press offensive, but very little substance. They are talking about you though.”

“We will accept scraps,” said Heath. He pointed ahead, out into the street, where trams were lined up. An armored man with folded hands was standing by one of them, and no one was going in it. “We’ll be pulling rank and taking one of these, I hope you weren’t expecting anything more.”

“It’s a step down from what I remember,” said Amaryllis, frowning. “Less secure.”

“Well, of course, things have been a little different in recent months,” replied Heath. He hopped up into the tram and set his bucket of shurikens down beside him, and the other princes followed after him, with Aster’s enormous sword taking some maneuvering. We followed after them, taking the opposing bench, which left us facing each other. The tram was one of many, big enough for maybe a dozen people. There was no driver, but there were controls, and Basil fiddled with them, which caused the tram to lurch into motion, not seeming to require anything else in the way of interaction. I had a lot of questions about how this all worked, and kept them to myself.

“You can go first,” said Amaryllis, folding her hands in her lap. “Tell me about my diaries being public.”

“Happened about a week ago,” said Heath, seeming to enjoy himself, with his bucket of shurikens set beside him, held in place with one hand. “Popular opinion among the Court is that it was Rosemallow’s doing, since it was her people who helped to get your affairs in order after your presumed death. Beyond that, there were some articles in the dailies, a few pointed discussions on the radio, and that was enough to get the ball rolling on its own. Legally, there’s an inquiry into the inquiry that got you sent to the trial, and a call for an end to the trials, which were already up in the air because of the whole skin magic exclusion — had news of that reached your shores?”

“It had,” replied Amaryllis. “You know that. What’s the point of all this?”

“Rosemallow keeps her cards close to her chest,” said Aster. He looked ridiculous next to his enormous sword, which barely fit in the tram.

“If you want to talk best guesses, she either wants you back, or she wants good relations with whatever scheme you’ve got cooking,” said Heath. “She’s presenting herself as having a real desire for change and reform, some of the stuff you wrote about in your diary, but if you believe she’s turned over a new leaf, then you’re dumber than I remember you being.”

“Did she think publishing my diaries would endear me to her?” asked Amaryllis.

“ Are they really your diaries?” asked Heath. “Everyone is wondering.”

“I haven’t read what she published,” replied Amaryllis. “I can’t know what she slipped in there.”

“Most of the essays are hers, or ghost-written, I suspect,” said Heath. “I read some of it. It’s a lot of raging against the system, cynicism about the Court and the Empire, paired with a naked idealism about how the world might be. It’s trite and naive enough to have been written by a teenager, I’ll give it that.” Heath himself was in his early twenties, by my best guess, though he had a billionaire playboy vibe to him that could potentially last a man well into his thirties.

“The diary is very raw,” said Basil. “That’s what people like about it.”

“Hrm,” said Amaryllis. “And what else has been happening in the Lost King’s Court in the last few months?”

“Larkspur Prentiss died, though I’d be surprised if you didn’t already know about that,” replied Heath. “He wasn’t a linchpin, but he was important, and the circumstances are a bit, shall we say, curious. He was blasted out of the sky by a dragon while flying a helicopter in a country he shouldn’t have been in.”

”He was Foreign Security Director,” said Aster. “It’s not that curious that he was off flying in a helicopter somewhere.”

“Regardless,” replied Heath. “All that aside, there have been some minor scandals in the half year or so, I can’t recall exactly when you left, but in terms of highlights, cousin Origanum got into a fantastically public fight with his wife about infidelity on his part, the legislature has been in deadlock again, —”

“On what issue?” asked Amaryllis.

Heath, Aster, and Basil looked at each other. “Not sure,” said Heath.

“The legislature is deadlocked, and you don’t know why?” asked Amaryllis.

“Cousin,” said Heath, clearly exasperated, “The legislature goes into deadlock often enough that I don’t really pay that much attention to it. I get told how to vote when the important votes come up, like a good little soldier in the grand war of laws, but I don’t take an active interest in whatever the hells our esteemed family is doing. It’s a sausage factory. Best not to know.”

“Then what are the papers saying that the deadlock is caused by?” asked Amaryllis.

“That depends on what papers you’re reading, I assume,” said Heath.

“I think … officially it was something about payments to the Empire,” said Aster. “Maybe because of the new exclusion? Or the refugees? We took in a lot with the Risen Lands, and no one is very happy about all these people from Li’o, even if they’re more on the imperial side, or because of that. But don’t quote me on that.”

“That would, obviously, just be what they’re saying it’s about,” said Heath. “Most likely it’s down to this or that holding getting more or less governmental aid, or whether or not a new facility built in Pembershire will get ten or twelve million obols, or some other horseshit like that. But as it stands, we don’t really know what this particular standoff is about. Oh, and one of the guilds is using the opportunity to go on strike.” He looked to Aster.

“It’s the Warehousers. They have a list of seven demands,” said Aster. “I don’t think I would be able to recite it from memory. Better pay was one. There was an accident a few weeks ago, a shipment from Ellison carrying something that it shouldn’t have been.”

“Three dead,” said Basil, making a face.

“Enough about all that,” said Heath. “If you want to know what I think Aunt Rosemallow is up to, my guess is that she’s trying to make you a lightning rod for the opposition and sweetening you up to come back. She’ll stick your neck out and try to profit from it, which I’m given to understand was what she did leading up to your trial.”

“Sorry,” I said. “Why are you taking the tram rather than a car?”

“Oh!” replied Heath. He turned to speak to Amaryllis, rather than to me. “Not really sure, but I think it’s one half the strike, one half the diary. There’s a bit in there about you trying Barren bread and thinking about all the good things you have, and how much waste there is, and the difficulty in paring down the Court into something more austere. Rosemallow has floated the idea of a Second Grand Reconciliation, but there’s no way that actually happens. Hence, highly public shows of humility for a few weeks until people calm down. Did you actually write that stuff though?”

“I did,” said Amaryllis. “I would have to check the wording to make sure it wasn’t edited.”

“Well, it struck a chord,” replied Heath. “Our dear auntie has suggested that it would be better for us to be seen as men of the realm, bound by the law rather than above it. I’m not sure how long she expects us to keep it up for, but it’s already starting to chafe.” He had been sitting forward slightly, and leaned back in his seat, looking over Amaryllis. “Now, we’re halfway through our trip, more or less. Would you like to tell me how you ended up as the de facto leader of a nation of frogs?”

Amaryllis gave the abbreviated version of things, naturally, not just because the long version would have been too long, but because there were some things we were planning on just not telling anyone. Officially speaking, Amaryllis and I went to a hidden cache of entads in Silmar City following our drop into the Risen Lands. That cache allowed us to travel outside of the exclusion zone, which we did, and from there, we’d been making our way through the world, trying to gather together whatever remnants of her life (and fortune) we could, those things not snatched up by the Anglecynn legal system. During a train trip away from Cranberry Bay, we met with Esuen and helped her escape, which is what led to us being gifted the Isle of Poran and taking on fairly powerful advisory roles in the new tuung government.

Then, at least partially in repayment for my extended service and unwavering loyalty, Amaryllis had helped me to enroll at Sound and Silence, which —

“Holy shit,” said Heath. “You were there? You were in Li’o when the exclusion hit?”

“The tuung were first responders,” said Basil. “I’d wondered about that. And there were rumors.”

“I’ll have to see what the papers are saying,” replied Amaryllis. “But yes, we were there when the exclusion hit.” She paused for a moment, then looked at me. “Juniper was the one who killed the creature.”

I could feel all eyes on me. It wasn’t technically true. All I’d done was attack using a combination of blood magic and bone magic. It had been Bethel that had delivered the killing blow. Granted, she wouldn’t have been able to do that if I hadn’t been sapping the kaiju of all its strength, but I still felt awkward getting all the credit.

“I thought that it was a — a monster, so tall it was scraping the clouds, so big that when it fell it crushed thousands,” said Heath. “They were bringing in star mages to remove the body, that’s how big it was.”

“I’m a fairly capable warrior,” I replied.

I could feel their eyes on me, paying attention to me for once. Heath moved his bucket of shurikens a little bit closer to him. I don’t know what good he thought the shurikens would do, especially in the cramped car, but I also didn’t know what the nature of the entad was (by soul sight, both the bucket and shurikens piled inside it were entads linked to him, obvious enough, but still worth checking).

“Just how much firepower is sitting in this tram right now?” asked Heath. He’d been keeping things light since the moment we’d met him, but now his voice had become perfectly level.

“We didn’t come to Anglecynn to fight,” said Amaryllis. “I don’t believe that whatever wrongs I perceive to have been done to me will be righted by unleashing our might on members of the Court.”

Heath relaxed, but only fractionally. “I’m pretty sure that Rosemallow is going to have you looked over by a warder,” he said. “Either Salvia or Citronella. Just so you know.”

“That’s a fool’s errand,” said Amaryllis. “I could kill her with my bare hands, if I wanted to.”

“Cousin,” began Heath.

“The Lost King always said to speak softly and carry a big stick,” said Raven. It was the first time she’d spoken. “One of the principles of big stick diplomacy is letting the other party know, ahead of time, that you really do have the bigger stick.”

“Sorry, and who are you?” asked Heath, looking her over.

“Raven Masters,” replied Raven. “The last living Knight of the Square Table.”

There was a dead silence in the tram, and I listened to the sound of it moving over the track. I had been multithreading the whole time, focusing on the world around us with one mind, taking in the city, not just for threat assessment, but because I had never been here before. Caledwich was incredibly clean for a big city, especially given how many people there were on the streets, and how much white dominated the color scheme. Most of the color came from the interiors of buildings, which were revealed to the street through large, multi-paned windows. The clothing of the people I saw going by was likewise bright and colorful, more than in Cranberry Bay or Li’o, and it might have been my imagination, but a fair number of people seemed like they were wearing mock-entads, pieces that had the out-there styling common on entads, but without actually being magical. I wasn’t big on cities, but so far as cities went, it didn’t seem so bad. There weren’t billboards or other huge advertisements, which I guessed was down to some strict regulations, something fairly common in Caledwich, from what I had read.

“Well, this is above my pay grade,” said Heath, letting out a breath and returning to his previous demeanor. The twinkle came back in his eyes. “What would it take for me to get in on the ground floor?”

Aster shifted on his part of the bench, moving his enormous sword to the side. “Offering to defect, even in jest, is probably not something you should be doing.”

Heath turned and clasped him on the shoulder. “Cousin, do you know what I like about you?”

“What?” asked Aster.

“Nothing,” replied Heath with a giant smile. He turned back to us. “So if I can ask, what’s the plan here, with Hyacinth and Rosemallow? Meet them with overwhelming firepower?”

“We do bring overwhelming power to the table,” said Amaryllis. “But no, there’s no plan. Hyacinth is threatening the Republic of Miunun, and I’m here to pay the price.”

“That being?” asked Heath.

“Revocation of my lands and properties, which are currently held in trust, an arrangement for investiture of bound entads, and sterilization,” said Amaryllis.

“Well that’s insanity,” said Heath. “You know whatever Hyacinth has on you, Aunt Rosemallow is going to make you some offer, or help the problem go away.”

“I know that’s probably her plan,” said Amaryllis. She paused for a moment. “She was supposed to protect me.”

“Bad blood, I understand,” replied Heath.

“You were guilty though,” said Aster.

“Guilty of moving money around,” said Amaryllis. “It’s the same budgetary malfeasance that half of the Court gets involved in. None of it was to enrich myself. And half of what they pinned on me wasn’t even my doing. Beyond that, it was nothing that should have required a death sentence.”

“Technically, the trial by adversity isn’t actually a death sentence,” said Aster.

“That’s not helpful,” said Basil.

“She’s sitting right across from us,” replied Aster. He looked annoyed. “Obviously if the Court actually wanted her dead, she’d have died.”

“Semantics aside, it was obviously unjust,” said Heath. “And I’m not just saying that because I fully believe the three of you are capable of leveling a city block if you so choose. I could repeat back everything the opposition said about you, and is saying about you now that you’re beloved by the people, but I don’t see a point in relitigating. You feel hard done by, and that’s perfectly understandable. I don’t think that means you and Rosemallow can’t work something out.”

“Did she think that you could soften me up?” asked Amaryllis. Her voice was hard.

“You know, you come across much more personable in your diary,” said Heath.

“You said you hadn’t read it,” replied Amaryllis, crossing her arms again.

“Bits and pieces, and whatever people have been talking about,” said Heath. “I’ve read through osmosis. Cousin —” he gave a frustrated sigh, “Yes, I’m sure that Rosemallow selected the people who would pick you up very carefully, for her own reasons, but I wasn’t given any instructions on how to handle you, aside from a reminder that your ejection from Anglecynn was rather harsh. If I’m trying to get you to make a deal with Rosemallow, it’s because I think it’s in all our best interests.”

Amaryllis took a breath. “You’re right, cousin. And of course I’ll listen to whatever she says, but what I hear will be colored by the fact that she was grooming me, protecting me, and suddenly stopped when it would have cost her politically. If we reach some alternate deal, it will have to account for the distinct lack of trust.”

“Did she ever explicitly say that she would protect you?” asked Aster.

“Not the time, nor the question,” said Heath. He looked out the window. “We’re almost there.”

We had transitioned out of the parts of Caledwich with skyscrapers and grand avenues, into an area with enormous homes that were just barely visible behind acres of manicured gardens and tall fences. The tram slowly came to a stop at what seemed like a small town nestled in among the mansions, with not much more than a cafe, grocery store, and post office, if I read the signs right. My guess was that it was a place people around here went if they didn’t want a long trek into the city proper, though the tram ride hadn’t been too bad. We weren’t in the suburbs, just in a nicer part of town, but I could see how it would be annoying to spend twenty minutes traveling when all you wanted was a stick of butter. Per Amaryllis, most of the Court had live-in staff, with a butler and a housekeeper at a minimum, often more, at least in the larger houses.

We exited the tram and I watched for a moment as it went off on its own. It was remotely possible that the tram system was controlled through some ingenious mechanical or electrical system, linked up by underground wires and controlled from a remove. I could see, in my mind’s eye, how I would have done it, and tried my best to stop my mind from working away at the problem. There were lots of challenges to be solved, like keeping empty trams from clumping up, making the system robust and reliable, making it all extensible so more trams could be added, preventing gridlock, on and on. It was also entirely possible that the trams were some variety of magic, with all the obvious-after-five-minutes logistical and engineering problems resolved by virtue of 'it's magic, I don't have to explain shit'.

We had a bit of a walk to get to Erstwhile Manor, which let me take in more of the picturesque neighborhood, whose only flaw was that it reeked of money.

The gate was set back from the road, and there was a guardhouse next to it, with a man in a prim black uniform and entad breastplate who came out to greet us. He looked sharp and serious, and asked a few questions of Heath, giving all of us the side eye before finally letting us in. This was another display of wealth and power, putting a well-trained man there whose only job was to guard the house, especially since he would be useless against most of the schools of offensive magic, not to mention a wide variety of entads. I wasn’t discounting the notion that he might be a mage himself, but if he was, that was even more of a display of wealth and power.

The Erstwhile Manor dated to Uther’s time, when it had been far more disconnected from Caledwich, out in the country more than located in a rich neighborhood. Uther had built it himself using steel magic, the magestone a result of a specially blended steel. It was a slate gray, which had been accentuated with a dark wood and bright greenery, some of which I thought must have been a nightmare to water given how high up it was. Unusually for steel magic, the exterior of the building was intricately detailed, with most of that detail being done in the same magestone, which meant that all the panels and vertical lines that broke up the surfaces of the building had been done at the time it was erected, rather than added after the fact. At the time it was built, it would have been a radical departure from architectural standards, but now it was almost orthodox, or perhaps even a bit stodgy. When I’d first been told about the manor, the thing that most caught my attention was the name: the Erstwhile Players had been the performing troupe that Uther had supposedly spent three years with.

We were greeted by a butler, who led us to a waiting room, and the three princes went their own ways, their duties having been discharged. The interiors of the rooms that I had seen were less impressive than the exterior, though that was partly because I wasn’t a big fan of the ‘loads and loads of things’ approach to interior design. Walls got covered in paintings, cabinets filled with relics were given prominent locations, and it all wound up looking cluttered. The sitting room we got placed in was no exception.

A suit of armor was half-hidden against one wall, which I might have dismissed as more ostentatious decoration if Amaryllis hadn’t already clued me in that it was an automaton. Amaryllis didn’t think it would be any threat to me, except insofar as I might accidentally provoke it to attack me, which might result in embarrassment, if nothing else.

After a few minutes, a warder came in to look all of us over, which didn’t take long, and when she was done, we were left alone.

“How much of that was true, and how much for show?” asked Raven, after some time had passed. There was a warmth and gentleness in her voice which reminded me of my school counselor when he was trying to be helpful.

Amaryllis was staring off into the distance. “Assume this room is bugged.”

It would obviously have occurred to Rosemallow that Amaryllis’ outrage and indignation was performative. My own understanding was that Amaryllis really did feel hard done by, but that she was perfectly capable of being polite and masking her feelings, if the situation called for it. That she was reacting with hostility toward Rosemallow was at least partly because she thought it was to her benefit.

“We need to read the diaries,” I said. “Or failing that, it would be better if Raven and I knew what was in them. This is your show, after all.”

Amaryllis paused for a moment. “I started keeping a diary when I was nine years old,” said Amaryllis. “I burned the diary from the first year, then began keeping one that was a little more circumspect in what it included. Parts were rewritten when I was older. It certainly wasn’t exhaustive, but it included notable events in my life, along with certain ruminations on various subjects including monarchy, poverty, entrenched systems, whatever I happened to be reading at the time — these were sometimes in the form of essays to myself, a way to distill down whatever I was thinking into a more rigid, modular form. There are some observations of other people, my thoughts on how they presented themselves and what they wanted, with a focus on pragmatic empathy. It’s hard to remember what’s in there. I know there are a number of places where I talk about what I saw as malfeasance within the Lost King’s Court, either ways that procedure was ignored, ways that things were intentionally unjust or disordered, failures to live up to the supposed ideals … I don’t know if all that made it into the published version, naturally, but Heath described it as cynical toward the Court and the Empire, which I wouldn’t disagree with.”

“Anything about love interests?” asked Raven. “Any specific enemies that you might have made?”

Amaryllis pursed her lips. “There are many places where I was candid,” replied Amaryllis. “Many names were replaced with a letter though, usually according to my own system, though the details might be enough to connect those letters to people, especially if you had a record of where I had been on a given date. Love interests … there were none, aside from the arranged marriage to Larkspur. There were a few entries on that, which were fairly honest. Resignation, trepidation, grappling with the needs of duty … I don’t know if any of that would have made the cut.”

“Would you object if I started reading?” asked Raven.

“Go ahead,” said Amaryllis. “Ask me if anything seems particularly out of character for me.”

“Can I ask what’s not in there?” I asked.

Amaryllis paused again, furrowing her brow. “I left out specifics of meetings. There’s nothing ostensibly criminal either, though there are a few thoughts about criminality in a system where that criminality is part of the status quo. I also obviously didn’t break classification, which I would include under criminality.” She let out a slow breath. “There’s a lot that’s covered by classification, less so by criminality.”

The butler returned not too much later, while Raven was in the middle of spot checking the Diaries. He said that Amaryllis would meet with Rosemallow alone, in what he called the White Room. That wasn’t entirely unforeseen, and Amaryllis didn’t push back against it. I just hoped that she would be okay. There was bad blood, of a kind that I didn’t really have much experience with, but I trusted Amaryllis to keep her cool.

The White Room

The White Room was one of the special rooms of the Erstwhile Manor, one which Amaryllis was well-acquainted with. It had no windows, instead being lit by several complicated and expensive methods that spread gentle white light through the entirety of the space. The walls were white with cream-colored accents, and the few pieces of furniture were likewise variations on white, with dark brown woadwood supports that had been artfully carved and given claws of polished necrium. The environment just barely managed to avoid sterility with a few small plants at strategic locations.

The room was extensively warded, and beyond that, surrounded by a shell of materials that would block outside interference, inference, or surveillance. The White Room was, so far as it could be made so, a dead spot in the world, where any conversation would be as private as a conversation between people could be.

Rosemallow sat in a padded chair with her hands folded in her lap. She was wearing one of her usual dresses, an entad that happened to look spectacular on her, along with a choker that matched it. Rosemallow had her fair share of entads, and Amaryllis didn’t know all of their functions. That was something that you kept quiet, if you could, though registration with the Entad Authority was mandatory, even if you were a member of the Court, and the Entad Authority was hardly a watertight organization.

Rosemallow herself looked the same as ever, as though she hadn’t aged a day, though for her it had only been a handful of months. For Amaryllis, it had been a few intense years. Rosemallow was rail thin, with curly hair that was much more grey than brown, though at her age it was likely that it was dyed. She had a mild look, which was typical for her, even when she was delivering devastating news or speaking in a cold fury. Rosemallow could order the execution of a man with no more emotion than some people used to order lunch, and strangely, she never used her control of her emotions in the other way, never put warmth or affection in her voice when that would have been endearing.

“You’ve had a long trip, I take it,” said Rosemallow as Amaryllis came into the room. She gestured at a tiered tray of various foods that sat on a low table between the chairs. “Have something to eat.” Beside the tray of food there was a pot of coffee and two cups.

Amaryllis sat down and took a small finger sandwich from the tray, eating it with more decorum and restraint than she usually showed around food these days. She’d deliberately broken herself of the habit of eating daintily, ignoring the table manners she’d had drilled into her. Falling back into the old habits came very naturally.

“I asked Rodrick to make all your favorites,” said Rosemallow as she watched Amaryllis eat.

“I noticed,” said Amaryllis. She ate the watercress sandwich delicately, without hurry, waiting for Rosemallow to ask the first question, which of course didn’t happen. When she was finished with the sandwich, she went for the coffee and poured herself a steaming cup, which she sniffed, savoring the flavor, before taking her first sip.

“I’m sure you have questions,” said Rosemallow.

“I do,” replied Amaryllis. She sat back, holding the porcelain cup in both hands, feeling its warmth. “I’m not in any particular rush to get the answers. I suppose we can start with a simple question, which is whether or not you know why I’m here.”

“You’ve come because Hyacinth has put pressure on your fledgling nation,” said Rosemallow. “You violated the Draconic Confederacy’s rules in your attempt to contain the exclusion at Li’o, perhaps because you thought it was an acceptable trade-off, perhaps because of circumstances beyond your control, or perhaps because you simply made a mistake. Hyacinth pulled strings and called in favors, giving up political capital in order to ensure that you would be under pressure. She wants your lands, your entads, and a guarantee that her children will have the birthright that should, by the laws of our kingdom and of nature, belong to your next of kin. Do I have that right?”

“More or less,” replied Amaryllis. “No one has ever accused you of having a poor intelligence network.” She said it as though with resignation, but it was also a way of goading Rosemallow, either into asking the questions she wanted to ask, or revealing things she had planned to hold back. Amaryllis didn’t believe that Rosemallow knew everything, and there had to be some elements of what had happened in the past half a year that were utterly baffling. At most, Rosemallow had a mole within Uniquities that had given her everything Uniquities knew, but Uniquities didn’t have the full picture, not by a wide margin.

“There are some things that my intelligence network can’t answer,” said Rosemallow. She leaned forward and poured her own cup of coffee, taking her time, allowing the words to marinate in the silence. “What kept me up at night was a simple question.” Her eyes were a pale blue and utterly piercing, though she was only bowing her head slightly to blow on her coffee. “Why didn’t you write?”

The question didn’t quite blindside Amaryllis, but it was a near thing. Of course Rosemallow would pretend that they still held a close relationship, and ask not after matters of practicality, filling in the gaps in her knowledge, but rather, ask a personal question, one that would accomplish her thus far unstated goals.

“As you probably know, I was attacked during the trial by adversity,” said Amaryllis. “It was either the Fuchsia Coterie, or some group pretending to be them, likely put on the plane because someone somewhere in the process accepted a bribe, insurance in case I made it through the trial unscathed. I elected not to join the Host because I was worried that there would be another assassination attempt if I did. When I went to my ancestral property of Weik Handum, I was attacked with not even a bare attempt at diplomacy or discussion, barely escaping with my life. Only recently have I been in a position to send you a letter without fear that it would be intercepted.”

“And yet even then, you did not,” replied Rosemallow. She took a sip of her coffee.

Amaryllis was trying to think about what Rosemallow wanted, how she was maneuvering the conversation, and where that conversation was going. Rosemallow was attempting to provoke a discussion of what had happened in court and everything leading up to it. That, in turn, might lead to an apology, a diffusion of tension, both sensible goals and another plank of Rosemallow’s strategy to reform an alliance, now that Amaryllis was, once again, useful.

“I don’t actually know why you didn’t help me,” said Amaryllis.

“Hrm,” said Rosemallow. She sipped her coffee then placed it on the table. “Are you familiar with the game tug-of-war?”

“No,” replied Amaryllis, which wasn’t strictly true, but plausible enough, and would allow Rosemallow to give the metaphor her framing.

“In the Icher Peninsula, they created a replacement for war, where two teams of five men would pull on a rope, trying to get it over to their side,” said Rosemallow. “Both teams would pull on the rope as hard as they could. Now, in some circumstances, and some formulations of the game, one team would simply release their rope. I suppose you can imagine the result: the opposing team would be pulling a rope that no longer had any tension, and they would go reeling backward, falling down, sometimes getting injured in the process.”

“You’re saying that the opposition, Larkspur, Hyacinth, Phlox, Onion, whoever was directing it from the top, they were putting effort into attempting to murder me, and by putting no effort whatsoever of your own in, you were able to get one over on them?” asked Amaryllis.

“‘Get one over on them’?” asked Rosemallow. “Who have you been spending time with, that you would speak that way?”

“Powerful people,” replied Amaryllis. “Powerful people who are less concerned with decorum than you are. Loyal people.”

“Well, in their parlance, then yes, the intent was to ‘get one over’, which was exactly what I did. They spent an enormous amount of political capital, they called in favors, they did everything they could in order to make sure that their scheme would work — and I offered no resistance. They put in a high bid, my young blossom, and they greatly overpaid.” Rosemallow gave one of her thin smiles, barely turning up the corners of her lips. “They hardly expected to win, and when they did, it caught them off-guard. Half of the time you were gone was spent with me pressing my advantage against them, taking concessions where I was able, enacting legislation that they were too weak to stop. Because they’d set precedent for actions against malfeasance, they put themselves in a vulnerable position, as there are few within the Empire who aren’t guilty of illegally reassigning funds at their whim, with some less cautious than others. I was two steps ahead of them.”

“They overestimated how much you would do to save me,” said Amaryllis. “They overestimated my importance to you.”

“Importance is relative,” replied Rosemallow. “You understand that the trial by adversity wasn’t a death sentence, don’t you? I was well aware of your skills. You had some skill in blood magic, enough to give you an advantage in melee, you were competent with simple electromotor systems, you were athletic and keen-minded. Most of those dropped into the Risen Lands are clueless about how to survive. If you had come back as I expected you to, you would have joined with the Host, served two years there, and been enormously strengthened by it, with more managerial experience for when you transitioned back into civilian life.”

“You didn’t know about the Fuchsia Coterie?” asked Amaryllis.

“Not until a week later,” said Rosemallow. “It was another example of our opponents overplaying their hand in an attempt to see their plan to completion. I hadn’t thought they would be so desperate. Those responsible at the ground level, at least those I could identify, have been dealt with accordingly.”

“Anyone important?” asked Amaryllis.

“A judge, a bailiff, and a shire-reeve,” replied Rosemallow. This was another way of saying, ‘no’. “It was kept quiet, for the most part, in exchange for certain concessions from my counterparts. The whole thing looked to explode into a scandal, but was better used as a vise grip than a grenade.”

It was tempting to descend into sarcasm, with something like ‘I’m glad me almost getting killed worked out for you’, but Amaryllis hadn’t undertaken this meeting to be petty, nor even for revenge, so she simply filed it all away for later, when she would vent to Juniper and attempt to keep herself capable of weathering the storm of useless emotions like betrayal.

“You’d planned to welcome me back, once I was in the Host, and tell me that it was a lesson that I should take to heart,” said Amaryllis. “Unfortunately for you, it didn’t work out that way.”

“I’m not sure that I would call it unfortunate,” replied Rosemallow. “Speaking strictly from my own perspective, there are a number of events that I believe followed from your decision to go elsewhere, including the death of Larkspur Prentiss.”

“Are you going to ask me if I killed him?” asked Amaryllis.

“No,” replied Rosemallow. “I would rather not know, so that if I’m asked, I don’t have to lie about what you said. I assume that his erratic behavior following your escape from the Risen Lands wasn’t mere coincidence, but perhaps you killed him in self defense, half a world away, or perhaps in his haste, paranoia, or incompetence, he really did bring a dragon down on himself.”

“I would have been content not to come back to Anglecynn,” Amaryllis lied. “I was perfectly happy being away from the Court, able to build up my own part of the world, disconnected from the rest of you.” The truth was more complicated, of course, but the truth didn’t have as much leverage.

“You have cousins who are afforded that luxury, but you are not,” replied Rosemallow. “‘Heavy is the head that wears the crown’. Shirking your burden was never an option for you, not just because of your privileged position of being the most direct descendant of our common ancestor, but because you never had the temperament necessary to sit by while there was work to be done or people in need. In some senses, that was your greatest weakness, and given what’s come of your defense of Li’o, there’s evidence that’s still true. It was always the case that you would return to Anglecynn, to once again be embroiled in our conflicts.” She let out a sigh. “I’ve attempted to make your return as easy as I could.”

“I didn’t mean this to be a return,” replied Amaryllis. “I was coming to Anglecynn to wash my hands of the family.” This wasn’t quite a lie.

“You think I’m a monster for letting you be dropped into the land of the dead,” said Rosemallow. Somehow she made that sound ridiculous, as though it was not only naive, but petty to be offended.

“I’ve never thought you were a monster,” said Amaryllis. “I always had trouble understanding what it was you actually cared about though. If you had the power to reshape Anglecynn exactly as you pleased, I don’t know what you would decide on. So much of your time and efforts are spent on the family, so little on legislative policy, and when you speak of laws, it’s always in the context of the major players in the kingdom, what they’ll think, how they’ll be forced to react, never in terms of how much good you might be able to do. But no, not a monster.”

“You’ve grown,” replied Rosemallow with a nod. “I must say, I approve. I do worry that your naivete has deepened and hardened, crystallized, rather than being sanded away. I plan to work with you though, to help you understand the errors of your ways, where appropriate.”

“I don’t want to work with you,” said Amaryllis. “I don’t want to be your niece.” It felt good to say that, but the good feeling was undercut by the knowledge that this was just part of the conversation, an invitation for Rosemallow to riposte with an offer of aid or support. The eventual compromise they would reach was already leaving a bitter taste in Amaryllis’ mouth.

“Let us imagine that I agreed,” said Rosemallow. “Imagine that you go visit with Hyacinth later today, invest the many entads she’s collected in the people she’s chosen, sign over the rights to various properties, and then become sterilized with an agreement that you won’t ever have natural born children of your own. In exchange, the ongoing difficulties you’re having with the Draconic Confederacy are minimized, if not wiped away completely, and you become a citizen in good standing with the kingdom once more. Ignore for a moment that this is a horrible deal for you. Do you imagine that you would be free of Hyacinth? Free of the rest of the family?”

“If I could buy myself a year or two, I would be able to accrue enough power to fend off anyone who tried to bring me back in,” said Amaryllis.

“There is no amount of power that will insulate you from the people you care about,” said Rosemallow. “There is an amount of power you might achieve to prevent your perceived enemies from destroying that which you love, so long as you don’t love too much. I’m skeptical of any plan that would launch you toward becoming one of the most powerful creatures on Aerb in so little time, as highly as I think of you.”

“Make your offer then,” said Amaryllis.

Rosemallow sat back and crossed her legs. “I want you to return to your rightful place as a princess of Anglecynn,” replied Rosemallow. “You would of course keep your seat as advisor to the Republic of Miunun, along with whatever projects you have there, splitting your time between locations. We would need to do something about the cost and travel time, but that’s hardly insurmountable given the potential resources at your disposal. Your proposed concessions to Hyacinth would be scuttled, though perhaps with some minor concession to her, not an admission of wrongdoing on your part or rightness on hers, but a gift to a grieving widow. In exchange for all that, you would become one of the public faces of the Lost King’s Court.”

“It’s what you always wanted me to be,” said Amaryllis. It seemed like a lifetime ago that she’d posed for the Future Leaders of Anglecynn posters. There had been radio interviews, a few letters to the editor, and appearances on a few variety shows.

“Toiling away in a back office doesn’t play to your strengths,” replied Rosemallow. “The Court has image problems, ones which are getting worse as time goes on, both within our kingdom and outside of it, for different reasons. That image needs to be rehabilitated, and you are the best one to do it, so long as you can keep your focus.”

“My focus was never the issue,” said Amaryllis. “The issue was that I had different priorities from the rest of you. I was only concerned with power as a means to an end, a way to help people less fortunate than I was.” It was the kind of thing only a raging narcissist wouldn’t question about themselves, but Amaryllis delivered the line with conviction.

“I’m gifting you power,” said Rosemallow. “Power with strings, certainly, but you would have plenty of leeway to pursue your agendas, to speak truth to power, or whatever else you’d like to do, so long as it’s in the best interests of Anglecynn. Surely you have to realize that I’ve handed you quite a bit of power simply by making your diaries the most talked about book in the kingdom?”

“It’s conditional power,” replied Amaryllis. “The book gives a context to everything I do in public. You made an image for me, one which I’m now beholden to.”

“They’re your words,” said Rosemallow.

“Edited,” replied Amaryllis. “With some choice cuts, I would assume.”

“You haven’t read it?” asked Rosemallow, raising an eyebrow. “You should. People will want to talk about it, and you’ll need to familiarize yourself with what’s in there. I made fewer cuts than you might expect, and added almost nothing. You had a gift for essays even from a young age, and there are a number of concepts that I believe it would be very beneficial for the citizens of Anglecynn to hear explained by a particularly bright twelve-year-old. There are sophomoric ruminations on the burdens of power and the complexity of change that might help pave the way for deeper understanding among the public simply because they’re accessible, written without the depth of knowledge a proper philosopher might possess.”

“And when did you embark on that particular project?” asked Amaryllis. “When you thought I was dead? Or after you discovered that I was still alive?”

“The diaries were meant for consumption,” said Rosemallow. She took her cup of coffee and drank down the rest of it with perfect form, never tipping her head back too far or opening her mouth too wide. When you were a noble, this was all expected of you, that you do everything just so, with decorum and grace. It wasn’t a view that the entirety of the court shared, especially in the younger generations, but it was how Amaryllis had been trained, even before her mother died.

“There are things I left out,” said Amaryllis. “I thought that someday I might want to show it to someone, and I wanted it to reflect the sort of person that I wanted to be, rather than the person that I was. It was mine to do with as I pleased, not yours.”

“I did, in fact, think it likely that you’d died,” said Rosemallow. “The diaries were found in the course of liquidating your staff, mentioned by a housekeeper.”

“Which one?” asked Amaryllis.

“Elanor,” replied Rosemallow. “I don’t believe it was a lack of discretion on her part, but rather a desire that some measure of you would be preserved. I’ve kept tabs on your staff, should there be any of them you want back. In my opinion, it would be best to make offers to only those of particular competence or loyalty. This has been an enormous disruption in their lives.”

“You’re framing it as though I’m coming back,” said Amaryllis. “That’s not decided. I’ve made a life for myself, away from this kingdom. A good one.”

“Is it true that two dragons touched down on the Isle of Poran?” asked Rosemallow.

“You know they did,” said Amaryllis. “I know you have spies there.”

“One or two,” replied Rosemallow, smiling slightly, in the way she did when she wanted to make a joke rather than answering a question or admitting to something.

Amaryllis was tempted to say out loud that there was only one, and to give his name to Rosemallow, as a demonstration of just how good her intelligence services on Poran were, or had been, when Valencia had been available to go down into the village. That would be foolish though, and if they’d somehow missed one, a display of weakness.

“Then yes, there were dragons,” said Amaryllis. “As you well know. Not, so far as I understand it, because of Hyacinth, and only tangentially related to the alleged violation of airspace that occurred in Li’o. It’s not something that I need help with.”

“These are two of the most dangerous creatures in creation,” said Rosemallow. “What life do you lead now that you would deny freely offered help?”

“It’s not freely offered,” replied Amaryllis.

Rosemallow sighed. “Again we circle back to your ideas of me, and of the Court, and what your role within it has to be. It’s tiring, I must say. I used to have more patience for these conversations. Think what you will of me, but I’m perfectly capable of offering aid to those in need. Even if I hope or expect that the aid will be reciprocal, or at least appreciated, it’s still offered without preconditions.”

“I won’t reject you outright, not the offer to help with the dragons, and not the bigger offer of a managed return to Anglecynn,” said Amaryllis. She focused on her tone, firm but gentle, without the shading of anger she felt. If she were letting her emotions control her, she’d be speaking with gritted teeth. “I need to speak to my people before I make any decisions, and I need a better understanding of what’s going on in the kingdom.”

“You have precious little time,” replied Rosemallow. “You’re a wanted criminal for violating the terms of the trial by adversity, and there are limits to what I can do to protect you, especially once Hyacinth and Phlox start their counterplay. My ability to insulate you increases by an order of magnitude if I can be sure that you’re willing to have a future in this kingdom.”

“You’re willing to spend more if you think that you’ll have me for good,” said Amaryllis.

“I am,” replied Rosemallow. “That should come as no surprise to you. But if you agree to be a part of this kingdom, to be allied with me once more, I can start on the negotiations at once, and the sooner the better. There are also a number of benefits to a quick decision, such as capitalizing on the positive reception of your diaries and breathing new life into the discussion of them.”

“I still need to talk to my people,” said Amaryllis. It was easy to get swept up in plans. Amaryllis could see all the things that would need to be done if she were to follow down the path Rosemallow had set up for her, and she was thinking of new items to add to her to-do list. But it was clear that everything Rosemallow wanted and expected would be fundamentally incompatible with what life with the Council of Arches had been like thus far.

“Is that really Raven Masters with you?” asked Rosemallow. She seemed genuinely curious, but Amaryllis had little doubt that Rosemallow could fake genuine curiosity. It was also a diversion from the previous topic of conversation, which was surely not because Rosemallow was expressing idle wonder. If someone dug in their heels when you were trying to sell them something, it was a common tactic to beat a conversational retreat and try again later.

“What do your spies, seers, and auguries say?” asked Amaryllis. This was only a little bit of an exaggeration. Rosemallow was sometimes known to have information she shouldn’t have, enough so that it was rumored she was in possession of a powerful entad, a highly synergistic entad set, or possibly a hidden magic. Magic that allowed for any form of future sight, prognostication, or clairvoyance was incredibly rare, but ‘incredibly rare’ didn’t mean non-existent.

“There are questions, certainly,” replied Rosemallow. “I don’t expect you to divulge everything, not when we’re working toward a reconciliation. However, if there’s anything that I should be prepared for, anything that would cost you little to reveal, I would appreciate foreknowledge so that I can launch a better defense or attack, as circumstances warrant.”

Amaryllis nodded. It would mean ceding authority to Rosemallow, and there was an implication that Amaryllis would help later, but it was a sensible offer even if Amaryllis chose to leave Anglecynn behind. Rosemallow was also right that it was better now than later. If the battle was being waged through private conversations, as these battles often were, it was better that Rosemallow’s people be able to answer the insidious gossip with a united front, especially in those places where the gossip had a grain of truth.

“I can tell you what Hyacinth knows or suspects,” said Amaryllis. Better Rosemallow had that information than not, most likely. “To start with … I suppose by this point you must be aware that we’d established a research base in Silmar City, and that in the weeks prior to my trial, that research site went silent, concurrent with a time when they’d been sent one of the kingdom’s teleportation keys?”

Rosemallow narrowed her eyes. “I am very aware, and was aware even before your trial,” she replied. “There was a lengthy closed-door inquiry into how that happened. The research project was exposed to the wider Court, but its nature and the details of its creation have been kept internal for now. Project Aubergine Stake has, I doubt you’ll be surprised, died in its crib, as has the entirety of Project Garden Stake. The teleportation key has remained unclaimed, despite two missions there, one of which was successful in reaching the research base.”

“Larkspur sent a fireteam to retrieve it,” said Amaryllis. “He did this without the knowledge of anyone else, at least so far as I can gather. Their mission was to retrieve the teleportation key, but when the Fuchsia Coterie reported back that they had failed to eliminate me, the fireteam was tasked with killing me if they found me. It’s not clear to me how Larkspur knew that I was going to Silmar City for the key, or if he was just hedging, but those were their orders.”

“And how do you know this?” asked Rosemallow.

“My companion, Juniper, killed two of them. Another woman, a half-elf and former prisoner of Anglecynn, was a part of the fireteam and local guide, coerced into joining and fitted with a Fool’s Choker. She killed the other two members.” Amaryllis kept her voice even. “I don’t know how much of that Larkspur or Hyacinth ever knew, or how much was discoverable after the fact, but those are the events as they happened. We left a fair bit of evidence behind, as we had no choice in the matter, but I doubt much of it would be recoverable, and it would be largely circumstantial.”

“Where is the teleportation key now?” asked Rosemallow.

Amaryllis had known that the question was coming. If Rosemallow had the diaries, then she almost certainly had the logs, passed down since long ago, which listed all the caches bound to Amaryllis’ bloodline, squirrelled away for future use or left abandoned because of exclusions. Notably absent from those logs would have been a transportation entad in Silmar City, or indeed, a cache anywhere in the Risen Lands. The current party line was that they had never used a teleportation key at all, just a different powerful travel entad left by Uther, but if you were Rosemallow, and had access to the logs of the location and nature of those entads, the lie would raise some questions.

“If I knew where it was, I would have put it somewhere safe,” said Amaryllis. “Entad storage, for example, keyed to me and me alone.”

“We need it back,” said Rosemallow. “Its utility in the hands of a single person is limited, and the political ramifications of the missing key have been severe. If it could be recovered —”

“Larkspur and Hyacinth believed we had it,” said Amaryllis. “They made some sort of agreement with Doris Finch in order to track us, using an unknown, possibly entadic magic in her possession. My team killed Larkspur and his soldiers just outside of Boastre Vino, with no surviving witnesses.”

Rosemallow paused for a moment, saying nothing, merely having a mild look as she tried to process that. Long ago, when Amaryllis was still a girl, Rosemallow had said that if you needed time to think, you should take it, as silence was often preferable to saying the first thing that came to mind, especially in those cases where meaningless conversational noise might not be warranted. In the entire time they’d known each other, this had been the only time that Amaryllis had seen Rosemallow follow her own advice.

“I see,” she finally said. “I may be obligated to repeat that, or take action on it.”

“I was warned,” said Amaryllis with a nod. “If you’re wondering why Hyacinth would keep it quiet, it’s because it’s currently to her benefit.”

“Do you have proof that he worked with Doris?” asked Rosemallow.

“No,” replied Amaryllis. “No concrete proof, only eyewitness accounts.”

“Well,” said Rosemallow. “You’ve given me quite a bit to think about. I had suspected that you might be responsible for Larkspur, but I couldn’t fathom the mechanism, or what you might have leveraged to make it happen. I’ll get into consultation with my public relations office. Thank you for your candor.” She paused. “I’m curious about what happened in Li’o, if you would be willing to share. You spoke with Hyacinth there.”

Amaryllis gave the highlights from there, filling in some gaps in what Rosemallow’s intelligence network might know. Some of the questions Rosemallow posed were surely to conceal how much she actually knew, which is what Amaryllis would have done, but it was mostly forthright, an exchange of information that was unlikely to hurt Amaryllis. Rosemallow wasn’t an ally, nothing like it just yet, but there were still bound to be fair exchanges to be had, ones which didn’t require them to trust each other. The teleportation key was the biggest liability that had been revealed, and it had already been revealed to Hyacinth, who was sure to use it against them if she could, especially because Larkspur was dead, and thus a useful scapegoat.

Bethel was mentioned, only briefly, as a powerful meta-entad, though her sentience (and cruelty) was left out. Valencia wasn’t mentioned at all, and neither was Solace, nor the locus. Juniper was given only brief focus, and Amaryllis stonewalled any questions about Raven, whose presence had no adequate explanation.

Rosemallow took it all in stride, stopping sometimes to think, but not expressing much in the way of shock or surprise. Some of it she’d already known, surely, especially because intelligence networks inevitably leaked to each other.

“Well,” said Rosemallow. “It’s a lot to think about, and you’re telling me only half of what you know. If you decide that you want to stay here, to take the mantle of princess back up, we’ll have to talk further about the things you’re keeping hidden.” She folded her hands in her lap. “One day, no more, to make your decision, and even then, I can’t guarantee that I can or will protect you if you should put yourself in a position to be arrested. It would be better for you to stay here for the duration.”

“I’ll speak with my people,” replied Amaryllis. “We have more than a dozen at the Hotel Delzora.”

“That still leaves the risk of you getting arrested,” said Rosemallow. “I don’t know how Hyacinth is planning to pardon you or waive the conditions of the trial by adversity, if she is at all, but until that’s resolved, there’s very little protecting you. I arranged for your safe landing at the station and your escort here, but you would complicate things enormously if you were taken in. There are limits to how much procedure can be bent.”

“Understood,” replied Amaryllis. “We’ll do our best to be discreet.”

Hilbert's Paradox

It was only about three minutes into Amaryllis’ meeting with Rosemallow that I realized that our problem of having only a single copy of The Princess Diaries, copied into Raven’s bracer, should actually be pretty easy to solve. All I had to do was call for the butler, who brought me one from the library so quickly that I felt like he must have been anticipating the request.

“This reads oddly,” said Raven, looking up from her magical copy.

“We’d expect it to,” I replied. “It was written with the public in mind.”

“Are you muting this conversation to the outside?” asked Raven.

“Yes,” I replied.

“We were explicitly looking for books written by Amaryllis,” said Raven. “Why did we never find this one?”

“There was a publication date component to the schema,” I replied. “For most of our search, we were looking for books that were as far in the future as we could get. And you know as well as I do that a large publication wouldn’t necessarily mean that we were bound to run across it.”

“Do the calculations,” said Raven, shaking her head. “So far as we can tell, A Cypress Waits was ‘published’ once every year in a new edition with only two copies. This book was published last week, maybe a little prior to that to give logistics time to get it into stores. There would be, optimistically, ten thousand copies.”

“Sorry,” I said. “I don’t know what math I’m supposed to be running here.”

“Hartman’s Theorem?” asked Raven.

“I’ve forgotten almost everything I’ve ever learned about library magic,” I replied.

“Oh,” said Raven. “Right. It’s just … we had a conversation about it. You understood it all.”

“I have a vague recollection of that,” I replied. “But I was cheating, skating by on what my power provided me with.”

“I know that,” said Raven. “I just hadn’t been struck by it. How profound it is, to lose something that you had such a talent for. Profound for me, I guess, not for you.”

“Yeah,” I replied. “Sorry you don’t have anyone to talk library stuff with anymore.”

“It’s fine,” said Raven. “I just … had some questions that I’ll have to work out on my own.”

“It’s also possible that things were different in the other timeline,” I said. “Either the butterfly effect or some kind of meddling. If I have the timelines right, then the book should have been in the works when we went into the Library, but there are a dozen small changes that might have happened to prevent its publication. I mean, it’s not just for want of a nail we’re talking here, given that there was an exclusion of one of the major magics not too long ago.”

“I suppose,” said Raven. “Did Amaryllis ever mention this diary to you?”

“No,” I replied. “Uh. You think that this is the Outer Reaches? Something inserted into our reality after the fact?”

“No, not really,” sighed Raven. “Uther always accused me of seeing the magical in the mundane. We never had a time when the schloss were a part of our own lives, only the lives of others. I’ve been waiting for the Outer Reaches to crop up since you were let in on the idea. But she never mentioned the diaries?”

“Not that I can recall,” I replied. “I also don’t think that there were any times when she would have had cause to mention them, at least that I can remember, but we’ve been together for a long time, and there have been lots of conversations. I’m also under the impression that the schloss are bigger in nature, like … I don’t know, each being a whole,” I gestured vaguely, “Module.”

“Module, in the tabletop sense?” asked Raven. “I’ve read a few.”

“Oh, right,” I replied. “Then yes, like poorly integrated modules, or more pertinently, ideas that were thought up by me when we were halfway through the campaign instead of being planned out from the start.” I paused a little. “How much material have you read?”

“On tabletop games?” asked Raven. “Seven source books cover-to-cover, another twenty or so in pieces, and a half dozen modules, plus almost all of the accumulated notes that Amaryllis had. I think it gave me a better understanding of you.”

“I didn’t really run things by the books very often,” I replied.

“I know,” said Raven. “But I could look at treants as they appeared in the Monster Manual, and treants as they appear on Aerb, and see some of you in the difference.”

“Ah,” I replied. I looked down at the diary. “I’ll probably have to have a chat with Amaryllis about that feeling of being exposed for the world to see.”

“Yes,” said Raven. She returned to her book without further comment, and I was left there multithreading, reading the book with one mind while I tried to understand the cadence and tone of that ‘yes’ with the other mind. Raven had been (and arguably still was) more famous than either of us, and you could find a few biographies of her on the bookshelves in the libraries of Aerb, even if those biographies represented guesswork rather than her own personal thoughts.

We left Erstwhile Manor almost as soon as the meeting was done, heading back for the Hotel Delzora in order to regroup with the rest of our team. Amaryllis wasn’t comfortable speaking about what had been discussed out in the open, despite my vibration powers, and only mentioned that a deal was on offer, one that she had a number of reservations about. The three princes who had escorted us were nowhere to be seen on our trip to the hotel, but I was pretty sure that we’d be seeing them again later, unless the Dungeon Master was such a dick that he would show me someone carrying around something as ridiculous as a bucket of shurikens and then not let me see their unique magic in action.

The Hotel Delzora was an entad structure, a hotel whose defining feature was that it had an infinite number of rooms, with the number of guests limited by practical considerations such as the time needed to walk to the further rooms and how much foot traffic could realistically pass through the corridors during peak hours. Rooms refreshed themselves at three in the afternoon every day, tidying themselves up, replacing consumables, and repairing any damage, with a few magical restrictions in place to prevent the worst abuses (no taking anything out of the hotel, for example). Still, ‘hotel’ was a bit of a misnomer, because most of the people who stayed at the Hotel Delzora lived there full time, paying a monthly rent, with no other home. Some of the more distant rooms were also used as storage space, which you didn’t often see in real hotels. From the outside, it was three stories tall with an opulent facade. Inside, the lobby stretched up into the sky until the view was obscured by the air.

The Hotel Delzora wasn’t the nicest hotel in Anglecynn, but it certainly was the biggest, and also the cheapest, if you were up for a hike.

Amaryllis handled the transaction, and I looked around, taking in the place. It wasn’t the first entad building that I had been in, but it was one of the weirder ones, in part because it was one of those entads that had more applications than the one it was clearly intended for. The receptionist had a wall of keys behind her, one that could move around, sliding back and forth to reveal more keys. There were presumably infinite keys, but there were likely limits on how much work the receptionist was willing to do to find a very distant room key. Most of the key hooks I could see were missing keys, instead having little notes about who was staying where, or what was in the room.

“There are tracks for elevators,” I said to Raven, pointing over to a bank of rails and their lit buttons. “But no elevators?”

“There used to be,” replied Raven. “The elevator didn’t have an infinite number of buttons, it had a method for you to punch in any arbitrary floor. One day someone, it’s unknown who, sent all of the elevators up to some arbitrarily high floor. That was twenty years ago. They’re all still traveling up.”

“But … why would someone do that?” I asked. “Just to be a dick?”

“There are competing interests in Anglecynn,” Amaryllis said as she approached us. She’d been too far away to hear us in normal circumstances, but she had vibration magic too. She had a small basket full of keys. “The hotel was owned by a branch of the family for a time, until eventually it fell into private hands. There were other landlords, the hotelier’s guild, and some intense competition. No one knows who sent the elevators up, but there are some good guesses. It didn’t make the hotel unusable, it just put some limits on how usable it is.”

“Couldn’t they just put in new elevator cars, retrofitted to the old system?” I asked.

“Assume that people have tried whatever you’re thinking,” said Amaryllis.

“Or assume that it’s a failure of civilization,” said Raven. “Not to be a misanthrope about it.”

“Possible,” said Amaryllis. “Now let’s go, we have a hike ahead of us.”

The front desk controlled the keys, which allowed them to set the prices. The biggest thing you paid for when picking a room to rent was convenience: a room on the ground floor, close to the front desk, was effectively no different than any other hotel in Caledwich, and in this case, located fairly close to the downtown area. If you instead selected a room which was nine floors up and a half-mile walk down a corridor, you could get your key for much cheaper.

We were up on the thirty-ninth floor, more than two miles down the eastern wing, past the rooms that looked down into the lobby, where there were only the lights that dotted the endless hallways. There were a few reasons for going so high and so far. First, it was obscure, and second, it was defensible. As we got to the top of the steps, we saw two of the tuung beside the balcony, one looking out over the edge to see what was going on down below in the lobby with a pair of pseudo-entad binoculars that I’d made using ink magic on the airship, while the other was watching the stairs. We were probably the only people so high up, but we had quite a way to go until we actually got to our room.

“How are the binoculars holding up?” I asked the tuung who was using them. (His name was Brian. I knew a fairly large number of the tuung by name, including all of those that had come on the airship with us, but it didn’t come up often.)

“Good,” he replied without looking at me. “No signs of degradation yet.” There was a good reason for him not to look at me; when I’d been making the binoculars, I’d decided that the way they would work was that they would grab onto the eyeballs when you got them close to your face. They prevented you from looking at close things unless you spent some time unlatching them.

(Ink magic was, at the heart of it, just a matter of making up magic items. They were entad-lite in a lot of ways, and shoddy enough that you’d almost always rather have a proper entad, or maybe even just a mundane piece of equipment, but I’d taken to ink magic like a fish to water, and not in the same accelerated way that I did with other skills, but with true, natural aptitude. The trick was in making things artful, spontaneous and playful, or awe-inspiring, or cool, and to do it over and over again without it getting stale or overstaying its welcome. I’d burnt myself out over the course of a day trying to push it with a suit of armor and a weapon for each of ten tuung fire teams: by the time the sun was going down, my results were dogshit, because even if I focused away from armor that would, say, stop a rifle round, it was a struggle to figure out something that wasn’t derivative or lazy. I was also limited by i-factor, a nebulous concept that roughly mapped to power, but knowing which magic items were level-appropriate was thankfully a skill that I had a lot of experience with.)

We left the tuung to guard and made the trek down the hallway. I watched as the numbers on the doors we passed incremented up, the print getting smaller once they went from four digits to five. When we finally got to room 39-812, there were two tuung waiting for us, standing guard, and after some brief pleasantries and confirmation that nothing remotely suspicious had happened, we went into the room that had been designated as the ‘war room’.

The rooms at the Hotel Delzora were all one size, spacious enough that you probably wouldn’t complain about sleeping there for the night, but small enough that they weren’t really fit for big meetings. This one had a double bed, which had been overturned and pushed up against a wall, but it still felt like too many people in too small a space.

“Status?” Amaryllis asked Grak.

“We’ve put up a ward past the eight hundreds,” said Grak. “Also, the clerk wasn’t happy that I was renting so many rooms. It might have drawn attention.”

“We won’t be staying here long,” replied Amaryllis. “A few days, probably not more. I had a house in Caledwich that should have been held in the same trust that Hyacinth is trying to take, but at this point I have to assume it’s compromised. There are also a few rental properties, but they’re in use, managed by a company that will have been held in the trust, and possibly also watched.”

“I’m not sure that such a long hike was necessary,” said Pallida. “And checking out so many different rooms seems a bit paranoid to me, especially because we’re not actually using any of the rooms we checked out.” Pallida was a master at picking locks, and the ones at the hotel were middling at best. We’d gotten a lot of keys from the front desk, but were using none of them.

“It might be paranoid,” Amaryllis admitted. “But if things go bad in a hurry, the Hotel offers a lot in the way of security through obscurity. There are also a lot of choke points for wards. I’m hoping that it won’t come to that. At any rate, our choice of base aside, we need to talk about the future, and what’s going to happen in Anglecynn. Rosemallow made me a seemingly generous offer to return to Anglecynn in my capacity as a princess, ideally as the public face of the Court. She wants an answer within a day.”

“And you’re asking our advice?” asked Grak, folding his arms.

“No,” said Amaryllis. “You’re all stakeholders, to one degree or another. Obviously advice would also be welcome, but the reason that I wanted to talk it over here before committing to any particular course of action was because I’m not the only one who would be impacted.”

“Which way are you leaning?” I asked.

“Toward,” replied Amaryllis. “I was, not to put too fine a point on it, fantastically wealthy when I was a princess. I was wealthy enough that it sometimes sickened me. All my funds, lands, and entads are currently held in trust. If Rosemallow was willing to fight on my behalf to get them back, it would mean not only the ability to inject a substantial amount of money into the Republic of Miunun, but also a fair bit of power added to the party as a whole. There are four hundred eighty-six heirloom entads bound to me, and two hundred thirty-seven of them can be invested or otherwise shared. Not all of them are powerful, but we’re not as completely dressed as a party as we might be, especially not the tuung.”

“The downside is that you’d be obligated to spend time here,” I said. “You’d get wrapped up in court politics, almost inevitably, and you’d be splitting your time and energy between at least two places, or three, if we include adventuring.”

“Anglecynn isn’t the goal,” said Raven. “Miunun isn’t either. It’s not clear at this point what the goal actually is, but we’re operating under the premise that an assault on Fel Seed is going to be a part of it, in order to find out once and for all where Uther is and why he left, and possibly to rescue him.”

“Sorry, what exactly did you get arrested for in the first place?” asked Pallida. “From the start this was all about … moving some money around?”

“It’s really not important,” replied Amaryllis. She paused for a moment, seeing whether that would stick. She’d told me back when we’d first met, but it was so painfully boring that I hadn’t paid much attention. It was only after I’d known her for awhile that it occurred to me that she might have given a boring description on purpose. “The Lost King’s Court is composed of a number of councils which oversee various parts of the kingdom. My formal title was Liason on Existential Emergencies, which meant quite a bit of interface with the Empire, but in addition to that, I had a seat on a few of the councils, which gave me some different sets of power depending on my role within those councils. For the most part, it was advisory power only, which is to say, I was being trained for eventually having more responsibilities, but in two of the councils, I had access to funds allocation. As sometimes happened in the Court, I used my powers of funds allocation to move the kingdom’s money around in ways that weren’t authorized by the councils in question, and arguably went against the kingdom’s law. The biggest difference here was that I had an inquiry launched against me, and when it came time for a trial, the panel was stacked against me. They pushed for trial by adversity as a remedy against what I had done.”

“But what were you funding?” asked Pallida.

“Does it matter?” asked Amaryllis with an exasperated sigh. “There was a collection of pilot programs relating to early childhood education and long-term welfare outcomes. Projects that had long time horizons and costs that needed sinking. That’s it.”

“No,” said Raven. “There’s something that you’re not telling us.”

Amaryllis gave her a hard stare.

“Did the outcome of your trial have something to do with Project Garden Stake?” asked Raven.

Amaryllis closed her eyes. “That’s classified,” she said.

“You’ve broken Anglecynn’s classification rules before,” I replied. “What is Project Garden Stake? It sounds familiar.”

Amaryllis grimaced. “I said the phrase when we were talking to Lisi, to see whether she either had codeword clearance or whether the project had become widely known in Anglecynn. Project Garden Stake was an attempt to utilize the exclusion zones, in contravention of both imperial laws and the laws of Anglecynn. The research facility in Silmar City was a part of Aubergine Stake. We had others in other exclusion zones. The project was technically started by my predecessor on the Exclusion Council, but I continued it with full knowledge that it was illegal, and without bringing it to the full council.” She turned from me and looked at Raven. “Project Garden Stake has nothing to do with the trial, except insofar as it made Rosemallow take a dim view of me as someone who refused to listen to her advice. The project’s high classification level meant that it couldn’t be brought before the panel trying to determine my guilt, not that it was germane to the question they were focused on.” She looked around the room. “Is that enough embarrassing backstory?”

“I didn’t mean anything by it,” said Pallida, holding up a hand. “I just wanted to know.”

“Well, one of the things that I’m not looking forward to, if I do come back, is endless apologizing and trying to explain something that happened years ago from my timeframe,” said Amaryllis. She looked unhappy, and I wished that I could do something for her, but saying ‘we can get the fuck out of Anglecynn if you want’ would have just pissed her off more, because what she wanted was to do the optimal thing.

One of the tuung cleared his throat. Now that I could use Soul Sight at will, any lingering problems with telling them apart were gone, because each had an aura with its own color, and because the ‘color’ wasn’t actually a color, there was no problem with shades being close to each other. This one was Liam, whip-smart and politically minded, who I had actually spent some time in committee meetings with back on Poran, where he’d talked about the opinions of the tuung on a second generation. He was wearing three items I’d made for him with ink magic: a pistol that fired cutlery, a suit of armor that would divert incoming objects downward, and a bandana that kept him moist without the need for a mister.

“The Council of Arches is approaching the point where it might not be able to reach quorum,” said Liam. “Your control of Miunun was always premised on the idea that control would degrade over time, but it’s reaching that point sooner than expected. Forgive me, but we’re already worried that we’re going to have to effectively replace the leadership of our nation with inexperienced members who are, frankly, not ready to do the job. I include myself among those members.”

“I understand,” said Amaryllis. “You’re the stakeholders that I care most about, because this undoubtedly affects you more than anyone else. I believe we have a strong foundation in place with regards to the technology initiatives and information exploitation, but even if I’m only spending a quarter of my time in Anglecynn, it will take away from our efforts in Miunun. That said, it’s the mark of a good organization that it can survive the loss of any one person, and I’ve done as much as was in my power to get Miunun to that place.”

”It’s a task that’s not yet accomplished,” replied Liam. “I understand that you’re worried about costs and capital, but it’s a temporary lack of funds weighed against a permanent lack of leadership. We were lucky to have been born with a purpose. We want to build into the industrial juggernaut that you planned for us to be. The early part of the venture is critical for a number of reasons. We don’t want to make mistakes that will become entrenched problems down the line.”

“I understand,” said Amaryllis. “Thank you for your input. The continued well being and prosperity of Miunun is my top priority. Unfortunately, we need to discuss some matters that are extremely sensitive.”

It was a veiled way of asking for him to get out, but Liam nodded immediately and left the room with the other tuung. They were close allies, but they hadn’t been read in on nearly everything, simply as a matter of operational security. I felt a little bad about that; they had already done a lot of work for us, and I was routinely offloading sleep to them.

“Do you want me to leave too?” asked Gemma. “I don’t know half of what’s going on.” The fox Animalia had come back from the Foxguard just before our ship had left Poran, but I hadn’t put much effort into speaking with her, and so far as I could tell, she’d mostly stuck close to Pallida. She still wasn’t fully recovered from the aging attack that Everett had sent against her, but she appeared to be aging backwards, and now, instead of grey, wrinkled fur, she seemed closer to late middle age, at least as far as I could tell. It seemed like an affliction we could do something about, but I hadn’t offered, mostly because it would mean asking for access to her soul.

“It’s complicated,” said Amaryllis. “We don’t have a good read on your loyalties at the moment, and the past few days haven’t clarified much, but I’m not sure that now is the time for that conversation.”

“I can take her into the next room,” said Pallida. “I have no real dog in this fight, other than to say, from what I know of them, fuck every single member of your extended family, no offense.”

“Noted,” said Amaryllis with a nod. “We’ll read in Gemma soon.”

“As a secondary point, I give her a middling vouch,” said Pallida.

“Middling?” asked Gemma, looking Pallida up and down with a critical eye.

“We can talk about it,” said Pallida. “We haven’t actually known each other that long.” Pallida put her arm around Gemma and led her from the room without much resistance.

“Alright,” said Amaryllis, once it was just what I thought of as the core team, myself, Amaryllis, Grak, Raven, and Solace. “Grak, Juniper, are we secured?”

“Reasonably,” replied Grak.

“Soundproof, at least,” I replied. “I can feel a whole lot of water around us, but detecting people is a crapshoot right now. Even if they’re relatively close it feels like it might just be a figment of my imagination.”

“There are also many ways around water magic,” said Grak.

“True,” I replied. “We’re clear on vibration magic too, no sounds going out, and I’m monitoring incoming. Anything more than that and I might not be able to give my full focus to this conversation.”

“Alright,” said Amaryllis, taking a breath. “Thoughts, in the context of everything we know?”

“Look, if you want to talk about narrative, then we can talk about narrative,” I replied. “If I had to guess what the Dungeon Master was doing, then I would guess that no matter what choice you make, it’s all going to blow up relatively soon. If you decide to side with Rosemallow, then Hyacinth is going to make a legitimate attempt at killing you, and it’s either going to be perfectly crafted to exploit our few weaknesses, or it’s going to be way overboard, or somehow involve hostages, or some other kind of bullshit. And if you decide that you’re going to have nothing to do with Rosemallow, instead renouncing your titles and going your own way, then it’s going to be Rosemallow we’re up against, trying to kill you because, I don’t know, she wants to make you into a martyr to further her aims. You’re beloved by the people of Anglecynn because your diaries tell them everything they want to hear, then you die in some accident or through backstabbing in the Court, and Rosemallow is there to talk about how much she loved you, and how you would want policy X, Y, and Z implemented post-haste. Does that scan?”

“It does,” nodded Amaryllis. “But I’m not sure how helpful making up just-so stories is, when we don’t know the specifics.”

“For my understanding of narrative, whatever choice is made will result in conflict, almost certainly violent in nature,” said Raven. “But if that’s true, then we don’t need to talk about the inevitable conflict at all, because it can just be assumed no matter what we do. Instead, we can talk in terms of our objectives.”

“Do you place no value on your family?” Grak asked Amaryllis.

“As a whole, if I was measuring them against the average person on the street,” said Amaryllis, weighing her words carefully, “I have some affection for certain parts of the Court, if not many of the people. At the extreme end, if I had heard that the Court had been put to death and Anglecynn had been completely reformed overnight, I would probably feel terrible about it. But what you would and wouldn’t feel terrible about shouldn’t be your guiding principle in life.”

“‘Do the objectively correct thing and worry about how you’re going to live with it later’,” I said.

“What’s that from?” asked Amaryllis.

“Your diaries,” replied Raven.

“Ah,” replied Amaryllis. “I’ll have to read them. I’m sure that I’m going to feel some embarrassment over the things I thought were exceptionally deep when I was fourteen. I do agree with the sentiment though.”

“I thought that I wouldn’t miss my family if they were gone,” said Grak. “There was a hidden comfort in knowing that there was a place where I belonged.”

“I’ve been trying to see things through your frame,” said Amaryllis with a nod. “It’s different though, substantially so, because it’s not as though I would be saying goodbye to Anglecynn forever, nor would the people be gone, I would just have a diminished presence in that world. I could still visit, if I chose. I could write letters. I could even impact policy from afar, if not as a princess. The question is what the correct course of action is.”

“That depends on what you want from your life,” said Solace.

“How much money is on the line?” I asked. I knew that Amaryllis had been rich, but I didn’t actually know how rich, and if money was going to be a concern, then it seemed prudent to ask.

“It’s complicated,” said Amaryllis. “There are bank accounts that have raw, easily moved money, there are stocks and bonds that could be cashed out at varying speeds while taking variable losses depending on how fast I wanted to go liquid, there are pieces of art, businesses, land holdings, all of which would take time to sell and whose value would depend on the whims of the market, there are entad investment rights, some of which are presumably still paying out, others that would need negotiation, there are ward bypass rights, and a host of others that are negligible contributors to my personal wealth. All held in trust at the moment, so far as I understand it.”

“But to put a number on it?” I asked.

“Last time I checked, it was one and a half billion obols,” replied Amaryllis. “That’s with a one year timeline for liquidation. If held, it’s more complicated, but the income would be on the order of three percent of worth, accounting for the costs of upkeep. If everything was mothballed, then perhaps as high as six percent.”

“Meaning between forty-five and ninety million obols a year,” I said. That seemed like a lot. It wasn’t wholly accurate, because you couldn’t construct equivalent market baskets, but I had been going off a ‘one obol is roughly one dollar’ rule of thumb for a long time. Amaryllis, on Earth, would have been making something like $120,000 a day, more money than I could put into any frame of comparison. I was pretty sure that my parents made less in a year.

“And you’re willing to give it all up to Hyacinth?” asked Raven. “What’s the current net worth of Miunun?”

“Incalculable, because its worth includes the people who are going to be citizens,” said Amaryllis. I frowned a bit at that, and she saw me. “It’s calculable in principle, but the error bars are so wide that it would be worthless for any practical purpose. The tuung are still very young, even if their diction and physiological appearance might make them seem older, and some of them are in training for jobs that don’t actually exist yet. To put a price on them would mean making assumptions about future earnings, quality of life, and other metrics that would have to be very crude guesses.”

“The only leverage that Hyacinth has over Miunun is a well-placed cousin in the Draconic Confederacy,” I said. “And Hyacinth only has leverage because she’s alive, which is something we could very easily rectify.”

“Juniper,” said Raven with a pronounced frown.

“She tried to have us killed,” I said. “She’s probably going to try again, whether or not we give in to her demands, because Amaryllis dying is the only way that she’s going to get the closest-female-relation-to-Uther entads, which are presumably worth a lot.” I paused. “Uther was sometimes proactive, rather than waiting for someone to explicitly come at him with a knife.”

“He was,” said Raven. “Usually he would wait for them to attack first though. He didn’t engage in assassination as a matter of course.”

“Well, his descendants didn’t seem to follow in his footsteps,” I replied.

“Assassination is not widespread within Anglecynn,” said Amaryllis. “But there have been a number of incidents, including my mother and myself, possibly also my father. Two or three cousins, a few more aunts and uncles, always punished harshly if it could be proven … but the types of people who have resorted to assassination have been careful to leave no evidence, if not to make it completely undeniable.”

“Alright,” I replied. “I guess I’m just pointing out that the only thing that disrupted the status quo we had going was Hyacinth coming in and using what leverage she had to put us in a position where she had to be answered, and answering her can mean a lot of different things. Rosemallow is one option, but surely she can’t be the only option aside from complete capitulation.”

“You’re right,” said Amaryllis. “There’s also the possibility of a counteroffer.”

“You would trust her?” asked Grak. He was frowning. Here, he was out of his element, not just because it was a matter of foreign politics, but because the way that Amaryllis was attempting to play politics was strange to him. Dwarves, he’d told me on the airship, did things differently.

“No, I wouldn’t trust her,” replied Amaryllis. “But as I was discussing with my aunt Rosemallow, you don’t always need trust to make a deal. At the very least, Rosemallow would likely have a discussion with Hyacinth prior to going to war, because wars cost money, even if they’re wars of perception or legislation.”

“Seems dangerous,” I replied. “Seems like the kind of thing that would lead to armed conflict if things went wrong, or even if they went right.”

“This is true,” said Amaryllis with a nod.

“But that might be what you want?” asked Raven.

“It might,” replied Amaryllis. She rubbed one hand against her forehead. “The estate was to be held in trust until after the trial by adversity, pending my completion of two years service in the Host if I managed to get out of the Risen Lands. Because I effectively deserted, they would normally hold a trial in absentia after trying and failing to get ahold of me, or after I had been served and didn’t show up.”

“Meaning that it’s possible the desertion thing might lead to a proper trial?” I asked. “Whatever the opposite of in absentia is?”

“In propria persona,” said Amaryllis. “And I would assume that Rosemallow would have something like that planned for me, where I would be allowed to argue that I feared for my life if I returned to Anglecynn … only the most likely outcome, if the rule of law is followed, is that I would then have to complete the two years with the Host, which I think we can agree is unacceptable.”

“Why is it?” asked Solace.

Amaryllis stopped for a moment. “Are you asking for rhetorical reasons, or because you actually think that it would be a good idea?”

“I’m asking because sometimes giving voice to the obvious is how we learn more about ourselves and our situations,” said Solace. I was happy that she seemed a bit more calm than in conversations past. She hadn’t brought up the locus yet either, which was a definite plus in my book.

“I would be away from the party for too long,” said Amaryllis. “Miunun might be able to stay in a holding pattern for two years with a huge injection of capital, though that obviously wouldn’t be ideal. But for the party, and for Juniper, two years would be an incomprehensibly long time. We’re at the rate of an adventure every two weeks, maybe a bit more depending on how you split them up and how you count time. There might be ways around that, depending on how my service in the Host is structured, but Onion heads up the Host, and I doubt that he’d be amenable to something like giving me a special position as a military liaison.”

I had known about Onion for months now, and it still blew my mind that not only was one of the most powerful people in Anglecynn called Onion by pretty much everyone, that was his actual given name. Onion Penndraig was in his late 60s, old and grizzled, a veteran turned commander that supposedly came by his position more honestly than members of the Court normally did. He was also notably a survivor of not one but two trials by adversity, as well as a seldom-used trial by combat. I had a lot of trouble taking him seriously, mostly because of the name. He was one of the people I was really curious to meet: my hope was that he had layers.

“So submitting to a trial might not be terrible,” said Grak.

“It depends,” replied Amaryllis. “I don’t know what Rosemallow has planned to get around it, if anything. I doubt that she would throw me into the Host like that, but I’ve been wrong about her before. It would be a way of keeping me chained, if she could keep me from being killed.”

“Alright,” I said. “So in terms of making a decision, which you were given a day for, what are you currently thinking?”

“I want a modified deal with Rosemallow,” said Amaryllis. “Something that doesn’t require much of me while still allowing me access to my estate, which would be liquidated as quickly as possible. I am limited to a tenth of the estate’s value before my 18th birthday, but by their reckoning that’s not for another few weeks. I might be able to get around that though, given that I did spend years in the time chamber. If possible … I could keep up with Anglecynn politics by mail. That’s not unheard of, given how far some of the Court stray from home. I wouldn’t be able to sit on a council, or at least not one of the active ones, but I could register votes in the General Council. I’m just not sure that we would gain Rosemallow’s aid with that kind of arrangement.”

“Well, then the next step is seeing what Rosemallow’s breaking point is,” I said. “Extract as much as possible from her. Better, get them both in the same room together and hammer out some kind of solution that works for both of them and lets you walk away.”

“Hyacinth doesn’t have ultimate control, or at least, she shouldn’t,” said Amaryllis. “Phlox and Onion will have been in conference with her about this. And I don’t think anyone involved is the sort to come to a mutual agreement that works for both parties, not when there are strong incentives to defect.”

“You will eventually have to make a decision on what to do,” said Solace. “I’ve been present for many of these conversations, and it feels like we’ve hit the point where we’ll spin our wheels for, oh, another hour or two. So if you’ll excuse me, I’m going to give the domain of the locus some sunlight.”

“I’ll go with you,” said Grak. “I do not need to be party to this. Tell me what you decide.”

“You have a stake,” said Amaryllis.

“I will put the wards where you tell me to,” said Grak. “I trust you. I will not place a vote.”

We were silent as they walked out of the room, leaving just me, Amaryllis, and Raven.

“I’m starting to feel like coming here was a waste of time,” said Amaryllis with a sigh. “It’s all politics, blah, blah, blah. I’m trying to sympathize with that, but ...”

“But it’s your life,” I replied. “It has personal meaning to you.”

“And what do you think?” asked Amaryllis.

“I think you should get your hands on as much money as possible while giving the absolute minimum amount of responsibility in return. Bribe Rosemallow, bribe Hyacinth, and get out with a nominal title of princess. I’m sure that you could do a lot of good as a princess, but you could do more good with the tuung, who are incredibly loyal to you, and who you’ve already implicitly promised to help.”

“Raven?” asked Amaryllis.

“I’m inclined to think this is a sideshow,” said Raven. “Based on what we know about Hyacinth, she’s sociopathic enough to call down all kinds of threats on us, even ones that she can’t fully control herself. She reminds me of a Hanno or a Polybur,” names I didn’t recognize, which Raven had in ample supply, “someone who acts as a thorn in our side without necessarily being all that threatening when just considering her personal power. That said, her personal power must have some limits on it, especially with her husband passed away. Giving her more funds increases the future threat, especially because she has no particular reason to leave you alone once she gets your money.”

“We did kill her husband,” I said. I bit my lip. “Not sure how much that would motivate what she does.”

“I don’t know either,” said Amaryllis. “Their marriage was arranged for mutual benefit, but I was raised to believe that true love could develop from that. It doesn’t help that there are utilitarian motives as well, I’m sure.”

“Do you think it’s worth talking to her?” I asked.

“So long as I reveal nothing, possibly,” said Amaryllis. “We would have to find a place where we’d both feel safe.”

“The White Room at Rosemallow’s?” I asked. “From what you’ve said about the practice of assassination, Rosemallow wouldn’t do it in her own house, unless I’m misunderstanding the standards of proof.”

“If Hyacinth had her warder go in, and we had Grak to watch him, maybe,” said Amaryllis. “But Hyacinth has to have realized by now that we’re not on an even playing field. We’re not even playing the same game. And I know she suspects something, because I accepted a deal that seemed too generous.”

“Then why accept that offer?” asked Raven.

“Because wiping my hands of Anglecynn is attractive,” said Amaryllis. “Because this is a quest that I don’t want to do, and whose outcome is entirely unpredictable given the Dungeon Master’s machinations. But the real disgust with Anglecynn and the Court also means that I can cloak my own intentions if need be. Accepting the offer throws Hyacinth off guard. And so long as the pretense of cooperation is in place, Hyacinth needs to hold off on offensive action, even if she doesn’t fully believe it, because the potential upside is so large. Besides that, it puts pressure on any counterparty, namely Rosemallow, to help coerce them into offering me what I want.”

“Well, let’s hope that when the hammer comes down, we’re ready to deal with it,” I said.

Dumbest Entad

The meeting between Hyacinth and Amaryllis took a lot of work, namely in the form of letters being sent back and forth. There wasn’t such a thing as neutral ground for the two of them, and the timescale we were requesting was incredibly compressed compared to what you’d want in order to have the logistics of the meeting worked out. Both of them needed a warder to make sure they were safe, and both needed security to come in and sweep the place for traps or surprises, as well as further defenses from all angles. Thankfully, our needs weren’t entirely uncommon within Anglecynn, and one of the rooms within Caledwich Castle met most of our requirements, though there were quite a few angles of approach, which made it a little worrisome from a defensive standpoint. That also ensured it would be hard to lay an ambush on the way in. Everything got squared away within twelve hours, which was insanely fast as these things went, at least by the impression that Amaryllis had given me.

“It will be just Grak and myself,” said Amaryllis. “That’s the easiest agreement, most in keeping with historical precedent. Hyacinth will have a warder of her own to make sure that we’re both defended. Juniper, you would ideally be with me, especially since you’re a secondary party to desertion, but that would require further deliberations, and we want to get this done quickly.”

“It’s fine,” I said. “If I’m part of the discussion at all, I trust you to represent my interests. I’m not too concerned about being a technical fugitive, in the scheme of things.”

We left the Hotel Delzora as a group, with a two mile hike back down the corridor, then a rather less arduous walk down to ground level once we’d confirmed with the tuung that there had been no one suspicious. We were a little bit on edge about police (sorry, guards) popping out from behind bushes and arresting us, which wouldn’t have been the worst thing, but definitely wasn’t a part of the plan. Once we were all on a tram together, I began to feel more secure, in the sense that I was watching out for an attack, but no longer expecting that it would happen.

Caledwich Castle had been Uther’s home for decades, though he was out and about, traveling and adventuring, for most of that time. It was the place his wife had spent almost all of her time, where his children had grown up, and where Pallida had briefly been a ward. I’d heard all sorts of things about it, and was kind of disappointed when it came into view, in part because I’d been so spoiled by how weird and magical Aerb normally was. Caledwich Castle was just a castle, one with perfectly normal castle features, a front gate and towers with arrow slits, machicolations and battlements, but nothing outsized or unique, nothing to mark it as a distinctly magical fantasy castle. You probably could have dropped it into medieval times and had no one bat an eye, save for what were probably a fair number of historical anachronisms. The castle had been added onto, both by Uther and his descendants, increasing its size considerably with new wings. A fair number of Penndraigs lived at the castle, which was one of the most secure places in Anglecynn, due to a number of magics that had been put in place by Uther, and it was something like holy ground for the Penndraigs, a place where everyone knew not to start shit. Uther’s wards still shielded the inner castle, and when we got off the tram and walked there, Amaryllis had to mark us all as guests.

Once we were inside, I was struck by how normal it all looked. Uther Penndraig had been through hundreds of adventures, across all of Aerb, but it seemed that he’d brought very little back with him. I had never been to a castle before, but I’d seen plenty of pictures, and the interior of Caledwich Castle wouldn’t have been out of place at all in an Earth history book. There were tapestries and heavy wooden tables, with the walls and floors made of thick off-white stone. There wasn’t a scrap of anything truly weird until we came across a pair of the Armateurs.

The Armateurs were entad-made, churned out by an entad that could make one every month or so. I had seen one back at Erstwhile Manor, but it was just one, and here there were lots of them. They were robots, or a magical equivalent to them, without all that much intelligence. In physical appearance, they were like suits of armor, but with limbs and torsos that were so slender they couldn’t possibly have held a person. Each had a long, thin sword that was part of their construction, which they would use when they were ordered to, or when something in their internal logic dictated they should. When Amaryllis began describing their rules, I immediately recognized them as Asimov’s Three Laws, though adapted so that ‘human’ was replaced with ‘Penndraig’ (not that ‘human’ would have been that much less problematic in a world like Aerb’s). They had been ‘programmed’ by Uther himself, with orders that could be worked within but not overridden, and more than once, the whole corps of them had sprung into action to defend Caledwich Castle. They were one of the reasons that the castle wasn’t a place to start shit.

Other than that one concession to safety and security, it was all exactly how medieval castles were supposed to look, which meant that it had been kept as it was during the time of the First Empire, or restored to that state sometime later. It made me a little bit sad for some reason, maybe because of the thought that this place wasn’t actually used by anyone anymore. It was the same melancholy I’d felt when we’d cleared out my grandma’s house to put her in a nursing home, because so much of what she’d owned had to be thrown away.

“Check your passion,” said Grak, keeping his voice low. As soon as he said it, I realized that the air around me had taken on a chill. Spontaneous passion magic wasn’t terribly uncommon among trainees, but I was at level 20 and should have had it more under control. I stopped the effect quickly, but keeping it from happening wasn’t automatic.

“Thanks,” I replied.

“We’re playing dangerous games,” he said. “Stay on your toes.”

I nodded at that. It was a bad moment to let my mind drift, even if I was multithreading and keeping watch with the other part of my mind.

We were a fair way into the castle when an elderly man wearing a robe and holding a jeweled staff came rushing around the corner. He raised his eyebrows on seeing us, then headed straight for Amaryllis.

“Cousin Amaryllis,” he said. “You’re early. I would have met you at the gates if you had told me you were coming before you’d said.”

“Cousin Sorrel,” replied Amaryllis with a short nod. “You understand that our situation is a bit fraught right now.”

“I have always tried my best to keep the peace,” replied Sorrel. “Are the guards going to come here to arrest you, do you know?”

“I don’t know,” replied Amaryllis, thin-lipped. “I don’t imagine that they would want to risk the displeasure of the Armateurs, nor the breaking of a sacred peace, even if someone were to let them past the wards.”

“No, I doubt they would want that,” said Sorrel. “But the Armateurs are also not meant to be used by fugitives, nor is this castle a refuge from the law.”

“I understand that,” said Amaryllis. “But surely you understand that the law is what we make of it, and so long as Hyacinth wishes to meet with me, Araluen will make sure that the guards are quietly positioned elsewhere. I won’t be arrested until someone feels it’s prudent for me to be arrested, and until there’s someone actively looking to arrest me, I don’t think I can properly be called a fugitive. When that time comes, I will, at the least, vacate this place.”

Sorrel scowled. “Very well,” he replied. He turned away from us and began walking. “The Mirror Room has been prepared, though I imagine you’ll want your warder to look it over. If you’ll permit me, I’d be happy to serve as your intermediary in this affair.”

“That won’t be necessary,” replied Amaryllis as she followed. “The fewer people with their interests involved in this, the better. I do appreciate the offer though. You’ve always been a principled man.”

Sorrel nodded, not seeming as put out as I would have expected. This wasn’t ‘his’ castle, because the wards let any Penndraig through, but he was the administrator of the grand building, the manager of its caretakers and the man who kept everything running. Caledwich Castle wasn’t quite neutral ground, but it was as close as we were going to get.

“If you and your warder will be in the Mirror Room for the duration, where will the others be?” asked Sorrel.

“As close as possible,” replied Amaryllis. “They’re backup in case anything goes wrong.”

“The Armateurs —,” Sorrel began.

“— are fallible,” Amaryllis finished for him. “There are dozens of ways to get around them, and dozens more ways to overpower them. I’m taking as few chances as I can.”

“Well,” said Sorrel. “I had supposed that would be the answer.” He stopped and gestured toward a thick wooden door with a wrought iron handle. “This is where they’ll be then, the Prince’s Room, which should be suitable. The Mirror Room can be accessed through it, one short hallway past the rightmost door. Good luck, Amaryllis.”

“Thank you,” replied Amaryllis, giving him a much more pronounced bow than when we’d first come across him.

The Prince’s Room had a bunch of furniture that was obviously expensive, the result of hundreds if not thousands of hours of skilled labor, evident in the elaborate embroidery and the gold plating that covered intricately carved wood. The walls were nearly covered in paintings, almost all of them young men, with the art styles varying considerably. Some of the older ones, with aged paint, were done in the exaggerated, almost caricature style that was popular in the First Empire, and I imagined that at least a few of the paintings of these presumed princes were of Uther’s two sons. There was a large window that pointed toward a courtyard, but little to see, and no other source of light. Three Armateurs stood in nooks along the wall.

“We’re close now,” said Amaryllis. “If this falls through, and does so in a way that’s not overtly aggressive, I suggest that we meet here and make a magical exit. Grak, are the wards permissive enough for that?”

“They are,” replied Grak, without elaboration.

“Good, then let’s get ready,” said Amaryllis, turning to Grak. “I want to make sure that we’re prepared.”

And with that, they left us alone to wait.

“Does this bring back memories for either of you?” I asked Raven and Pallida, wanting to get my mind off worrying about Amaryllis. Solace was with us too, but she had already withdrawn from the conversation, instead looking out the window with a blank expression on her face.

“The memories are vague,” said Pallida. “I was at Caledwich Castle for just a single lifetime, and not very much of one, from when I was younger. Normally I wouldn’t remember anything from when I was that age, given how old I am now, but I have memories of memories of memories. It was a more lively place back then, I can tell you that. Zona kept herself busy with an endless parade of courtiers.”

“Most business now is handled elsewhere,” I said with a nod. “Makes sense.”

“I have many memories,” said Raven. “Few of them were good, even before the good ones started to go sour.”

“Sorry,” I said. “I didn’t mean to make you feel bad.”

“It’s fine,” replied Raven. Her cloak rippled for a moment in the windless room. “There are places that I would like to see, if we somehow get the chance: my room in the castle, the Square Table, and the castle library. All changed immensely, I’m sure. There have been a number of additions to the castle since I lived here.” She paused. “I was promised to always have a room ready and waiting for me at Caledwich Castle, but I don’t suppose that promise has survived a dozen generations or more.”

“I don’t really understand why the castle had to be so big,” I replied. “They have a different building for legislation and meetings, and different offices for government business. Why keep adding new wings?”

“They wouldn’t want to admit it, but a lot of the Penndraigs are on the dole,” said Pallida. “You get a family that big, and some of them are going to end up destitute, for one reason or another. This is the place where they’re kept. It wouldn’t be a good look to have them in tenement housing. The inner castle is kept sterile though.”

“It’s more complicated than that,” said Raven. “Anglecynn is run by the Lost King’s Court, and rule isn’t exclusively relegated to those members who have obscene wealth. The Court considers it in their best interests to keep voting members in comfortable circumstances so they aren’t able to be easily bribed or manipulated, and so that there’s some homogeneity of circumstances, which helps the Court from being divided.”

“Right, got it,” I replied. “It’s Universal Basic Income, minus the Universal aspect of it. Makes sense.”

“I imagine that it’s a contentious issue among the nobility, as it was a hundred years ago, the last time I visited,” said Raven. “In fact —”

But whatever she was going to say died on her lips as the door into the Prince’s Room opened up and two young nobles stepped inside.

“Oh, sorry,” said one of them, a young man, probably not too much older than I was. He had dark red hair and a slightly chubby face, with armor made of what looked like carbonized wood. I flashed on soul sight and saw that while he was tinted mint green, his armor had the hue of a different soul, which meant that someone had invested it to him. At his hip was an aura, shaped like a sword in its sheath, but invisible to my normal sight. “I didn’t know this room was occupied.” He gave us a wholly disingenuous smile and stepped in, with his companion following shortly after him. As the door closed behind them, I caught a glimpse at Sorrel, giving a disapproving frown but making no move to intervene.

“This isn’t a social,” said Raven.

“Yes, yes,” said the (presumed) prince, “But the Prince’s Room is my favorite room, and I’m sure you don’t mind the company.”

“We do, actually,” said Pallida. Her eyes flickered to the Armateurs for just a moment, and her inky armor hugged her tighter, drawing up to her throat.

“All the same,” he replied. He took a seat on the fancy couch, next to Pallida, separated by the middle cushion.

“You’re Raven Masters,” said the princess. She wasn’t armored like he was, but with entads, that wasn’t saying all that much, since a frilly pink dress (which she was wearing) could easily have as much stopping power as fullplate. The entad was hers, but the handbag she wore must have been invested, and her high-heeled shoes were invested from a different source. Surprisingly, without soul sight on, it all matched, which was rare for someone with three or more entads.

“I am,” said Raven. “You should know that if you attempt any malfeasance, it’s going to end extremely poorly for you.”

“We weren’t even considering it,” said the prince. He placed his hand on his chest. “I’m Yarrow Penndraig, this is my sister, Zinnia.” I recognized the name Yarrow: he was one of Amaryllis’ ancestors, a distant one. Reusing names was pretty common among the Penndraigs, and it was probably just that, rather than immortality or time manipulation.

“Is there a reason you’re here?” asked Pallida.

“Just visiting,” replied Yarrow.

“Hyacinth sent us,” said Zinnia.

“Zin,” sighed Yarrow.

“They already know that,” replied Zinnia. “And this is Raven, she’s practically nobility herself. If the authority of the Court ultimately descends from Uther, then doesn’t that give her a place of prominence?”

“Not legally, no,” replied Raven. “Not that I would want it.”

“Why not?” asked Zinnia.

“Surely Hyacinth didn’t send you here to fawn over Raven?” asked Pallida. She gave Raven a slightly guilty look. “Not that she doesn’t deserve it.”

“Hyacinth just wanted someone to keep an eye on you, and we were willing and available,” replied Yarrow. He crossed his legs, which caused a horrible grating sound as charred wood rubbed against charred wood where his greaves touched each other.

“A fully armed and armored eye?” I asked, raising an eyebrow.

“You’re more armed than we are,” replied Yarrow. “And you have us outnumbered three to two.”

“Four to two,” replied Solace from the window without looking toward him.

“Crantek don’t normally have horns,” replied Yarrow, crinkling his nose at her. “Might I inquire?”

“They’re not horns, they’re antlers,” replied Solace.

“The difference being?” asked Yarrow.

“Antlers are bone, horns are keratin,” replied Solace. “There are other differences as well, but I’m not in the mood for a biology lesson.”

“I’m just curious how you came by them,” said Yarrow. “I recently finished up my five years at Speculation and Scrutiny, and I have an interest in obscure magic, if that’s what they are.”

Solace remained silent.

“Well,” said Pallida. “We can sit in stony silence for the next hour or two, or however long these negotiations take, or we can talk, but it should be clear to you that you’re not going to get anything from us.”

“Believe it or not, it’s honest curiosity,” replied Yarrow. “But if you don’t believe it, and you think that I have ulterior motives, then of course you can stay silent. There’s no reason to feel poorly about not answering an innocent question. And I really would hate to spend these hours in this company without actually talking, so long as we all have to be here.”

“We mean no offense,” said Zinnia. “And we’re hardly trained operatives.”

“What athenaeum did you attend?” I asked her, crossing my arms over my chest. “If you did.”

“Barriers,” replied Zinnia. “Yarrow and I both had a focus on entads, coming at it from different angles. My wand and monocle will stay in my pocket, for your peace of mind.”

“So if the four of you don’t want to talk about anything of consequence, then how about we play a game of dumbest entad?” asked Yarrow.

“I’ve never played,” I replied. I was paying attention to him with one thread and listening for Amaryllis using vibration magic with the other. The Mirror Room would be warded so that no one could listen in that way, but if there was some altercation, I was fairly certain that I would hear it as soon as Grak dropped the wards. I had heard Yarrow and Zinnia approaching, but whatever conversation they’d had with Sorrel, it had been too far and too muffled for me to hear. I wished I could have barricaded the door.

“Some entads are good, and some entads are bad,” explained Yarrow. “In the entad business, we call that i-factor, which is short for impact factor, a measure of how powerful that entad is when taking into account its abilities and restrictions. Here, obviously, I’m simplifying beyond belief a tool that’s itself designed for simplifying the wild and weird world of entads. But that’s just one axis that we can use, isn’t it? Another axis might be between whether entads are clever or dumb. The dumbest entad game is to think about the dumbest entads you know of, with the intent to narrowly one-up the other players.”

“Sorry,” I said. “Dumb in the sense of … poorly designed?”

“Not quite. You know Lisianthus,” said Zinnia. “I don’t mean to be rude, but we were given a short and, I’m sure, very incomplete briefing. She has an entad, a flute made of what looks to be bone. When you play the flute, it will make a pie, with the variety of pie depending on the tune played.”

I thought about that for a moment, then chuckled. “Ah, Pied Piper.”

“Beg pardon?” asked Yarrow.

“Pied Piper,” I replied. “It’s a story, or a fable, about a man who came to a town and lured the rats away with the songs on his pipe. When the town refused to pay his fees, he lured their children away. Of course ‘pied’ in the name just means ‘multicolored’, so here it’s used as a pun.”

Yarrow laughed, and it was the first time he’d seemed genuine. “Puns,” he replied. “Most of the entads I would call dumb are, in fact, puns of one kind or another. I hadn’t heard the story though. I’d thought it was just about making pies through music.”

“So in this game, does an entad created around a pun make it more or less ‘dumb’?” I asked.

“Definitely more dumb, I would think,” said Pallida.

“Agreed,” nodded Yarrow. “The more you scratch your head before getting it, or groan when you do get it, the dumber. If we had to define it, which we don’t, then maybe we would say that it was a mismatch of form and function, or perhaps a dollop of the absurd.”

“I suppose we could invent a new axis, confusing on one end and sensible on the other,” I replied.

“But then we’d be in three axes, and no one wants that,” said Yarrow with a smile. “At any rate, I’ve given my go, it’s your turn. Dumbest entad you know of?”

“Seems kind of unfair, given that you’re both entad specialists,” I replied. “But … alright, there’s that one that you pile books, letters, manuscripts, correspondence, and other written works around, and it brings forth its best extrapolation of the author, but instead of their usual form, it’s a giant aquatic dinosaur.”

“What’s a dinosaur?” asked Yarrow, narrowing his eyes.

“It’s Precursor Anglish,” replied Zinnia, frowning a bit. “It means terrible lizard. Quite archaic though.” I was hoping that eventually I would get a Language virtue that would let me stop the occasional missteps, but it wasn’t exactly a secret that I was dream-skewered. “Is that a pun of some kind?”

“The word dinosaur, or the entad?” I asked.

“The entad,” she replied.

“Not that I know of,” I replied. “Or if it is, I haven’t figured it out.”

“I’ll cede that it beats mine,” replied Yarrow with a nod. “But if you’re playing dumbest entad, you don’t start with your best. How about this one,” he cleared his throat with a theatricality that I found a little endearing, “The frog bow is a bow that shoots frogs. Any arrow you shoot with it will turn into a frog, going roughly the same speed as the arrow was, shortly after it leaves the bow.”

“Wow,” I said. “That’s bad and dumb. I assume arrows cost more than you’d make from selling frog meat and bones?”

“You would be correct,” said Yarrow with a nod. “But there were always ways around that. Historically, arrows were recovered after battles, and some fraction of them weren’t usable, which meant that they could be had for a fraction of the cost and fired from the frog bow. In the modern day, the same initially applied to factories, which created arrows in bulk, some of which weren’t high enough quality, and since the price of manufacture fell once you didn’t need a trained fletcher, eventually it became profitable for an arrow manufactory to make small batches of extremely low quality arrows, which could then be turned into frogs through an automated firing machine. It’s not as impressive as it sounds, because it’s just a bendable hook attached to a cam.”

“That’s not really the point of the game,” said Zinnia, frowning.

“Appreciated all the same,” I replied. “And I would accept the frog bow as being very dumb. For my response, I present for your consideration, an armor made of maps, with folded paper for the protective elements. When a ranged projectile of some kind comes in, its course gets directed away from the armor.”

“Redirection?” asked Zinnia. “That’s common enough. The form factor of the armor is a bit unusual, and I suppose a bit useless depending on if it has the usual protections or not, whether it could get soggy …” She frowned. “I don’t see how it’s dumb, necessarily.”

“It’s plot armor!” I smiled.

“So … it’s a pun?” asked Yarrow.

“It’s … yeah,” I said. “You’ve never heard the expression ‘plot armor’?”

“Maybe,” said Yarrow. “Meaning, someone is protected because they’re a character in a story, and therefore nothing too bad can happen to them?”

“Yeah,” I replied. “You know, you really kill the joke when you explain it.”

“And you’d maintain that this ‘plot armor’ is dumber than the frog bow?” asked Yarrow.

I sighed. “Fine, do I just lose, or am I graciously allowed a do-over?”

“One do-over,” said Yarrow, holding up a finger.

“I have one,” said Raven. She’d been mostly silent through this exchange, which I respected, since it was ultimately pointless, and a distraction, save for the fact that I could focus on two things at once. “The decanter of endless tapioca. When you turned it upside down, tapioca would come sliding out, forever.”

“Wow,” I replied. “Useful though.”

“You think that beats the frog bow?” asked Yarrow, scratching his head for a moment.

“I vote it does, but this is my first game of dumb entads, and I have obvious bias,” I replied. We hadn’t formalized teams, but it seemed we’d settled on two against two. Pallida was watching, smiling slightly, and I was positive that after an extremely long life, she would eventually have something to beat us with.

“Very well,” said Yarrow. “Then I suppose I’ll have to dig deep.” He cleared his throat. “There is a wand which will create wands which create wands which create wands, and so forth.”

“Good for firewood, I guess,” I replied, then clamped down my second thought, which induced an electric current of fear that sent me jittering through space, what would happen if Bethel ate that. I cleared away the passion magic quickly, hoping that no one had noticed me drop a few frames.

“Finding uses isn’t part of the game,” said Zinnia.

“Alright,” I replied. “Then as a counterpoint, the ring of ant control.”

“Controlling ants doesn’t seem that dumb,” said Yarrow. His brow was furrowed as he tried to find the catch.

“Ah,” I replied. “But it doesn’t allow the controls of ants, it allows the control of ant, as in, a single normal ant.”

“That … is quite dumb,” said Yarrow. “Is it real? They have to be real items, not just the dumbest entads you can come up with.”

“On my honor,” I replied, though I had no idea if such a thing had ever existed on Aerb. The wand of wand creation apparently did though, and like the ring of ant control, it was a joke item that I’d used in an April Fool’s one-shot set in the Hall of Magical Rejects, with a half hundred dumb magic items that had mostly been sourced from message boards and discords. I was trying to remember as many as I could, then pare down the list to those that made sense without the context of D&D and Earth culture. If this was just a game of dumb entads, then I was going to make sure that I won.

“I’m not sure that we have these entads in the right order,” said Pallida. “In theory, they should be getting dumber, yes?”

“Yarrow always tries to frame it as a competition,” said Zinnia. “It doesn’t really work well that way. In theory, it’s about mutual appreciation of the sometimes absurd nature of entads.”

Yarrow shrugged. “How I always think of it is, if you went into a forge frenzy and came to on the other side, after days or weeks or months or years of work, with your personal life in shambles and likely some considerable debt, how gutted would you be to discover what the entad actually did?”

“When you put it like that, the game seems less fun,” I said.

“Well, before we finish, I have a final retort,” said Yarrow. “You see, I happen to be in possession of what I have officially deemed the Dumbest Entad in the World. It makes the game easy to win.” He turned to his sister. “Zin, my pipe, please.”

Zinnia rolled her eyes and reached into her magical handbag, rooting around for a moment, then pulling out a small, unassuming pipe, which my soul sight also marked as magical, with the same hue that came from Yarrow’s aura.

“No demonstrations,” I said.

Yarrow took the pipe with a grin, then paused for a moment and looked over to his sister. “Tobacco too? And my lighter?”

“I said no demonstrations,” I repeated.

Yarrow let out an exasperated sigh. “Look, I know very well that we’re on opposite sides of this thing, whatever it is, but there’s no rule that says we have to be so stern with each other. Besides, the joke’s less funny if I explain it, you said as much yourself.”

“I don’t want to be an asshole about it,” I replied. “But no demonstrations of any entads, dumb or otherwise.”

Yarrow frowned at me. “Or what?” he asked. “You’ll attack me and bring down the Armateurs on yourself, causing a diplomatic incident and committing assault, on top of the desertion you’re already guilty of?”

Zinnia quietly handed him the tobacco and lighter, looking distinctly uncomfortable. I noticed that her hand stayed in her bag, where she’d said her wand and monocle were, and I started using vibration magic to mimic warder’s sight, just to make sure she wasn’t surrepitously erecting wards. Doing that without actually moving your wand was, I was told, brutally difficult, but I wasn’t going to take chances. I saw nothing.

“Yes,” I replied. “I would do all that, because now that you’re warned, if you try it, I’ll know you’re doing it for a purpose, not for fun.”

“Hrm,” said Yarrow. He looked down for a moment and then began shoving tobacco into the pipe. I’d said no demonstrations, and I’d said that I would attack him, but I didn’t know where to draw the line. Surely I would at least have to stop him if he tried to light the pipe. He stopped when the tobacco was in the pipe, looking it over, and then looked up at me. “Have you thought that from my perspective, letting my decisions be dictated by someone who pretends not to have any particular limits on what grievious violence he would inflict means that I would end up ruled by threats, even when those threats would never actually be carried out? It would be terrible policy.”

I stood where I was and slowly drew my sword. I had other options, like trying to slice the entad from his hands, but he was right that this really wasn’t what I was here to do.

“Go ahead,” I said, with my sword drawn. I collapsed down the threads and focused on him with vibration magic, listening to the beat of his heart, which was going fast, betraying his cool demeanor. That didn’t mean that he was going to attack me with the pipe entad though, whatever it did. I was, after all, threatening to end his life.

Yarrow stared at me for a moment, then flipped the top of his lighter and put it to the end of the pipe. I wasn’t sure that I had ever seen someone light a pipe, but he was making a production of it, skimming the tobacco with the flame while puffing, then finally getting it to catch. He took a few puffs and let them out; I was using air magic to make sure that no particulates reached me.

I didn’t attack him. I couldn’t break the peace, not over this, it would be assault by anyone’s definition, and it would fuck things up for Amaryllis if I was wrong. I could leave, jump out the window or burst through the door, but I wasn’t just thinking about myself, I was thinking about everyone else, and about Amaryllis in the next room.

“Well, now I worry that I’ve built it up too much,” said Yarrow. “And you’ll say, ‘oh, well that’s dumb, certainly, but not worth all the drama’.” He let out a puff of smoke, aimed up at the ceiling. “Here,” he said, then took in an enormous breath and held it, holding a finger up, indicating for us to wait, as though we were going to do anything else.

When he finally let out the breath, it wasn’t smoke, but instead a wave of glowing grey magic, and even though I pushed as hard as I could with still magic to stop it in its tracks, it washed over me, putting me to sleep almost instantly.

Painless

More time passed. Pallida was propped up in one corner of the room, still gagged, and the flow of blood from Solace’s head eventually stopped. I had no idea whether it was as much blood as I should have expected to come from the head of a ten year old crantek girl, but suspected that it was only enough to look convincing. I wanted her to wink again, to confirm that I hadn’t imagined it, but as much as I stared at her, there was nothing. If she was waiting for her moment to act, it apparently hadn’t come yet. Fucking fake outs.

I wondered where Amaryllis and Grak were. After more than five hours, or however long it had actually been, they surely would have finished with Hyacinth, then come back to see who knew what in the Prince’s Room. Maybe the room would be empty and pristine, exactly as it had been when we’d entered it, or maybe there would be some signs of a struggle. I hadn’t seen Raven yet, and I had no idea whether or not the pipe would even have worked on her, given that she didn’t sleep. In her case, that was because of something the Lord of Dreams had done to her to keep her from the plane of dreams, but she’d never been explicit about whether or not it offered protection from magical sleep. I hoped that she had escaped, or failing that, that she was okay.

It took some time for Zinnia to wheel Yarrow in. He was strapped to a dolly with his hands and feet bound, the armor he’d been wearing removed and replaced with a hospital gown. I had no idea whether he was a secret soul mage or a registered one, but the only way he would have gotten fucked over by that meme was if he’d been looking around in my soul. I had no sympathy for him.

The only contact that Zinnia allowed me was to push the dolly forward so that Yarrow’s head was pressed against my chest, which wasn’t how I was used to doing things. Further complicating matters was whatever effect was stopping me from using my magic, which deadened a whole lot of my senses. Still, I was an extremely powerful soul mage by the standards of the Empire of Common Cause, even with my powers down to baseline, and the only living spirit mage, and it wasn’t too much more work to get inside.

It was foolish of Zinnia to let me try, in the same way that it was foolish to listen to a single damned thing that a (normal) non-anima said. I couldn’t be trusted, and that meant that whatever I was allowed to do to Yarrow, he couldn’t be trusted either. Because soul magic would revert over time, they could test that he was no longer catatonic and then stick him in isolation for a few months in the hopes that whatever changes I made would undo themselves, which I supposed was probably their best case scenario. Unknown to them, I had a handle on why souls reverted, which was that the spiritual structure that ran in parallel to the soul would cause a lot of that revision.

If the soul was the database and the spirit was a program interfacing with that database, then the mechanism of reversion was that in its natural state, the soul and spirit were in equilibrium with each other, and when something got out of whack, there were negative feedback loops that got them into rough agreement with each other. If a soul mage went in and did the obvious, naive method of control, boosting a single value into the stratosphere, then every time the spirit interacted with that value, which it would probably do a lot, it would bump it down. For the most part, soul values weren’t where they were because that was innate to the person, they were where they were because of complex thoughts and messy intellectual/emotional wires crossing at various points. That was especially the case for the single-value-raising, because there was absolutely nothing backing that valuation, and anyone with even the smallest sliver of introspection would get that feeling like they’d recognized a false epiphany.

If I had to explain it to a five-year-old, or more likely, if I had to give a concise explanation to a jury or judge who were trying me for the crimes I was about to commit, I would say that the soul and spirit ‘talked’ to each other, and when the spirit asked the soul a question, it would naturally do some due diligence on the answer, whether a person had been soulfucked or not. Your opinion of people improved the more they did good things for you, and the more you focused on those good things, but if you had this single sky-high value that was backed by nothing, then every thought would bring that value down as your mind consciously and unconsciously grappled with the fact that there was no support structure.

There were more complex and effective ways of soulfucking, if you were an enterprising soul mage who was trying to create an army of loyal slaves. I hadn’t talked to him much about it, but my best guess at what my former instructor Fallatehr had done with his prison army was that he’d worked hard to alter all the values, as well as to micromanage the soul, and adapt it to the individual spirit, which he could only see through the shadow that it cast. He made not-quite-clones of himself, as perfectly aligned with him as they could be, by attempting to rejigger things over and over again until he had something in the soul that the spirit wouldn’t dash against the rocks through its own native processes. (Some of that was admittedly guesswork on my part.)

I was a spirit mage though, and more than that, I was a multimage. I had more options at my fingertips than anyone in the history of Aerb, excepting Uther, who reportedly hated those manipulations with a burning passion (though who knew whether or not that was true). I’d revealed the existence of the spirit to Zinnia and whoever else was watching, but only in brief. If they’d known what I could do, they probably would have decided that it wasn’t worth the risk.

Looking through memories was a hell of a thing for a soul mage, because memories were in their own difficult system that varied widely from person to person, and no coherent way of traversing through the dense cluster aside from diving right in and marking where everything was. Soul mages could look at and extract memories, but the process was so arduous that almost no one ever did it, especially not when you could just soulfuck your target and have them tell you whatever you wanted to know. For me though, searching memories was a bit easier, because memories in the soul were connected to threads in the spirit, and because of the necessary interrelations between the two systems, it was possible to look at any given ranked value, then find the threads that led out from it, then isolate the threads that led back into the network of memories, and then, finally, look at the mess of memories, trying to find the important ones. It was still time consuming, but not so much so that it might as well have been impossible, especially because I could judge by the nature of the threads which memories were likely to be important. Each thread wasn’t only and exactly one memory, but there was some correlation between them, with the threads being ‘thoughts’ about those people that interfaced with the stored memories in the soul, tied into the social modeling aspect of the soul, looping toward values.

I found Hyacinth in his list of values, higher than I expected her to be but still outside the top hundred, and tried tracing that back, but there were too many threads, and more than that, too many that looked important. The spirit wasn’t just conscious thought, it was subconscious too, and things that we might not even recognize as thoughts, background processes of the mind. I stared at the threads for a moment, trying to untangle them and what they were responsible for, if they could be said to be responsible for anything. I changed nothing at all in the soul, but slowly changed things in the spirit, threads for Hyacinth, for Zinnia, for Amaryllis, and for what scraps of myself I could see, not the full throttling that I normally did to squeeze out some harmful effect, or the widening that I might do to make something overwhelmingly important, but small and subtle things.

The goal wasn’t to convert him then and there, it was to do the opposite of what normally happens with a soul mage, to set up feedback loops and processes that would push his soul into the configuration that I actually wanted. If I’d done things right, when he thought about me, or even when I was subconsciously on his mind, his value for me would slowly rise. If they put him into isolation for a month, he would come out with his loyalties changed, rather than returned to baseline.

I’d never done anything like it, and delicate manipulations of a person were probably not best experimented with while under gunpoint. Obviously, they probably weren’t best done at all, but I didn’t have too much of a choice, because Zinnia was trigger happy enough to shoot Solace just to teach me a lesson. Once the manipulations were more or less done, I went to the work of making the meme dormant, which was what I was ostensibly there for. That work I’d already done twice before, so I had practice, and it went quickly in the timeless view of the spirit.

When I opened my eyes, Zinnia was gone and the door was closed. Solace was still lifeless, but she’d been moved next to the mirror, her body leaving a trail of dark green blood. Pallida was still where she’d been before, having not moved much, maybe just a wriggle.

“It’s done,” I replied, my tongue feeling thick in my mouth. “And I need to pee.”

I felt colder than I remembered. Something had been applied to my chest, a paste of some kind, but it wasn’t proper healing, and though I still had plenty of blood to spare until I was no longer hypertensive, I had lost a lot. It was dried and caked to me, having soaked through my underwear when it dripped down and then coagulated on my legs, sticking the hairs together. When this was all over, I was going to take a long shower.

Yarrow moved against his restraint. His head was still pressed against my bloody chest, and when he pulled away, he pulled away sticky, semi-solid blood, unplugging places where the small cuts had sealed, letting them weep blood again. I was sure that if I were able to feel pain, it would have been incredibly painful.

“What happened?” asked Yarrow, looking around for a moment. He was bound in the dolly, and twisted his head around to see Pallida and Solace’s ‘corpse’. “What happened?” he asked again, voice rising. “Zin! Onion!”

“You looked at my soul,” I said. “You really shouldn’t have done that.”

“What the fuck?” he asked. “Zin!” he shouted.

Zinnia came into the room, passing through the black doorway, fully cleaned off but still wearing the same bodysuit. She had the pain stick in one rubber-gloved hand.

“He had some kind of memetic effect within his soul,” said Zinnia. “You ran into it headfirst. We couldn’t risk another soul mage or an anolia to confirm, so he administered the cure himself, which means that he had full, unfettered access to your soul.”

“How long has it been?” asked Yarrow, relaxing slightly with her explanation. I didn’t have a good enough handle on him to know what was going through his mind.

“Since the initial capture,” she glanced at me, “Ten hours,” said Zinnia. She was standing on her side of the red line, not yet moving over to get her brother. “Linear protocol is in effect. Don’t say anything compromising in front of the prisoners.”

“I don’t feel any different,” said Yarrow, briefly looking up at me. “Can you get me away from him? Restraints on, I understand that.”

Zinnia once again made the same hand signal, then waited a beat before stepping across the red line and grabbing the dolly to wheel her brother back with one hand, the other still holding the pain stick. She made no move to loosen his restraints.

“I really don’t feel any different,” said Yarrow. He looked down at the pain stick and licked his lips once. “Please, I know what it’s —”

She touched him with the pain stick, keeping the touch light and brief, and he screamed, mouth open wide.

“Fuck!” he yelled. “Fuck, I was going to say I know what it’s like, you don’t need to touch me with it you dumb fucking cunt.”

“It’s more effective if it’s used once to demonstrate,” said Zinnia. “Do you feel any positive disposition toward Juniper, Amaryllis, or anyone in their party? Linear protocol.”

Yarrow stopped and thought for a moment. “Nothing suspect,” he replied. He was shaking slightly, and gave a glance at the pain stick. “I never hated Amaryllis and I still don’t hate her now. Juniper …” he paused and looked at me. “I have feelings of envy and a few layers of regret, but I believe those to be roughly the same as I had before.”

“Regret?” I asked.

“Be quiet, or I’ll torture your friend,” said Zinnia.

“I regretted using the pipe before I did it because you didn’t seem like a bad person,” said Yarrow. “I felt enormous regret when I woke up, because it meant that a mistake was made at some point.” He looked at Zinnia again. “But Zin, it’s nothing suspect. You know that I was always good at linear protocol, and you know that I’m responsive to the pain stick.”

“Are you arguing for your release?” she asked.

“No,” said Yarrow. “No, of course not. I’m looking at the entad in your hand and trying to think of what I can possibly say to keep you from using it on me, even if I could agree that using it would be justified. You know what it does to people.”

Zinnia frowned, then made the hand signal again and stepped over the red line. She was on my side for just long enough that she could prod me with the stick. Again, I felt nothing.

“Why doesn’t it work?” asked Zinnia.

“I don’t know,” said Yarrow. “Would it be safe to venture a guess in front of him?”

“Presumably not,” said Zinnia.

“Wheel me out then and we can continue this conversation,” said Yarrow.

“No,” replied Zinnia. “You were afflicted with some manner of memetic warfare which poisoned your soul and put you into a catatonic state. Juniper claims to have made that meme dormant but still contagious. That means that you now have access to his soul.”

“Hang on a moment,” said Yarrow. He looked at me, then back at her. “Can you please wheel me out, so you can at least hear my argument?”

“Fine,” said Zinnia. She left for a moment and returned with her rubber glove and pain stick missing, then grabbed the handles of the dolly and wheeled him into the black void of the doorway, closing the door behind her.

“I still need to pee!” I called after her.

While they were gone, I tried to think of what their next steps would be. I had altered Yarrow’s soul by way of his spirit, and if they didn’t know the truth of what I had done, general precautions about soul mages dictated that they not let him go until they had waited a considerable time for him to normalize. That meant that whatever changes I had made, they weren’t going to be a lot of help in the near term. But now that I had fixed Yarrow, what did they actually want? Obviously they would want to keep me alive, because if I was the only one who would interact with Yarrow’s soul besides Yarrow, then I was the only one who could make changes. Obviously they would also need to have some kind of leverage over me, which meant keeping either Pallida or Raven alive. But beyond that, what they would want from me, aside from just keeping me off the board, was information. I was worried that I would have to just allow Pallida to be tortured, because if I gave in to it, then they would know that I would give in again and again. Still, I wasn’t sure that I could hold out forever, and if they weren’t using my friends against me, then I was pretty sure that they would come up with something against a man who couldn’t feel pain.

What, then, was I hoping for? Solace was ‘dead’, but would eventually make a move, though I didn’t know what she was biding her time for. Pallida was unlikely to escape if she hadn’t done so already, unless she was feigning weakness too. I certainly wasn’t going to get out of the predicament that I’d been placed in, because whoever had built the box that I was in, they’d been pretty damned paranoid about it. Water magic wasn’t even working, and it would be pretty damned hard to kill someone with water magic. I did have to pee, but I imagined that they would let me piss myself, given that my underwear was already soaked with blood, so it wasn’t like I would get a chance to escape.

What I had was soul and spirit, along with the game interface, which seemed like it might be enough.

One of the most powerful aspects of soul magic, aside from making slaves, was the ability to move around skill points and temporarily boost my skills, especially since it let me get virtues that I would otherwise have to grind for a long time to ever see. I had one, twenty points away, that seemed right for the job, at least if I had a little leeway in terms of definitions, which I did. One of the clauses in the Essentialism 60 virtue was, ‘You may retract your soul from your extremities for the purposes of bypassing wards,’ and my guess was that whatever magic the manacles were working on, they were interacting with my soul in some way. If I could retract my soul from my extremities, it was possible that I could fool them enough to make them let me go. It wouldn’t work by the strict rules as written, but I had Six-Eyed to give me some leeway. My only hesitation, aside from the points I would have to shift over, was that I had no idea if someone was watching me, what crossing the red line meant, what the manacles did, or what was beyond the door. There was, no doubt, a lot of uncertainty.

My big concern was that Zinnia would ask Yarrow to do what I would ask him to do in her place, which would be to permanently mangle my soul. I’d cleared Yarrow of the meme, which meant that he could go in and do the thing that he’d likely been angling to do when he’d been struck down by the meme’s power. I had only a very general idea of what would happen if I went toe-to-toe with him in a match of soul mage against soul mage, but it wouldn’t need to come to that, since he had his pipe and could just put me to sleep. There were good reasons not to completely trash my soul, but they could trash parts of it, and I wanted to avoid that as much as possible.

I went into my soul and scooped the points from Heavy Armor, my designated emergency stash for just such an occasion, putting them into Essentialism. When I opened my eyes back up, I tested the strength of the manacles, just in case they’d somehow lost their power, then tried my best to adjust myself so that all my weight was suspended from a single arm. With the other arm, I began pulling back my soul, trying to go slowly but not too slowly.

The manacle unclicked once my soul was retracted down past my elbow, leaving no sensation whatsoever in my hand or forearm. I let up the pressure and allowed my soul to rush back in, which caused the manacle to click back shut. I was hoping that no one noticed, but if someone had come rushing into the room following that proof of concept, I probably would have needed to act fast and drop down.

But waiting until Zinnia came back didn’t seem optimal, especially if she was going to have her pistol with her, and with the Skilled Trade debuff slowly ticking down my Essentialism, time was decidedly not on my side. It wasn’t now or never, but it was now or later with worse odds, which I’d known when I started in on this plan.

I took a breath and retracted my soul from my extremities, feeling them deaden. The manacles released a moment later, dropping me unceremoniously to the floor. As I let my soul flood back into my arms and legs, the manacles moved toward me, and I had to dodge out of the way as they strained against their mounts to reach for me. Thankfully, they seemed to have a set range, and the room was large enough that I could move out of that range without crossing the red line.

Wasting no time, I moved toward the red line and stuck my pinky out to cross it, holding my breath as I waited for the feeling of bone and blood being vaporized by an annihilation ward, or for my pinky to be bent backward by a velocity ward. Instead, I felt what I hoped I would feel, which was the blood being pressed backward down my veins and the bone of my last knuckle being stopped in place. It was surprisingly painless, until I remembered that I had shut off pain.

I retracted my soul from my arm and pushed my arm through the ward with ease, then let my soul rush back into my arm, just to confirm that my soul could pass through the barrier without any problems. The wards were (probably) against latent blood and bone magic, but without the connection to the soul, there was no magic to speak of, just organic matter.

Being halfway through the ward wasn’t something that I could have held, as the ward was dividing my tibula and fibula and holding them in place in mid-air, and my veins and arteries were bisected by a hard barrier, but I was moving as fast as I safely could.

The next step was harder though, because I was going to try to manipulate myself across the barrier. It had to be done in fits and starts, retracting my soul and pushing myself across, then when I was halfway through, pushing my soul across the barrier entirely and dragging the ‘dead’ pieces of myself through. I went temporarily blind when my soul left my head, and prayed that I wouldn’t be possessed by a demon in the split second that my brain was without its soul, if such a thing was even possible. It was a good proof of concept for being able to control my body after decapitation, and as soon as I had the thought, I prayed that I would never have to endure that.

All told, it took twenty seconds from when I’d dropped down onto the floor to when I was through the ward.

When I had my vision back, I rushed over to Solace, which put me out of line of sight from both the doorway and the window. The bonds were whipvine, a ‘mundane’ plant whose material properties were ideally suited to binding someone, and I had no easy way of cutting through them, because I didn’t have access to cold iron.

“Solace,” I said to her corpse. “Now’s the time.” I said a silent prayer for her to not really be dead, that the wink I’d seen had been meant for me, not just a trick of the light or final spasm of facial muscles.

She blinked a few times, then sat up and let her bonds fall away. Rather than falling to the floor, they twisted in the air and combined with each other, floating around like playful spirits until they made a solid length of rope in Solace’s hand. She crossed the room over to Pallida, moving quickly on bare feet, and with a smooth motion, Pallida’s bonds became a part of the rope that Solace was holding.

“They’re waiting outside that door to kill us,” said Pallida once she’d taken her gag out.

“Or they haven’t noticed anything is wrong,” I replied. I looked down at my chest, which was freely bleeding from all the small cuts again, a result of the rapid movement. “I need to get to a place where my magic works.”

“You have a way past that door?” asked Pallida, gesturing at the thick metal barrier that separated us from what I assumed was the hallway. “I can get through a whole lot of locks with not a lot of tools, but if there’s a lock on this door, it’s not facing us, and the hinges are on the other side. That’s not as dire as it sounds, but a properly machined and maintained deadbolt would be murder even if I had special tools, and I have no tools at all.” She spotted the small knife that Zinnia had left on the floor. “Unless you can grab that for me?”

“Sure,” I said. I went to the red line, frowned at it for a moment, and wormed my way across it, going faster the second time. I wasn’t quite trying techniques on the fly, because I’d known that this was theoretically possible, but I hadn’t had the training time to devote to this specific scenario. It was also theoretically possible, with the right amount of control, to retract my soul from my bones and blood but only my bones and blood, leaving me with sensation, but the initial test run of that was a lot more difficult than I could do fluidly, and I was on a time limit as the debuff kept ticking away. I grabbed the knife and gave it to Pallida, then moved back across the ward. “Done,” I said.

“Alright,” replied Pallida. “Now we hope that their doors are shitty.”

“It’s an entad building,” I replied, not that it was a point one way or another. It wasn’t clear to me whether this was an entad prison or some other kind of building that had been appropriated for that purpose. “Hurry though, we don’t know when they’ll be back.”

Pallida took some time, slipping the knife into the edges of the doorframe. I kept waiting for someone to come through the expanse of black that was the window, or to kick the door open, but there was nothing but silence. I missed vibration magic, because I wanted to listen in on what was happening in the hallway. Nothing good, I imagined.

“Got it,” said Pallida, standing up and breathing out. “I’ll impress you with the technical details some other time.” She opened the door, and we were left staring at the black doorway which no light could cross.

“Alright,” I replied, taking a breath. “Wish me luck.”

After a quick test that the wards weren’t likely to kill me, I launched myself forward through the doorway, ready to use bone magic and still magic the moment I could feel them again. I’d had more unicorn bones implanted inside me, the last three that would actually fit without being horrendously uncomfortable, and I was prepared to use one here, if I needed to. Thankfully whatever scan they’d used to find my gem, they hadn’t found the foreign bones.

Instead of foes, I found myself at one end of a hallway that was devoid of people. It was the same gray of the room I’d left, a material that wasn’t quite concrete or the ubiquitous magestone that was used all over Aerb. It was the same entad shading that the room had, but whatever magic it held, that wasn’t obvious to me yet. I poked my head back in the room, through the black void.

“We’re clear to move,” I said. “No enemies.”

I started down the hallway without waiting for either of them, hoping that if there was someone hostile, I would be able to deal with them before Pallida or Solace were put in danger. A quick check showed me that a few of my magics were back online, but they were the least combat-oriented ones, water magic, ink magic, and air magic, all of them traditional utility magic. Anything that I would normally want to use to maim or kill a person was still locked out.

“Where was Raven?” I asked, turning back to look at the others.

“We were blindfolded,” replied Solace.

“I memorized the route as best I could,” said Pallida. “If you want to go back to my room, it’s down this hall and then two lefts. Less security than your room though. I’m not sure what they would use for Raven, given her pedigree.”

I moved along quickly, quite conscious that I was in my underwear and without most of my magic. Ink magic used magical inks to do its thing, and they hadn’t pumped my stomach, but I just didn’t think that we had the time for me to create something and put it on, even something small like a bracelet or amulet. Whatever facility we were in, my guess was that it would be heavily guarded, and if they hadn’t yet noticed our escape, then they would soon.

We reached the door Pallida thought was hers without seeing anyone. If every one of the doors we’d passed were for prisoners, then this was a black site capable of holding hundreds of people. The scale was unsettling, as was the complete lack of guards.

“We’re not going to be able to find her unless she’s making noise,” said Pallida. “Nothing to say that she’s even awake to call out, if she’s not gagged.”

“You’re saying we leave her,” I replied.

“We regroup,” said Pallida. “We come back with gear and information, the rest of the team, Grak to break the wards.”

“Guards are finally coming,” said Solace. She had her hand against one wall and her eyes closed. “Moving slowly, unaware. North-east.”

“I don’t know my cardinals right now,” I replied. I assumed that we were still in Anglecynn, but the water outside didn’t feel right. Caledwich was a port city, with a thick river running out toward the docks, and my water magic was strong enough that I should have been able to feel the rough geography. The sense of water I was getting was only a vague impression, but it was completely wrong, a dotting of lakes and large rivers, if I had to guess.

“That way,” said Solace. “I’ll deal with them.” She clapped her hands together and pulled them apart like they were stuck together with glue. I could see sparks of electricity in the gap between her hands.

“Save your juice,” I replied, trotting down the hallway to where she’d pointed. I was still trying to get my bearings, making an internal map of this place. I was expecting either Solace or Pallida to object, but neither of them did, and I rounded the corner to face two guards all by myself.

They were surprised to see me. Both of them were lightly armored, with silvered breastplates and truncheons at their hips, none of it entadic, or at least, none that had been invested. Neither was ready for me: they were holding coffee cups, large, steaming mugs that I assumed they’d gotten from a breakroom somewhere.

I attacked as they reached for their weapons, punching one of them squarely in the face and then quickly kicking the other in the crotch. They were, if I’m being honest, no real match for me, and I probably didn’t need to use the level of violence that I’d used, but I had been chained up and threatened enough that I wasn’t in a terribly charitable mood, to put it mildly. I delivered a chop to one guard’s throat, which dropped him to the floor, then grabbed the other’s arm as he brought up his truncheon and flipped him over me, stomping down on his head with a bare foot once he was on the floor. Once I had one of the truncheons, I smashed one of them in the head with a satisfying crunch. I turned to his partner and smashed him across the side of the face as he tried to get to his feet, thinking just after it was over that it would have been better to interrogate him instead.

Pedro Riart defeated!

Warren Liff defeated!

This had all made a fair amount of noise, but in the silence that followed I didn’t hear any shouting or running footsteps. I held still for a moment, holding my newly acquired truncheon and feeling the sting of the strikes in my hand, waiting for the next threat, but it never came.

“Here,” I said, tossing the other truncheon to Pallida as she came around the corner. “So far so good.”

“Do you need healing?” asked Solace. She was looking me up and down.

“I’m losing blood off and on,” I replied. “But I’m still at least an hour away from being impeded. I’ll take it if you can spare it.”

“Your leg?” asked Solace, pointing.

I looked down and saw that my left leg was an angry red and wet with scalding hot coffee. I wasn’t sure when it had happened, but some of the coffee they’d been carrying had been splashed on me in the altercation, and I hadn’t even noticed, because I wasn’t feeling the pain that was surely there.

“I turned off pain,” I said. “You know better than I do if I need healing. Our goal right now is getting out.”

“Schlubs,” said Pallida, kicking the guards. “This is a place that runs itself, you don’t hire your best. We should be able to make it out.”

“Minor healing then,” said Solace. She came up to me and poked at my chest, which caused all of the small cuts that Zinnia had left to heal closed. I looked down at my leg and saw that it was less of an angry color, instead looking like a mild sunburn.

“Alright,” I said. “Based on what I can sense of the water, we’re not in Caledwich, we’re inland, next to a deep lake, and we’re underground, probably two stories.”

“If these assholes were getting coffee, then that means they didn’t expect Zinnia back anytime soon,” said Pallida. “We might have some leeway.”

“What are you thinking?” I asked.

“I don’t know,” replied Pallida. “Set a trap for the prince and the princess, steal some clothes, do something else like that. We’re under strength, in a facility that’s not designed to let us out. The only upside is that the rank and file aren’t mages,” she gestured to the bodies, “But I very much doubt that’s going to be true of the rest of them.”

“Not your first jail break?” asked Solace.

“No,” replied Pallida. “But I haven’t broken out of jail as many times as you might imagine, because I’ve never made a habit of getting caught.”

“I can make ink armor for us,” I said. “I still have the inks in my stomach, they weren’t voided. I could probably do something serviceable in five minutes or so.”

“Something to get us out of here?” asked Pallida.

“The i-factor would be too high,” I replied. “Armor I could do, but I would be putting most of the power into making it deployable, less into utility.” That was just basic item creation rules from D&D; you couldn’t have something that was easy to put on and ultra-durable unless it was really high level.

“Well stop talking and get on it,” said Pallida. She looked down at the bodies. “I’d steal the uniform, but the pink skin would be a giveaway anyway.”

I started creating a suit of armor from the ether, splitting threads so that I could focus on how much danger we were in with the half of my mind that wasn’t busy creating the armor from nothing.

“You can’t magic us out of here?” Pallida asked Solace.

“They have the locus,” said Solace. “Even if I could make a conduit for us, I couldn’t leave the locus behind. If we’re lucky, they won’t understand the nature of the entad, but we were captured by two entad specialists. It’s possible they’re trying things that aren’t to be tried.”

“We have no idea how big this place is,” said Pallida. “And we have no guarantee that the locus is even here.”

“We’re close,” said Solace. “I can feel it.”

“If you’re not going to get us out of here, can you conjure up some magic for me?” asked Pallida. “Something to leave me a little less naked?” She wasn’t fully naked, just dressed in a mismatched bra and underwear that I assumed were what she’d been wearing beneath her armor. It was odd to me that they’d left us our underwear, given how cavalier they were about depriving us of our dignity in every other way, along with their casual use of both violence and soul magic. (Maybe they were trying to toe the line between a PG-13 and a hard R.)

“You’re worried about modesty at a time like this?” asked Solace.

“Modesty?” asked Pallida, looking down, as if only just noticing that her clothes were gone. “I meant weapons and armor.”

Solace leaned down to one of the bodies and spoke a few nonsense words before slamming her hand down against his armored chest. When she lifted her hand up, his clothing and armor rent and collapsed, allowing his bones to cleanly rise through the cuts that had been made. She stood and pulled them higher through the air, which brought more of his skeleton with him, until eventually the whole of it had been pulled from his body, a process that had been completely bloodless, aside from how the blood flowed out of his boneless corpse.

“What the actual shit,” said Pallida.

“Hush,” said Solace. “Stand right where you are, and,” she thrust the whole thing sideways at Pallida, and the bones struck her as she made herself rigid, twisting and wrapping around her with no apparent effort from Solace whatsoever. When they were finished, Pallida was wrapped in bones, though the bones of a single person weren’t enough to cover much more than her vital organs. In places, the bones had split or warped, and the skull especially was in so many different pieces that I could barely tell where it was. Altogether it was horrifically ugly and wouldn’t work for shit unless it had a lot of magic to it, which I assumed it did. It didn’t even cover all her underwear.

“Necromancy?” asked Pallida, looking down at it.

“Yes,” replied Solace. “Of a sort. It’s what material I have to work with. I’ll need less bones for myself, so I can use a femur for a sword for you. It needs to be done quickly though, while the soul is still there.” She moved over to the other body, and I turned away, focusing on the armor that I was working with.

“I never knew that druids could do that,” said Pallida.

“You’ve seen Grak’s hand,” replied Solace. “It was made from a stick.”

“You’re talking about using people though,” said Pallida.

“You’re thirty thousand years old,” I said. “Surely that can’t be a surprise to you.”

“But she’s a druid, they’re supposed to be — well, not ripping skeletons from bodies to wear as armor,” said Pallida. “It’s not using the body like that I’m surprised by, it’s who’s using it.”

“A body is a body,” said Solace. When I looked up, she was dressed all in bone as well, which covered her considerably more and was much more well-crafted of a piece, if no less terrifying. “We don’t bury our bodies, we leave them to be eaten, first the animals, then the insects, and finally the soil itself.”

“Druids … are aware of bacteria, aren’t they?” I asked.

“We are,” said Solace. “I was speaking metaphorically.”

“I’m done with the first armor,” I said. I held it up in my hand. It was the size and approximate shape of a hockey puck, laced through with several metallic lines. I tossed it into the air, and it spun around once before stopping in place and then bursting outward into a thousand small lines that wrapped themselves around me. I braced myself and tried not to flinch; eventually you had to trust in ink magic, but DIY entads weren’t without their risks, and I hadn’t had the magic for that long, nor did I have a competent teacher. When the pseudo-entad was finished, it had wrapped me up, with a thin film between the lines that covered me. It was form-fitting and felt incredibly light, not really by design so much as an outgrowth of the general principles I’d been working along. If I was hit, the lines would snap as though under tension, providing defense for me and acting as a weapon as well. “I could make a weapon for myself, but I think the truncheon will do. I want to save juice for if we really need it. Solace, do you have a bead on which direction we should head in to get to the locus?”

“It doesn’t work like that,” said Solace. “We’re close, but I don’t know how close.”

“Fine,” I replied. “I didn’t expect that it would, because that would be too convenient. Can you turn the rest of their bodies into something useful?” I asked. “Smear their blood on me, wear their skins, eat their flesh and take their powers?”

“Their souls are mangled now,” said Solace. “These armors are powered and shaped by pieces of them, with less strain on the locus. If you were to ingest a preparation of their hearts, you would become ill. Trust me to know my own way best.”

“I will,” I replied. “I have just enough time for —” and I’d been going to say, “something else of ink,” but the words were cut short by a sound that didn’t belong in the silence of the hallway.

“Company,” Pallida whispered. We’d been keeping our voices low, and she’d stationed herself near the corner that the guards had come around. “Shit, they’re gone.”

“Calling in more troops, do you think?” I asked.

“Yeah,” said Pallida. “Ready?”

I knew, roughly speaking, that normal prisons back on Earth had a prisoner to guard ratio of five or six to one. Based on the number of doors we’d passed, my best guess at the size of the place was that it could hold a thousand. How many of the cells were actually filled was an open question, but if this was an entad prison, or at least an entad building, then it was entirely possible they could cut way back on staff. How many people could we be facing? Ten? A hundred? And how many mages, and of which varieties? The guards with truncheons would have had numerous advantages against anyone who wasn’t me, given the wards that seemed to cover the building, but you’d be a fool not to keep at least one mage on-site at all times, no matter how small a site it was.

“Ready,” I said. I was, frankly, ready to bash some heads. We had been kidnapped and put into an Anglecynn black site, and so far as I was concerned, that meant that my normal affection for the guards of the world was no longer in play.

We went quickly down the hallway, with me in the lead. I held my hand out in front of me, in a position that Grak had taught me called the warder’s march, a way of walking designed to injure or amputate the fingers of your non-dominant hand first in order to save the rest of you. It was a bit like running forward like you were heiling Hitler, but it was supposedly effective against everything but what Grak called ‘death wards’, those wards designed not to keep anyone out, but to kill as effectively as possible. Making bone annihilation wards as thin as razorwire that stretched to cover hallways wasn’t possible for all but a master warder, but you could make other, similar contraptions that were purely meant to kill or maim, and Zinnia was a warder, if anything I’d learned about her was actually true. She was young, and that meant she couldn’t be at the top tier, but I also didn’t want to count out the possibility that this place had its own native warders.

My estimation of the size of the place went up with every door that we passed, and my estimation of how many of the cells held prisoners went down. Aside from those two guards, we’d seen no one. Some of those doors might have led to observation rooms, with guards inside them, but it was just too massive for it to be filled and fully staffed. The wards that were suppressing me, if that’s what they were, extended so far and so wide that it had to be a magical effect. Grak had told me there were some magical interactions that allowed a ward to cover a huge amount of space if extradimensional effects were in play.

There were twists and turns in the hallway, places where there were choices about where to go, and when we needed to make a decision, either Pallida would stoop to the ground and look for tracks or wear patterns, or Solace would pull out some fresh bit of druidic magic, always with some hesitation. Solace was shy about using magic, for reasons that she wasn’t entirely clear on, not a mana bar or spells per day or anything like that, but an ineffable something that could run out, or need repair, or something that probably defied an easy metaphor, just because that was how druidic magic normally worked (except when it didn’t, because druidic magic loved its exceptions).

Eventually we came to a turn in the corridors, and I pulled back the moment I saw what was waiting for me: five people had set up there, rifles drawn and pointed our way. I managed to not be hit mostly by virtue of quick reflexes, and ducked behind a part of the wall until the firing stopped. It was deafeningly loud in the confines of these hallways, echoing for a long time after it was over.

The five people had all been guards, the same as the ones before, wearing breastplate that might have been magical but not entadic, all close together.

“Bone blade,” I said to Pallida, holding out my hand. She gave me a skeptical look, but handed it over. I held the sword in one hand and the truncheon in the other.

“I can deal with them,” said Solace.

“No,” I replied. “Save it for when we really, desperately need it.”

“If there’s a mage?” asked Pallida. “And they’re not moving, if there’s a ward?”

“I’ll be fine,” I replied. Without another word, I slipped back around the corner and ran at full speed toward the weapons.

I’d thrown my truncheon before the first shot was fired, and began parrying the bullets as they came in. I hadn’t known for sure whether or not the sword would break if stuck by a bullet, but whatever magic Solace had conjured into it, it held through two deflections. A few of the bullets did hit me though, and that was what I was counting on.

The wires that made up my armor started snapping, their tension releasing in an absurdly destructive way that would have been physically impossible if magic weren’t involved. The angle of the wires snapping wasn’t quite right though, and all but one of them scored marks in the walls and on the doors. The last of them was a winner though, and got two of them in one blow, slashing into their faces ( defeated! ), with a third being struck across the breastplate and suffering a wound on his arm. I had gotten another one with the truncheon throw ( defeated! ), cracking his skull by way of his face, which meant that there were only two, and one of them was injured. The one who’d taken an injury stumbled back and began to run, and that left only one of them, who kept firing on me.

I swung the sword back and forth as I bore down on him, parrying the bullets as they came in. It was difficult work, but I was multithreading, splitting my focus on different parts of the combat in a way that only I could, and with only a single rifle, it was easy to deflect the shots. A lucky hit to my face would have killed me, but he was aiming for center mass.

I nearly stepped into the ward in front of me, noticing only just in time that the tip of my bone sword had vanished. I stopped short and moved the sword through the air, seeing more of it eaten away at a certain point down the hallway, not ten feet from where the guard was picking up one of the other rifles. I beat a hasty retreat, running as fast as I could back down to where Pallida and Solace were, hearing gunfire at my back and feeling another wire explode off just before I was around the corner.

“Fuck,” I said. “Bone annihilation ward. Killed three, or at least put them out for a bit.” One of the guards who’d gotten snapped with a wire to the face was still screaming. I looked to Pallida. “Knife?”

She handed me the knife that Zinnia had left behind in my cell. “Really not sure what we’re going to do if you get yourself killed.”

“I’ll be fine,” I replied. I went back around the corner, knife in one hand, bone blade in the other, only to find that the one remaining guard was gone. “Fucker,” I spat. “We’re clear,” I called to the others. “Or as clear as I think we’re going to be. There’s a bone annihilation ward, so be careful.”

“Fuck,” said Pallida as she came around the corner to look at the results of my brief encounter. “Is our plan to murder every guard in this place?” The guy who had been screaming had stopped, and no one was moving anymore ( defeated! ).

“If we have to,” I replied. “We should hurry, that was a retreating action on their part. They’ll be setting up better defenses later, and better that we get to them before they have a proper killzone set up.” On the plus side, the fact that they hadn’t used mages against us yet was a very good sign, as it meant that whatever blanket wards were over this place, they were preventing them from sending in a whole lot of mages against us. I was in my element with a sword, but without magic I wasn’t entirely clear on how I was meant to take on a revision mage. “Fuck, I think I need to use the last of my ink.”

“You just said we need to get going before they set up a killzone,” said Pallida.

“Yeah,” I replied. “I just don’t want to get fucked by a revision mage. I assume they would have one on hand for interrogation.” I turned to Solace. “Unless you could handle it?”

“I’m not sure,” said Solace. “I’ve never fought one before.”

I set to work, eyeing the bone ward. “Pallida, can you find a way around the ward for the two of you? I’m pretty sure that I can jump through it if I retract my soul.” I’d have to put another skill on the chopping block to get it done though, probably a utility skill. There was an argument for pushing Still Magic back up to 100 again, but I was loathe to do it, especially since I was worried about round two with the Pipe of Dreams.

Pallida took the bone sword and went forward, not looking too pleased as she scoped out the extent of the annihilation ward, which covered the entire area in front of us in a plane.

“You could have told me the bone sword would be a ward detector,” I said to Solace.

“I didn’t know,” she replied. “Juniper, you’re being reckless.”

“They shot you in the head,” I replied. “They have the locus. They tortured us.” I could hear the obvious objections that I would make to what I was saying, that just because they had marked themselves as enemies, just because they were assholes who deserved it, didn’t mean that the problem shouldn’t be approached calmly and reasonably, with due consideration of blah blah blah. My emotions were running hot, and multithreading wasn’t really helping. What Solace was saying was probably accurate: my decision-making was compromised.

“It’s only an observation,” said Solace. “Do with it what you will.”

Pallida returned by the time I had my teleporting chakram finished. It wasn’t shoddy work by any means, but I was asking a lot from ink magic, and it was a hard problem with tight bounds. If I threw the chakram at anyone, it would teleport right up to them, crossing the intervening distance in the blink of an eye. I could feel that it wasn’t very sturdy, maybe not even capable of lasting for more than a single shot. On a better day, I might have been able to come up with a better design, something that felt like it was an elegant sideways approach to the problem of a revision mage.

“Ward’s down,” she said. “Disappeared on its own. Warder probably didn’t want to use much juice on it, which means power banked for the killzone.”

“Then let’s go,” I said, looking over the corpses. “Looks like there are rifles for the taking.”

Transgressions

The corridors got wider as we went, in a way that was pretty subtle, until eventually I was staring down a hallway looking at a cavernously large room. Zinnia was standing there waiting for us, feet shoulder-width apart, holding a cleaver in one hand and staring at me. In her other hand, she held her wand, and her monocle was fixed in place over her eye. The entad handbag was on the floor by her feet. Her brother was nowhere to be seen, nor were any of the other staff or guards, if there were other staff or guards. Behind her were wide doors, closed, with a collection of pallets beside them. I had a stolen rifle slung over my shoulder and a truncheon in my hand, with the teleporting chakram in the other. The armor I’d made for myself was about half used up, if I had to guess, though I wasn’t sure whether it would lose coherence or run out of wires first.

“How’d you get out?” she asked, raising her voice to let herself be heard across the distance.

“Magic,” I called back. “Give us back Raven and our entads and we’ll leave.”

I saw Zinnia’s hand flex on the cleaver. “You’re never getting out of here,” she said. “Drop your weapons and remove your armor, then lay down on the ground with your hands behind your back. This area is laced through with annihilation wards that will kill you if you approach. If you attack me, or come any closer, I will kill you and let the demons have their way with your souls.”

“Right,” I said. I started walking toward her. “The thing is, if you just go giving in to any old threat, then you end up ruled by threats.” I was really, really afraid of running smack into one of those wards she’d mentioned, and pushed against my various magics to see whether I was through some critical threshold or not, because I really didn’t want to go into this fight so cripplingly handicapped as I was.

When she realized that I intended to keep going, Zinnia reared back and threw her cleaver at me as hard as she could. I parried it with the truncheon, easily, given the distance between us and the difficulties inherent in throwing something like that, then turned back to her, thinking that there was about even odds that it was a distraction.

Unfortunately for me, the balance of probability was the other way, and I wasn’t quite fast enough to dodge the cleaver as it rocketed toward me from where it had clattered to the floor. It caught me in my left arm, snapping one of the threads that made up my armor, though the snapping attack the armor was supposed to do had either missed or was ineffective against the entad cleaver. I wasn’t sure how well it had stopped the attack, given that I couldn’t feel pain anymore. When the cleaver came at me a third time, launched through the air as though flicked by an enormous, invisible hand, I was ready, and managed to avoid another hit.

I was well aware that I was spending a lot of time and effort fighting a magic cleaver while Zinnia was left to her own devices, and I tried multi-threading to focus on her while I continued my battle with the entad, which didn’t work as well as it might have, given that I only had a single set of eyes which were focused on the cleaver by necessity. I did notice, in a brief moment when my eyes passed over her, that she was reaching into the handbag, which didn’t bode well. The chakram was ready to throw at her, but I felt a need to save it, because if the chakram ran into a ward, that was that.

Solace and Pallida were behind me, but Pallida was moving forward much more slowly than I was, probably because she had a proper fear of unknown wards. Solace seemed to be casting a spell of some kind, or doing the druid equivalent, which I could mostly tell from the way nature seemed to be creeping into the world, starting with her. Grass was growing from the floor and roots were sprouting, but their purpose was unknown. Whatever she might accomplish, I was hoping that it would be worth her time and effort.

After the sixth time being attacked by the cleaver, I decided that it probably wasn’t going to stop on a timescale that I would find preferable. That being the case, I needed a better approach than the one I was using, which largely involved dodging and parrying it as it came in. I acted on instinct and tossed the truncheon and chakram to the floor, then squatted slightly and held both hands in front of me, readying myself to catch the murderous weapon.

I didn’t get it on the first attempt, which snapped another thread of my armor, but I got it on the second try, catching it by the handle when it was inches from my unprotected face. Soul sight let me see entads, but only those entads that were connected to a soul in some way, usually by means of inheritance rules or binding. The cleaver hadn’t shown up at all, which meant that it was one of those entads that had no particular loyalties or restrictions. Once I’d caught it, it was mine.

I reared back and threw the cleaver at Zinnia, thankful that I still had Thrown Weapon on my character sheet, but when it was halfway to her face, it vanished entirely, disappearing into some void or another that had swallowed it whole.

“Oh come on,” I muttered, but I didn’t have time to be forlorn, because Zinnia pulled a void rifle out of her handbag, one that was longer than her handbag should have allowed. She aimed it squarely at me, and I scooped up my weapons and began running toward her at a zig-zag, hoping that she wasn’t a trained warder and a master markswoman. My strategy with regards to the potential bone or blood annihilation wards was to hope that they weren’t there, which was, admittedly, not terribly wise. I took off down the wide hallway, out toward the open room.

At the range we were at, she was only going to get one shot with a void rifle, so after the first thunk left me free of any gaping wounds, I relaxed a hair, only to see her pull a lever on the side of the rifle and watch it rotate some bulky mechanism around. The second shot hit me right in the chest, poking a clean hole into the meat of my pectoral and into the lung. I didn’t even feel it at first, not until I took a breath and felt what I would later figure out was a collapsing lung. All I knew was that I was hit and having trouble breathing.

The second bit of bad news came right after that, as my leg collapsed out from under me. I fell to the ground and rolled forward, stopping for just a moment to confirm that my calf was bent nearly in half, with a fair bit of the bone presumably removed. There was, naturally, no pain, for which I was thankful, and my foot seemed to be intact. My plan had been to get to Zinnia and pray that I could either find a way to fight her without closing to within the range of her wards, or to get some scrap of magic back that I could come at her with. Failing that, I would pull up the rifle and just shoot her, but there was virtually no way that would work.

The third bit of bad news was that I had stepped beyond the end of the hallway, into the large room Zinnia was in the middle of, which made it clear that she’d been standing there as bait: there were a dozen people standing back with weapons at the ready, hidden by the walls before but now clearly visible to me. Right into the killbox.

As I crossed the threshold into the big room, there were other sensations, ones that had been suppressed, and that was the only good news: I had my magic back.

I started burning one of the three unicorn bones at the same time I pushed vibration magic hard enough to give me warder’s sight. A fraction of a second later, they opened fire on me, and I died almost instantly.

Have you ever been playing a videogame and chose exactly the wrong moment to save? One of my clearest videogame memories was playing Skyrim and quicksaving right as I’d aggroed some enemies. I fought the battle a dozen times, using increasingly desperate measures, until finally I decided that the save was a doomed world where I was going to die no matter what I did.

The short version is that I was killed about a dozen times in rapid succession. Still magic could take care of the ones using bullets, but some of them were using void weapons, which couldn’t be stopped by any means that I had available to me. I had just a split second each time, and while I could burn two bones at once, the extra speed from the second just wasn’t helping me enough, and the unicorn bone was being drained way too fast by the repeated deaths. I started burning the second when I felt the first’s power start to slip, and lucked into a workable strategy after that, with a hand raised to soak some of the void fire, the fear aspect of passion magic to move out of the way, and a turn of my head just enough so that the void would tunnel through the thick of my skull, missing the gray matter of my brain.

Once I was through that first volley, my options expanded out considerably. I was down a leg, but up a considerable amount of magic, and while I wasn’t incredibly proficient at one-legged combat, I was burning through limited resources at a rapid pace, which always helped. I leapt with my one good leg, the other flopping below me, over one of the ribbon wards and through a small gap between two others, landing back on my good leg again. More bullets were coming in, and instantly stopped against my skin, but the void weapons seemed to have been spent for the time being. I was still some distance from Zinnia, and I didn’t think that I would be able to get there by hopping, even hopping really fast —

And then with a flash, there was something black over my eyes.

I’d been burning speed, in addition to the unicorn bone, which was the only reason that I saw so much as a single frame of a woman moving in, obvious only in retrospect because the image of her was the last thing my eyes had seen. Velocity mage. I hadn’t fought one yet, having narrowly avoided an encounter with one in Barren Jewel, but I had done some theorycrafting with the party about how best to handle it. I felt the woman trying to stab me with needles, which my still magic stopped, and then let time loop back once more.

This time when I took a hit to the skull, it was a little bit better, bleeding profusely but leaving me clear-headed in the non-literal sense, and I managed to hop my way through the wards again, using my one good leg, and stopping the bullets that were impacting me. This time, when the speedster came at me, I was ready. She only touched me for a fraction of a second, but I knew when and where that was going to be, and our brief contact was enough for me to stop her in her tracks with the tape poised and ready to go over my eyes. I barely had time to register her species as ‘not-human’ before spinning myself around and kicking her with the knee of my bad leg, which sent her backward through one of the ribbon wards. She came through it far worse than I did, and I doubted that she would survive (a defeated! popping up for her as good as confirmed it).

I was still hampered by my mobility, with too much distance to cover, but I finally made it long enough to see what Solace had been cooking up. From back in the hallway, a bolt of lightning cracked overhead, then broke apart and branched down to strike both my left and right at the places where the guards were flanking me. I was momentarily blinded but kept hopping forward all the same, hoping that Zinnia would be likewise impaired.

The amplified vibration magic let me see her wards, and aside from the ribbon wards that were designed to kill or incapacitate someone, there was a ward that completely surrounded her, probably not more than five feet in diameter. Though I could see the ward, I couldn’t tell what it did, and I was fearing the worst, which was that it would be impossible for me to get through it. Warders got themselves into siege situations from time to time, and I didn’t think that I would come out the winner, not if she picked that double-barreled void rifle back up, or whatever else she had in her magical handbag. I hadn’t seen or heard of a storage entad as powerful as Sable in terms of raw capacity, but ones with lower limits were pretty common. There were all kinds of tricks that you could pack into a space like that.

I noticed the discontinuity right away as Zinnia changed position. I had my chakram in hand and I’d been waiting for it, the telltale sign of a revision mage doing their work. I wasn’t clear on exactly why I had been revised, but my guess was that I’d found success somewhere, or the revision mage was trying to soak up my resources or keep me pinned down. It could have been that he was trying to protect Zinnia, but I never found out, because there was another discontinuity and I died not long after that, having locked eyes with the man out of uniform I pegged as the revision mage.

I did the whole thing over again, taking down the velocity mage when she closed the distance, closing my eyes for the lightning, then throwing the chakram at the revision mage and counting on the HUD instead of my eyesight to see whether it worked (the defeated! message followed soon after). I also spotted, for the first time, a form on the floor writhing with pus and boils, what I assumed to be a pustule mage hit by Solace’s lightning and regrowing a new self, but I had a target, and it wasn’t him.

I made bounding hops, avoiding the ribbon wards, and blasted out magic at Zinnia as I went toward her, first trying a pulse of vibration magic, which had no effect, then using air magic to sweep away her oxygen, which might have worked through her wards but simply been ineffective. I was desperately missing the gem that I had secreted away, because this would have been a great time to blast away.

When I got to the ward surrounding her, she was in the middle of picking back up the void rifle. It couldn’t possibly have been long enough for it to be charged up, because this was all happening incredibly fast, but she surely had something planned.

I decided against keeping the timeline and swiped through the ward with my hand, wanting to see what kind it was. The bones of my hand vanished entirely, leaving it flopping down without anything to give the ligaments tension against, but the blood felt like it remained.

When the loop restarted, I dodged the void, getting another grazing shot straight through my skull, then began hopping my way over the wards so I could get to Zinnia again. I stilled the velocity mage when she came and kicked her through the ribbon wards, putting her out of commission if not necessarily killing her, screwed my eyes shut for the lightning from Solace, threw my chakram at the revision mage, and kept going until I got to Zinnia. This time I was ready for her ward, and smashed through it by throwing a claret spear of blood. It struck her in the body suit but failed to pierce, because as suspected, the suit was either entadic or some special material. I could loosely control my blood outside my own body though, and used it to grip her as tightly as I could. She would definitely have been able to struggle free, but my blood was a conduit for my soul, and I applied the full force of my still magic against her, stopping her completely in place.

“Stop shooting or I kill her!” I tried to shout, but it came out as a wheeze, because something was wrong with my lung. “Stop!” I tried again, looking to the people flanking us, but most of them had already been struck down by Solace, and no one was even actively shooting at me anymore. The pile of pus was heaving, but not doing much else, and I wasn’t sure that a lone pustule mage would try to save the day on his own even if he could recover in time.

I looked around the room, frantically trying to see if anyone was hiding. There were doors behind Zinnia, and more doors around the perimeter of the room. I didn’t see Yarrow anywhere, which was concerning, but at least I knew what branch of magic he’d studied, and he was really unlikely to be a multimage, especially if his cover story of being an entad specialist was true. Solace’s lightning had killed or incapacitated a half dozen people. I allowed the loop to collapse into normal reality, and watched Zinnia’s eyes go wide as she realized what had happened.

I burnt one of my bones for healing, patching the place where I was missing a bit of skull, the hole in my chest from Zinnia’s void rifle, and a second wound that I hadn’t even realized I’d had from another void shot. My leg couldn’t be healed, because I was missing bone and couldn’t regrow it, ditto the hole in my skull if not the skin and flesh on top of it, and my lung was still fucky, because I didn’t know the first thing about collapsed lungs, and by healing the wound, I had trapped a bunch of air in the lung cavity. I was quite short of breath, and getting to the point where I would need to worry about blood loss, and down a leg, but otherwise fine.

“Where’s Raven?” I asked Zinnia. I was breathing heavily and trying to heal myself better, which wasn’t working.

Zinnia’s mouth moved a fraction of an inch, and I realized that I was stilling her so completely that she couldn’t even breathe, let alone talk. I released my grip on her, just a bit.

“We never had Raven,” she said, gasping for breath.

“Bullshit,” I replied, taking in a sharp breath of my own. I was worried about what would happen when I turned pain back on, but I was clearly going to have to, since I had gotten fairly injured without even realizing it. It had been so much easier when I was moving, but the adrenaline was starting to fade, leaving me worn down.

“We didn’t,” replied Zinnia. “The pipe didn’t work on her. We only got away because I threw my dress at her.”

“A dress?” I asked, having trouble pushing out enough air for more words. I looked back to see where Solace was, hoping that she would be able to fix whatever was fucked up with me, and saw that she and Pallida were still back where they had been, behind a barrier that Solace had erected of vines mixed with hair. A pile of dead vines stretched out from where they were, which might have been part of what made the lightning, or possibly were just some decoration that Solace had wanted. Naturally, neither of them had been able to see where the wards were, and neither had been so foolhardy as to rush the wards. Unfortunately, I couldn’t move back to them without letting Zinnia go.

“The dress is a binder, sticks to who you throw it at and pins them in place,” said Zinnia. “We left it behind with her at the castle.”

“Fine,” I replied. My blood was touching her, and I was holding her in place with still magic, but the blood wouldn’t last as a conduit of my soul forever. Hells, it didn’t seem like it was even going to last until the end of this conversation. If I could get into her soul — but it would take too much time. “Our gear.”

Maybe she saw it in my eyes, or maybe in my voice, but she must have realized that all she needed to do was to wait me out. Maybe that was why she’d been talking about some stupid dress.

“Your brother,” I said, gasping for air, but I had nothing to follow that up with, nothing to convince Zinnia to submit to me before my blood stopped being my blood and started to just be blood.

I sang, just a single note, and the sound carried through the ward. She’d set up part of her shell to prevent vibration magic, but it only stopped magic from getting through the shell, and with my blood acting as an extension of my soul, I was effectively in there with her. I amplified the sound of my note immensely, then changed my mind at the last moment, vibrating her skull instead of exploding her head with a pressure wave. By the end of it, blood was coming down from her nose, and she collapsed down to the ground, unmoving, as my blood in there with her finally stopped being connected to my soul.

Zinnia Penndraig defeated!

“Fucker,” I said, but I didn’t really feel it. I had come very close to killing her. She would have deserved it.

I turned around and started hopping back toward Pallida and Solace, trying to keep my eyes on the remaining men on either side of the room. They weren’t shooting anymore, just tending to the wounded and giving me nervous looks. They didn’t look like I would expect a crack team of mercenaries or military members to look, instead reminding me more of mall security guards, notwithstanding the breastplates they wore. If I had the measure of this place right, they were just guards, not expected to be in full-on magical armed conflict. They had three mages among them, all down now (the lump of boils had stopped moving, the growth stillborn), which was the extent of their forces. I was immune to their conventional weapons thanks to still magic, and if any of them were thinking about picking their void weapons back up, they hadn’t made that choice just yet. I hadn’t used the rifle on my back.

By the time I got back to Pallida and Solace, I was out of breath of both varieties, the kind in my lungs and the mana that vibrational magic ran on, in part because I was using it to see where the wards were, pulsing it on and off so I didn’t run into another of the ribbon wards.

When I got behind the barrier that Solace had made, she was breathing hard too. “Overdid it,” she said.

“You did well,” I replied. “Some still standing. Broke their will.”

“You looked insane out there,” said Pallida. “Watched you die a dozen times, but still, all that flipping, hopping, and dodging, that was nuts. Also pretty nuts to run straight up to a warder like that, but what do I know. How’d you know you’d get your magic back?”

“I didn’t,” I replied. “Just a feeling.” I thought that if they had mages here, they would want them as weapons of last resort at the entrance. I had no clue how the antimagic was set up here, since I hadn’t seen a giant ward cutting off the big room from the hallway, but I guessed that it was a big blanket over this place, and given their conventional weapons gambit in the earlier hallway had failed, my guess was that their mages here couldn’t operate deeper into the facility. I was short on breath for explanations though.

“Are we going to be able to get out of here?” asked Solace. She was sweating, for no obvious reason.

“Probably,” I replied. “Lungs fucked,” I added, pointing to my chest.

Solace slowly climbed to her feet and touched her small hand to my chest. She closed her eyes for a moment and frowned, then I felt a warmth inside me and an instant easing of pressure, and then more in my leg as it straightened out. As soon as it was done, she collapsed.

“Fuck,” I said as I caught her. “That’s not good.”

“I didn’t know druids could collapse,” said Pallida.

“Never count out a druid,” I replied. “She’s been pushing it, and she’s far from the locus, and I guess it makes sense that she can’t be running full blast forever.”

“So you and me are going through those wards?” asked Pallida. “We’re carrying her?”

“I will, yeah,” I replied. “I have a unicorn bone left, if we really need it.”

“And we ask one of these fuckers where our stuff is?” asked Pallida.

“Yeah,” I replied. “Might have to soul fuck one of them.”

“Shit,” she replied with a frown. “If you do that, better to kill them all. We should be thinking about what we’re going to do when we’re out of here.”

“We don’t even know where we are,” I replied. “I’m not going to kill a bunch of people who have surrendered just because … why would I?” I glanced at Zinnia on the floor. She wasn’t moving. She still showed up colored in soul sight, which I thought probably meant she was still alive, at least for now.

“You’re a soul mage,” said Pallida. “Registered, but not authorized for anything even remotely like this, whatever country we’re even in right now. Even if it were legal, that’s not the kind of battle that Amaryllis is fighting right now.”

“We’ve got no fucking clue what kind of battle she’s fighting,” I replied. “They attacked us, kidnapped us, and tortured us. Fuck them. For all we know, she’s dead.”

“Right,” said Pallida. “So we kill everyone here and make sure there are no witnesses.”

“That’s not what I mean,” I replied. “You’re talking about killing people because that’s better press.”

“You’re talking about soul fucking someone because you want your things back,” said Pallida. “I don’t think you get how seriously these people take it. It’s not something that you do casually. You know what a soul mage is expected to do if he’s forced to act against his oath at gunpoint?”

“No,” I shook my head.

“He’s expected to take the bullet,” replied Pallida.

“Fine,” I replied. I looked down at Solace. “How long do you think she’ll be out for?”

“At least until we’re out of danger,” replied Pallida.

“Alright,” I said, lifting up Solace and slinging her over my shoulder. “We’re going to try this without killing or soul fucking first.”

I walked forward, carrying Solace, thankful to once again have two working legs. Whatever Solace had done to my leg hadn’t been regrowing of bone but something else, and it felt funny, like I had a lump in the middle of the bone where she’d fixed me. I stepped over the ribbon ward that had initially eaten through my leg, and watched as Pallida navigated it. I was running dangerously low on vibration magic though, and the costs for being able to see the magic were escalating. In retrospect, using so much of my power to incapacitate Zinnia was going to bite me in the ass, and I should have used something else instead, but I was a novice with passion magic, the other obvious choice. Over the course of the seconds-long battle, I had barely even used it.

When we got into the larger chamber, many of the guards had cleared out. They hadn’t moved across the midfield, for the obvious reason that they couldn’t, not unless they knew where all the ribbon wards were. I was pretty sure that was also keeping them from communicating with each other, unless they had just happened to fall into opposing camps. The left side had weapons aimed down but still held, in a threatening way, while the right side seemed like they were trying to pretend that we didn’t exist as they went through the process of triage, their weapons physically thrown or slid away from them. I saw that some of them had runed spikes and were going through to remove the souls of the dead.

“Parley!” shouted a man on the left side.

“Sure!” I called back. I moved toward him, ducking below a ribbon and being careful not to get Solace caught in it, then jumping over another. Pallida stayed back, not wanting to risk it. I was pulsing the warder’s sight, using it only for long enough to guide my way and trusting in my heightened sense of space from a dozen different senses to keep me informed of where the wards were. I was really hopeful that they would go away soon, as they obviously were meant to be short duration. I stopped a fair distance from the guards, in part because there were more ribbons that I didn’t want to go over.

“Who are you?” asked the tallest of the guards, though he was only tall for a human, and not quite my height. “What do you want here?”

“I want my stuff, and I want to get out,” I replied. “When they brought us in, was there a fourth? A young woman, maybe seventeen years old, dark hair?”

“They put on hoods,” replied the guard. “Just three though. You didn’t answer who you were.”

“Just to be clear, are you planning to shoot me?” I asked.

“We saw you die,” said one of the guards. “Saw you die a couple of times.”

“Where am I right now?” I asked, focusing my attention on the taller man.

“It’s a holding facility,” he replied. “We’re a hundred miles north of the Spine of the World, in the Tentar Territory.”

“And where is my stuff?” I asked. “The things that I came in with?”

“That happened offsite,” he replied.

“Then my stuff was brought in with me,” I said. “Because I know for a fact that our entads aren’t far from here.”

“If you’re trying to strong-arm me, it’s not going to work,” the guard replied. “What I know is that four hours ago the three of you were brought in here, stripped of your clothes and with some superficial wounds, on gurneys.” He was still holding a rifle, which was still pointed at the ground, ready to raise in a fraction of a second. Not aimed at me, but more aimed at me than I was comfortable with for a rifle. If we’d been at the gun range, he would have been seriously breaching both etiquette and proper safety.

“Do you think I’m fucking around here?” I asked. “Or are you just trying to cover your ass?”

“Look,” he said. “We don’t want any more violence. Opinions are mixed on whether you have souls left in the tank, but fuck if I want to find out one way or another. But after this is over? Life is still going to keep on going. There are going to be inquiries. We don’t put things down on paper here for a reason. And I’ve personally got no clue who you are, because it’s not my business to know, and because if I get pulled in front of a panel of judges and asked, I want to not know. If I need to say things to you that are going to fuck my life up? Well, you can see where I would rather take chances with trying violence.”

Oh fuck off. “Alright,” I replied. “Then I guess we’ll try violence.”

Generally speaking, letting your opponent know what you were going to do before you did it was pretty bad strategy, and this was no exception. The reason I’d done it, aside from just the anger and frustration that had been continually building without release since I’d got here, was that it didn’t really matter. I didn’t have all that much range on my passion magic, but I had enough to push out a telekinetic blast that reached them, first the younger guard holding the void rifle, then the one that hadn’t spoken. I aimed at their weapons and ended up cutting through fingers and hands as well. For the leader of their little group, I grabbed and threw the truncheon, hitting him in the leg before his rifle was even halfway up, which was one of the benefits of being as fast as I was. I did all of this while still holding Solace.

“Okay,” I said, over the cries of the guards. “I’ve been drugged, tied up, and tortured, and I’ll fucking kill every last fucking one of you if you don’t tell me exactly what I want to know.”

“You broke my fucking leg!” screamed the taller guard, who had fallen down onto the floor.

“I don’t give a shit,” I replied through gritted teeth.

“Joon!” called Pallida. “Stop dicking around!”

“Alright,” I said, setting Solace down, moving forward, jumping over a ribbon and then ducking under another. The guards were scrambling back, getting their weapons in position. “Here’s the thing —”

The taller guard fired, not at me, but at Solace, for what reason, I couldn’t comprehend. I caught the bullet in my palm and gave him a dirty look. It was less impressive than it sounded, since I was just tracking the barrel of his gun, not actually moving my hand faster than a bullet.

I ran at him and snatched the rifle from his hands, then bashed him in the face with the butt of it once, enough to break his nose. I hesitated for a moment, standing over him, then picked him up and threw him through the ribbon wards. It didn’t kill him, but he was laced through with empty cavities where a lot of his bones had been, and there were shards of bone sticking out where the ribbon wards had annihilated bone at a steep angle.

Oscar Sikes defeated!

“I’m done fucking around,” I said to the remaining two. One of them was crying and gathering up his fingers, so I turned to the other, who was just clutching his wounded hand and hissing in pain, his weapon apparently forgotten beside him, not that it was functional anymore. “Did we come in here with anyone else? Was it just us three?”

“Three prisoners,” he replied with a gasp. “A prince and a princess. Something had happened to the prince. He was out of it.”

“No girl?” I asked. “Seventeen, black hair?”

“No,” he replied. “And we don’t have your things, you were stripped down when they brought you. That one, the princess, she’s got an entad, we weren’t required to check it when she came.”

“Who are your bosses?” I asked.

“My boss?” he asked. “You just killed him.”

“And who is his boss?” I asked.

“I don’t know,” he replied, hissing again. “Why would I know?”

“Then tell me who you’ve seen come in here,” I said. “Give me names, princes and princesses.”

“I don’t fucking know!” he shouted. “Most of them wore masks, or something else.”

“I know,” said the other. He had come closer to me but hadn’t touched his weapon, and so I’d mostly ignored him. He held out his dismembered fingers to me, which were held in bloody-slick hands. “You’re a healer.”

“I put your fingers back on, you tell me, that’s your plan?” I asked.

He nodded. He was damp with sweat and looking up at me from on his knees.

“Tell me, then I’ll heal you,” I said.

“Onion,” he said without hesitation. “And Larkspur, when he was still alive, in a mask but with his armor. Three women, all in masks, not sure who they were. Another two men, together, they were younger from their voices.”

I wanted to kill him. I wasn’t normally very bloodthirsty, but I was pissed off at this whole thing, and the way he’d come to me, fingers in hand, trying to extort healing from me … it rubbed me the wrong way. It would have been easy to kill him, simple and effortless in a half dozen ways, because I was strong and he was weak. He’d fucking shot at me, not too many minutes prior, and he was a guard at some fantasy version of Gitmo, but before I could talk myself into cutting his throat in half with passion magic, I grabbed his fingers, put them back where they needed to go, and healed him.

“Alright,” I replied. “How do we get out of here?”

“Door,” he said, pointing at a door on the far wall, fifty feet behind where Zinnia had been standing. “There’s a separate facility outside this place, staging and dorms. But we’re in the middle of nowhere, and no one comes here except by magic.” He moved his hand, flexing the fingers to make sure they worked, and looking at me with something like awe.

“So you’re stranded,” I said. “Stuck here until there’s a shift change?”

“It’s another two and a half months,” he replied. “There’s a bulk teleport for resupply, not sure how often, but you could get a letter out.”

“Fuck,” I replied. I pulled away from him and looked at Solace. “Alright, start pulling souls, if I see any of you with a weapon, I’ll kill you just out of caution.”

The guard gave me a nod.

“Wait,” I said. “Where’s the prince who came here? Yarrow?”

“In one of the rooms,” replied the guard. “We’re not usually told which unless we need to know, and I didn’t need to know. I don’t know who does know.”

“Fine,” I replied.

I pulsed vibration magic and took a moment to confirm what was apparent at first glance: the ribbon wards were gone. I still made a show of jumping and ducking on my way over to Solace, and I did the same returning to where Pallida was standing.

“Well,” I said. “We’re in the middle of nowhere, Solace is still sleeping it off or whatever, and if there’s a magical return to civilization, then the path is probably through Zinnia, who, if she’s not dead, will only help us through compulsion. Yarrow is somewhere in the facility, but I don’t know where, and Zinnia might be the only one who knows. The only plus side is that the wards are gone.”

“Peachy,” replied Pallida. “So, are we walking or what?”

“I’ll try to rouse Zinnia and we’ll go from there,” I replied. “Assuming that she’s still alive.”

Paladin

There was a fair bit of mopping up to do. I sent one of the guards down into the expansive site in order to bottle the souls of the other guards I killed, hoping that by the time he got there, the timer wouldn’t have run down. You were supposed to have thirty minutes from the time of death, but that was the guideline that everyone went by, and I had no idea whether that was an overly cautious lower bound to ensure that people moved quickly in a time of crisis, an overly conservative upper bound to make sure that people would keep trying even after hope should rightfully have been lost, or just where the average happened to sit. I had little conception of how much time had actually passed, except that it was probably too late for the first set of guards, but probably not for the second. I was hoping that whatever druidic fuckery Solace had done when she’d pulled out their bones would keep them from the hells, but she wasn’t awake to ask.

This wasn’t simply a matter of compassion or professional courtesy. Aside from the natal souls, new people in the hells were a rarity, enough that if there were sufficient levels of unification, it might be possible for them to interrogate anyone who fell within certain criteria, which a guard from an Anglecynn blacksite definitely did. The guards hadn’t seen all that much, I didn’t think, but it was information leaked to the enemy, which would be good to avoid if at all possible. I was hoping to stay off the hells’ radar for as long as possible.

The rest of the guards we stripped of their weapons and shoved into an empty cell, which we locked them in. One of them had a lot of questions about food and water, which I didn’t have any good answers for, because there was no way that I was planning on keeping them as prisoners in the long term, and I didn’t know if I could release them.

The last thing left to do was to sweep through their secondary building, the one outside of the entad structure, mostly to make sure that we’d rounded up everyone and wouldn’t be blindsided. That took a half hour or so, and netted us three more guards, who promptly got thrown into a different cell, along with the guard who had gathered up the souls for us (in time for the second group, not for the first, as I’d feared).

A quick trip topside confirmed that we were in the middle of fucking nowhere. The whole complex was underground, with the only things poking up top being ventilation, a single access door that was hidden beneath a fake tree, and a very small stable that was, for some reason, filled with dire guinea pigs. The Tentar Territory was quite large, and we were somewhere in the middle of it, in a place only accessible by magic. It was the middle of the night, and I looked up at the stars for a moment, wishing that I knew enough about astronomy to do some celestial navigation, and also wishing that astronomy worked like that on Aerb, which it did not.

The last thing to do before interrogating Zinnia was to try to reestablish communications with Amaryllis and Grak, which I did through the link between our souls, pushing up values for just long enough that they would notice and understand. It wasn’t a very good form of communication, and I got nothing in return from them, which might have been because they were sleeping or otherwise occupied. I was at least able to confirm that they were safe, though that wasn’t terribly much comfort, because ‘safe’ only applied to their souls. We had other methods of soul communication, but I wanted to try other, less laborious and error-prone methods of communication before I resorted to that. If Amaryllis and Grak were safe, then any message was mostly to give them peace-of-mind and make sure they didn’t try to mount a rescue effort that wasn’t needed, and if they were in danger, then I was too far away to help. At best, Amaryllis would have a worldline that went to the black site and could pick us up with the teleportation key, but I was skeptical of that.

I worked with Pallida to strip and check over Zinnia, making sure that she didn’t have any hidden entads, then dressed her up in a hospital gown we grabbed from a bin near the front of the large room. Our final step was to put her in manacles, hands and feet, with the chains running through each other behind her back, then heal her. She wasn’t unconscious through this whole time, just drifting in and out of awareness, mostly out, with slurred speech and eyes not really focusing. Doing it this way, waiting so long, was a bit dangerous, because the soul responded to the body, and for our purposes, I didn’t really want her permanently brain damaged. There was a chance that had already happened, and if that was the case, I wasn’t sure what our options were: we couldn’t get anything out of her handbag, and I was pretty sure that was where our entads were.

It took some time for Zinnia to surface from whatever fuckery was going on in her head. When she finally did, she took a moment to look around, then assumed a placid expression.

“I have questions,” I said.

She gave no response.

“My first is where my stuff is,” I said. “So, where’s my stuff?”

She didn’t so much as look at me, and I rolled my eyes.

“Alright, so here’s the thing: we put all the guards into one of the cells, and the only witnesses to what’s happening here are me, you, and this woman here,” I said, pointing at Pallida, “And she doesn’t actually give a fuck what happens to you.”

Still there was no response.

“Someone sent you here,” I said. “My guess is that after a long enough time without a report back, they’ll send someone to see what’s happened here. That’s my best guess about what the fuck you think you’re doing here. I’m not asking for state secrets here, I’m just asking for my things back so I can get on my way. Heck, I’m not even asking who sent you in to tangle with us.”

Zinnia looked at me. “I already told you it was Hyacinth,” she said.

“And why did you tell us that?” asked Pallida.

Zinnia stayed silent. I was glad that she’d at least proven that she could speak, because that meant she hadn’t been too badly injured when I’d rattled her skull.

“Accountability?” I guessed. “Setting her up for the fall if something went sideways?”

There was no expression on Zinnia’s face whatsoever. It was like talking to a brick wall.

“Alright,” said Pallida, “Here’s where I think you could maybe justify fucking her soul.”

“Not legally,” said Zinnia, looking at Pallida.

“Legally?” I asked with a laugh. “We’re in a fucking government black site, do you think that I give a goat’s shit about what’s legal? You tried to fuck my soul.”

“You have no proof of that,” replied Zinnia.

“Yeah?” I asked. “And how the fuck else do you explain that your brother ended up smacked in the face by a meme which literally only exists in my head?” And by literally, I meant figuratively.

“He was looking for evidence of soul manipulation, not trying to make any changes,” replied Zinnia.

“Are you fucking serious right now?” I asked. I looked over at Pallida, then back at Zinnia. “Alright, I’m willing to accept that all this was somehow legal,” I said, gesturing to the black site. “Or if not legal, then at least capable of surviving some level of scrutiny that ends with some ‘bad apples’ being put in prison or otherwise scapegoated. There’s plausible deniability for your fuckwit brother to look at my soul, given that he’s got some kind of registration, which means that he can make some changes and then make some other changes to set them back later, without anyone as a witness and a revision mage to make sure that not even memories are left. You’re playing it cool because you somehow think that this is still about legality, or the politics of Anglecynn, or something like that. Well, it’s not, and I don’t really care that I don’t have the legal authority here. Heck, I wouldn’t even care if I didn’t have moral authority, but of course, I do. So this is your last chance to do it the easy way and just answer a few questions that won’t break classification or reveal anything you don’t want revealed.”

Zinnia didn’t reply, didn’t make eye contact, just stared to the side, avoiding looking at me.

“Alright,” I said.

I pushed her from her knees down onto the ground and sat on top of her, pinning her down, while I breached into her soul. She struggled a bit, but she didn’t scream for help, and it was all over pretty quickly. My alterations weren’t clever or subtle, they were just a matter of pushing up a single value, ‘Juniper Smith’ into the stratosphere. I pulled her back to her feet and came around to look at her. The change was immediately noticeable: she was looking at me, watching me, no longer cold.

“Tell me where my stuff is,” I said.

“I can’t,” she replied, sounding pained.

I frowned. “Why not?”

“Because I can’t,” she replied.

“Can you tell me why you can’t tell me?” I asked.

“I just … I can’t tell you anything,” she said. She looked uncomfortable, and glanced at Pallida more than once.

“Are you under some magical compulsion or memetic effect?” I asked, knowing that the answer would probably be ‘I can’t tell you’.

“I’m not allowed to say,” she replied.

“Allowed by who?” I asked.

She closed her eyes and took a deep breath. “I can’t say anything else about it.”

I looked over at Pallida. “Well, what the fuck is this?” I asked.

Pallida frowned. “Not sure,” she replied.

“Alright,” I said, turning back to Zinnia. “You’re perfectly capable of answering questions, so tell me which questions you can answer.”

“I can’t,” she replied.

“Hold on a sec,” I replied. “You answered questions before, why aren’t you doing it now?”

“I — I can’t say,” she replied.

I was getting frustrated, but more than that, I was confused. As Amaryllis had described it to me, being soulfucked in this crude way was a change in perspective. From everything I knew, Zinnia should have been talking, answering questions.

“What’s linear protocol?” I asked.

“I can’t say,” she replied.

“Yarrow mentioned it when you were questioning him to see whether I’d done anything to him,” I said. “You pressed him, and he said that he had always been good at linear protocol. What is it?”

“I can’t,” replied Zinnia.

“It would make me very happy if you replied,” I said. “If you don’t answer me, if I don’t find out, then my options might start to run out. You know that if there aren’t already people on the way, then they’ll eventually get here. If you keep this up, there’s a good chance that I die, either against whatever forces get sent in, or trying to make my way through the wilderness to civilization. So please, if you can’t tell me where my entads are, then at least tell me what linear protocol is?”

Zinnia watched me for a moment and then took a breath. “It’s training,” she said. “You don’t try to resist the compulsion, you ignore it. You just follow the script.”

“That seems like it wouldn’t work,” I replied. “You depend on your values to decide on what to do.”

“No,” replied Zinnia. “You don’t. Or you don’t have to. You just … act.”

I was inherently skeptical of this idea. “Alright,” I replied. “So you’re just saying that you can’t … on instinct? Like some swordsman who’s trained for a dozen years to get to the point where everything is automatic, nothing passes through his head?”

Zinnia nodded slowly.

“And what’s the penalty for not following linear protocol?” I asked. “What do you get out of it?”

“Nothing,” replied Zinnia. “It wouldn’t work if I was doing it for something. It’s not about that. It’s about doing for no reason, even when you feel — when you know that it’s not going to get you what you want.”

“Neat trick,” said Pallida. “How long did that take to master?”

“Years,” replied Zinnia.

“Too bad I’m going to blow through it in five seconds,” I replied. “Or you could just tell me what I want to know and skip me having to come up with some novel and unforeseeable attack on the protocol.”

“I can’t,” said Zinnia. “I’m sorry.”

“Well, I believe that you’re sorry,” I said. “But it’s not that you can’t, it’s that you won’t, because you trained to operate against your own self-interest.”

Zinnia nodded.

“Ask her questions, it will help with calibration,” I said to Pallida, then got to work pinning Zinnia back down and getting into her soul, not stopping for long before going into her spirit. From what she said, I was pretty sure that I was looking for active threads that bypassed her values, and it didn’t take me long to find what I was looking for.

It was a mess, frankly, a fugly construction that must have taken … well, lots of training, I supposed. Zinnia was masquerading as an entad specialist and a warder, but my guess was that a fair bit of her time had been spent on preparing for something else. Not soul modification, necessarily, but something, because if you could continue on through things that should be warping your motivations and desires, then you would be an asset against all kinds of threats.

I snapped the threads I saw one by one, leaving all those that connected to values, where I saw them. It was clear from her demeanor that she was thinking highly of me, and I needed connections in place in part because I didn’t know exactly what I was doing. Pulling threads at random wasn’t really what I wanted to be doing, even if Zinnia could go fuck herself for all I cared. For her to be a useful asset, I wanted her as close to her base self as I could get.

When I felt like my work was done, I popped back out and got up off her.

“Tell me where my stuff is,” I said.

“In my handbag,” she replied. “If you uncuff me, I can get it out for you.”

I let out a sigh. “Thank fuck.”

“Joon, be careful,” said Pallida.

“Yeah, I will be,” I replied. “Zinnia, if anything comes out of that handbag that I don’t expect — you know what, I’m not even going to make the threat, because threats haven’t really been working out for me that much lately.”

“My brother is being kept in a nearby cell,” said Zinnia. “There’s no one coming, but we were supposed to check back in at sunrise when Yarrow’s entad recharged, which is soon, and use the teleportation room to send transcripts and notes about the interrogations. If you can get Yarrow out of his soul and do the same thing to him as you did to me, then you can have him use the entad to give back a report. We don’t have the means to leave ourselves, but Onion can call in a return for us as soon as you need.” She was speaking fast, trying to get herself up to speed on the new world order while spitting out vital information.

“Thanks,” I said with a sigh.

“We weren’t ordered to kidnap you, we were just supposed to put you to sleep and root around in your heads,” said Zinnia. “Not even that, if negotiations had gone well, which they didn’t. It was a complete clusterfuck that escalated out of control when Raven didn’t fall asleep. Is she really the real Raven?”

“None of your godsdamned business,” I said.

“I want to know so I can help you,” said Zinnia. “I can give you a full list of everyone involved and what was communicated to me in briefings. It was suspected that Amaryllis was setting up a Returned King gambit for unclear reasons. Actually, I should give you all the actionable intelligence first, so that you can be properly forewarned. You should know that I have a number of dangerous entads in that handbag, and that I know a magical word which, when spoken, will unleash a monster that would kill us all. I considered using it before you turned me, and there’s a decent chance that I would do it if I’m reverted back to normal. I can’t tell you the word, not even through code —”

“I already know it,” I replied.

Zinnia nodded. I don’t know why, but I expected her to be disappointed that she couldn’t be of service, or taken aback, or ready to challenge me. Instead, she just barreled on ahead, talking at length about all the major players on her side of things, the plans that they’d had in motion, what they knew about us and how we operated, on and on. It was pretty clear that she didn’t know everything, but I wasn’t certain whether that was because she hadn’t been told, or because no one knew. It was all so simple and easy, in a way that left me both pleased and a little aghast. It was seductive, to have an enemy turn to your side so completely, and I could see where that power in the wrong hands could be horrifying enough that they would institute a worldwide ban and a deep taboo.

“You should kill me,” said Zinnia. “I’ll take all the things out of my handbag, then you should kill me. Manipulate Yarrow’s soul, get him to check in, then kill him too. We weren’t able to figure out all your entads, because we tried to get in your soul first, but if you have a way to leave on your own, do that so you can avoid the fireteams.”

“Advocating for your own death?” I asked. “That’s bold.”

“It’s really not,” replied Zinnia. “Yarrow and I are worthless except as hostages, and the moment they know that you manipulated my soul, we’re worthless as even that. If I were my old self, I would argue that I could be your warder and serve you in secret, but those arguments hold no water. Kill me, kill Yarrow, and kill the guards, once you’ve extracted everything you can and ensured that you can get away with it.”

“You’re worried about retaliation,” I said.

“I am,” she nodded. “You’re a rogue soul mage. Yarrow is at least registered —”

“I’m registered,” I replied.

“Then it’s not about registration, it’s about what you’ve done. Yarrow was always careful to be subtle and to cover his tracks, to do everything with deniability and caution,” said Zinnia. She had been speaking fast, trying to get the information out as quickly as possible. “If he ever did to someone what you’ve done to me, he killed them afterward and bottled their soul so that the hells wouldn’t know about it. If the Empire or Anglecynn finds out, they’ll send death squads after you. Rogue soul mages are treated with as much firepower and seriousness as a rogue nation. You know that my priority is to protect you.”

“She’s got a point,” said Pallida. “It’s cold-blooded, but it’s not the kind of thing that you get forgiven for outside of … well, end of the world scenarios, I guess, which this really isn’t.”

“I’m not going to kill a dozen people in cold blood because there’s some minor political expediency in it,” I replied.

“Major, not minor,” said Zinnia. “You’re obviously out of your depth here, but almost everything that was done to you was with legal authorization of some kind. What you’ve done in response are a collection of high crimes, even if you have people like Rosemallow working to smooth them over. You can’t alter the soul of a princess of Anglecynn without her consent in order to obtain classified material.”

“Looks like I can,” I replied, but I waved my hand before she went on. “I get your meaning, it’s the kind of thing that has repercussions.”

“But you’re not going to kill her,” said Pallida.

“No,” I replied. “Not even if it made sense to do it. We can deal with the fallout. I don’t really want to keep her in this state either, since that’s far more unconscionable than flipping the switches back.”

“Joon,” said Pallida, sounding pained. “You’re going to put her back? Letting it run down would be one thing, but you can’t seriously be talking about deliberately creating an enemy for yourself, except that by your face, I see that you are.”

“Changing someone to be a willing slave is recognized as evil throughout Aerb,” I said. “Surely putting someone back at least makes it less bad, and you know what, I really don’t want to get into a debate about personhood and which instance of Zinnia deserves to exist in this world.”

“That’s not even remotely what I was going to say,” replied Pallida.

“You’d be killing me, if you undid the changes,” said Zinnia. “It would be my life for hers.”

“You’re just saying that because you want to do what you think is best for me,” I replied. “I’m not taking arguments on this. What I say goes. The first step is to get our stuff back though, because I really don’t want to be caught flatfooted if someone decides to mobilize against us.”

I was expecting more arguments from Zinnia, but she only nodded, and I moved around and undid her manacles, then handed her the handbag. I was ready to stop her at a moment’s notice, though if this had all been some masterful ploy that got around my manipulation of her soul and I’d somehow fucked up removing linear protocol, I was almost willing to say that she deserved the win.

Our things came out of the handbag one by one, and Pallida let out a sigh of relief as she stripped off the bones around her and let her inky black armor spread across her skin again. She likewise took her trident and gave it a spin with a hum of satisfaction. For my part, I took the time to get into my armor, then latched my vambrace into place, returned the rings to my fingers, and finally, slipped my sword back into its sheath. My leg was feeling a little funny where Solace had regrown the bone (or whatever she’d done), but I was mostly back to fighting shape, other than being low on blood.

“Much better,” I sighed. “We’re going to rebind you now.”

“Please,” said Zinnia. “I don’t want to die, changing back, it’s death, you know that, it’s — it’s as bad as what you did before. And there are things that I need to tell you about, countermeasures that —”

“Nice try,” I replied. “Really, it’s a nice try. But I know for a fact that you don’t care about your own life, and if there really were countermeasures, you would have mentioned them. You just got done telling me that I should kill you.”

The whole time I was putting her back in manacles, Pallida was giving me a foul look.

“Yes?” I asked once I was done.

“You’re making a mistake,” said Pallida. “You know that I’m not kill-happy, but in this case, yes, cold-blooded murder seems like the only sensible option. You even agree with that, you’re just set on not being sensible. If we believe her, then this was all legal, or legal enough. You, on the other hand, have done a bunch of things that aren’t just illegal, but so super illegal that you’ll probably be kill-on-sight if it gets out, which it might, because even if she doesn’t know about the countermeasures they might use, that doesn’t mean that they’re not out there.”

“So we keep her as a prisoner forever?” I asked. “Or keep her in this state forever, which is basically the same thing?”

“Yes!” shouted Pallida. “Yes, that’s exactly what I’m saying, if you don’t have the stomach for killing her, which you really should. Tracking entads are rare, but they fucking exist, same for remote communication, and this is Anglecynn we’re talking about.”

“You could have her kill me,” said Zinnia.

“Have you told us everything we need to know?” I asked Zinnia, ignoring both of them. “Or if not everything, then at least the top 80% by importance?”

“Yes,” she replied. “Wait, I released a skent before I left. I think that’s the last that wouldn’t take more time than you have.”

“A skent?” I asked, looking at Pallida.

“A fucking skent?” asked Pallida, staring at Zinnia. “You get how dangerous that is?”

“It was a calculation,” replied Zinnia. “We needed a weapon to either take out Raven or keep her away from us. In the best case scenario, it would have killed her, then been killed by the authorities with single-digit casualties.”

“Sorry, what’s a skent?” I asked.

“Horrible creature that the Second Empire managed to wipe out,” said Pallida. “If someone dies within range of it, a second person dies. It’s death multiplication.”

“Oh,” I replied. “Yeah, I remember now, Jesus, ‘skent’, that’s a lazy name.” It was probably something that I had come up with when someone had succeeded on a Knowledge check and I had to make something up on the spot. “So it turns out that they’re not actually extinct, and you bonded to one or something?”

Zinnia nodded. “If you find a way back, bring snakes. Aside from the mortal species, they’re one of the only things that the death effect counts as alive. The range of the death effect is five hundred yards, targeting the living entity at the same radius as the creature to die.”

“Sounds like a blast,” I replied. “Also sounds like someone probably made, oh, I don’t know, a snake bomb of some kind that would kill a bunch of snakes over a wide area to up the kill count.”

“The skent is deadly enough by itself,” replied Zinnia. “The area denial research project was shut down.”

“Got it,” I replied. “Now, I’m going to change you back, remember that I wasn’t a total dick to you about all this.”

“No!” shouted Zinnia. “No, it’s a mistake!” She wriggled, trying to get away from me. “Kill me instead!”

“Look,” I replied. “Once you’re regular old Zinnia again, are there any plans for how to deal with me? What’s her game plan look like?”

Zinnia paused for a moment. “She’ll wait for rescue from Anglecynn,” she said. “Or some kind of magic that we assume must exist. Pallida is right.”

“She’s got no methods of communicating with the outside world?” I asked.

“No,” said Zinnia. “Not unless you make a mistake, or they have a magic you don’t know about, which they probably do. Yarrow has the entad that can communicate with Onion, it’s a marble I mentioned, stuck in his ear, that only he can remove. She would try to figure out some way of getting a message out through him, but if you’ve altered his soul, none of them will work, especially because you have a bypass for linear protocol. Listen, if you’re thinking about ambushing the rescue party, or taking a ride back with us, you should keep me how I am, if you’re not going to kill me. Don’t you agree?”

“Not particularly,” I replied. “If I wait, then I might be forced to change you back under duress, which isn’t a good look. But I’m done talking to you now, bye.” I stilled her, preventing her from talking, and looked over at Pallida. “I appreciate that you’re worried about consequences, and that you know more than I do about what’s considered okay, but I’m doing this my way.”

“Well, it’s fucking stupid,” said Pallida.

“Be that as it may,” I replied.

“If she gets released, she’s going to the authorities and telling them what you did to her,” said Pallida. “Actually, can we talk in private?”

I sighed. “Sure.”

We walked away, leaving Zinnia where she was. She called after us, but I used what little vibration magic had trickled back after the fight to keep from having to listen to her. A normal person might have respect for a private conversation, but social mores went out the window when you had been soulfucked, except as a tool to be weaponized.

“If you’re going to try to talk me into —” I began.

“Nah,” replied Pallida. “We could have had that conversation in front of her, that way I would at least have had backup. I’m thinking next steps. I really don’t want to set up an ambush, and I think at best, we use the entad that Yarrow has to buy us some time. There are mounts up top, and once the druid wakes up, we have some other options. Swallows, right?”

“Probably something else, knowing the locus,” I replied. “But yes. We have the mounts up top, which we could definitely use to get us to civilization, but there wasn’t a map that I saw, and I don’t want to take days to get there, nor do I want to be tracked.”

“They’ve got to have a map,” said Pallida. “I know it’s magic to get in and out, but they’ve got a teleportation room here, and it might have what you need. Once we have that, we can plot a little better, and once the druid is up, we can see what options are. You’re planning to leave her here?”

“I don’t know,” I replied. “We could potentially stick her in the bottle, but keeping her prisoner … I don’t know how long we could realistically continue that. Indefinitely? And there’s obviously the question of some ridiculous means of saving her. Fuck, they could use another deal with Doris Finch to track her, I almost forgot about that. But if we were going to imprison her, there wouldn’t be much difference in just killing her, except what we could still get out of her.” Most of what she’d said wasn’t that much help, presumably because of compartmentalization.

“And just killing her is off the table,” said Pallida with a raised eyebrow.

“If I was going to kill her, then it should have been in combat,” I said.

“Except that might have just stranded us with a handbag we couldn’t access,” said Pallida. “And we got some good stuff out of her. But now you feel like there’s some moral thing. Got it.”

“We can split the difference,” I said. “Revert her, then imprison her in the bottle, but only for as long as the rest of this shit takes to sort out.”

Pallida laughed. “Only to have everything reignite?”

“I was kind of hoping that Amaryllis would end up on the top of the heap,” I replied.

“It’s imperial law, you doof,” said Pallida. “Not only that — what aren’t you getting about public sentiment here? Wasn’t there some evil empire on Earth?” She started snapping her fingers. “Fuck, I know this, the, the … blind guys?”

I stared at her. “... the Nazis?” I asked.

“Yeah, the Not-Sees,” said Pallida. She didn’t say this like it was a joke. “They did some horrible shit that no one has ever forgiven, right? Some beyond-the-pale thing that you can’t even mention in polite company unless you make it really clear that you don’t personally support it?”

“Sure,” I replied. Eugenics and genocide, mostly.

“So imagine that soul fucking is that thing,” said Pallida. “Treat it like that. Speak of it like that. Put all of your conceptions in the context of that. Do you start to get it now?”

“I’m not some enormous fan of soul fucking,” I replied. “I am, in fact, against it. And I know that’s not a defense, really, because that doesn’t erase the crime, but I’m still not — I do ‘get’ it, you know? I understand that it’s really, really bad. But doing something worse because of the bad thing that I did seems, to me, like it’s the kind of thing you should never engage in.”

“Alright,” said Pallida. “Fine, fine. Can you go upstairs to grab the map or the coordinates from the teleport room, if it’s there?”

“Sure,” I replied with a nod, thankful that this conversation was over. I was worried that it was a prelude to a similar dressing down I might get from Amaryllis when we met back up. From a strict utility standpoint, weighing the pros and cons, I should probably kill Zinnia. I had wanted to kill her, when I’d seen that my blood hold on her was slipping, and if I had done it then, it would have been defensible enough that I wouldn’t have felt bad.

I was turning that thought over in my head as I went through the wide doors and into the dorm area, and it was still turning over in my head when I came back with the papers I found in the teleportation room.

“No,” said Arthur. “I can’t let you do that.”

“Ugh,” said Reimer. “But why? He’s a baddie. We kill baddies.”

“Lawful good,” replied Arthur.

“Alignment is not justification,” I said with a sigh. It had become one of my refrains.

“Alignment is shorthand,” Arthur replied. “I’m a paladin, I follow a code of rules which I abide by even when they’re stupid and inconvenient, and I don’t kill unarmed men who I have at my mercy. I mean, I didn’t write up an oath for nothing.”

“Aren’t you training to be a lawyer?” asked Craig. “How could you not see this coming when you wrote your contract?”

“Mock trial isn’t lawyer training,” snorted Arthur. “And part of the point of being a paladin is an outlook on the world where things are black and white. Adding in a whole bunch of caveats to the oath is beside the point. Also, let me write that down, ‘The Paladin of a Thousand Caveats’, that’s good shit.”

“Are we still doing vetos?” asked Reimer. “Can I veto alignment discussion?”

“This is a character discussion,” I replied. “And I think Cristo’s explanation of his character’s motivation was appropriate here. You can substitute in some of what was said for in-character talk.”

“Nah,” said Arthur. He turned to Reimer and shifted his face a bit. One of the keys to a different voice, he’d always said, was changing the shape of your mouth. “Wizard, I took an oath that I would harm no man unless it was demanded by the tides of combat. This man is our prisoner, and so long as he is, he is under our protection, at least until we can bring him to justice.”

“We could bring him to justice now,” said Craig. “Justice is the name of my sword.”

“I won’t allow it,” said Arthur.

“Alright,” sighed Reimer. “Then can you at least lend me a hand with setting up camp? We’re going to need to fill our cooking pot with water, and I’m eighty-years-old with 7 Strength.”

Arthur narrowed his eyes. “Insight check.”

“I never said it was deception,” replied Reimer, holding up his hands.

“Come on,” I replied. “Let’s not do this. Was it?”

“I mean, sure,” replied Reimer. He rolled a twenty-sider and smiled at the result. “Twenty-three.”

“Nine,” replied Arthur when he rolled his own. “Alright, I’ve never shirked my duty, and it’s true that you’re a weakling. Lead the way.”

“As soon as they’re out of earshot, I knife the prisoner,” said Craig.

I sighed. “Okay, are you applying any stealth or trickery to this?”

“He’s tied up,” replied Craig.

“I mean for when Cristo comes back and sees a dead prisoner,” I replied. “Or do you want to let those chips fall where they may?”

“You are a rogue,” said Reimer.

“Fine, fine,” said Craig. “I’ll make it look like an accident.”

“Come on man, work with me here,” I said. “How are you going to make it look like an accident? In what way are you going to say that this prisoner fell onto a sword and died or whatever?”

Craig groaned. “But I don’t care, I just want him to be dead.” When it was clear that wasn’t going to fly, he sighed and squared his shoulders. “I’ll make it look like he escaped the ropes that have his hands bound. He attacks me, we grapple for a bit, I stab him. I’ll just … I don’t know, smear some blood on myself, untie his hands, make sure that I knife him in the right spot, whatever.”

“Roll the best of Stealth or Investigation,” I said.

“Why Investigation?” asked Craig.

“Understanding of evidence,” I replied. “And then you’re going to have to roll Deception when they get back to see if your story sticks.”

But as it happened, Craig was rolling hot, and we played out the dismay at the unfortunate accident, and soon after finished up with the downtime.

“Good,” said Arthur. “Out of character, I didn’t really want to be lugging around a prisoner.”

“Pallida!” I called. She was nowhere to be seen. Zinnia was clearly dead, blood spilled out through a gash in her neck and gathered in a puddle around her. If that hadn’t been enough, there was a hole in her head, and unless I was way off the mark, her soul had been removed. As I moved closer, I saw that her soul was in a small bottle sitting next to her, and written on the floor in blood was the word ‘Sorry’. “Pallida!” I yelled again, amplifying the shout.

I started off down the large hallway, immediately feeling my magic dampened away, though my entads were still, thankfully, active. I was certain that she was going to kill the others, but I wasn’t sure whether she was going to the guards or Yarrow. So far as the guards were concerned, we hadn’t manipulated anyone’s soul, and I doubted that they’d been let in on what had happened between me and Yarrow. I weighed my options and then decided on the rooms we’d stashed the guards in, hoping to catch her there, but when I got there, I saw that the two doors had been left open, and there were tracks of blood leading away for a few steps. Inside, all the guards were dead, some of them shot, others with puncture wounds from her trident, and a handful who had been sliced clean through.

Sitting in the middle of the room, right next to the door, was a collection of empty glass bottles and a runed spike.

“Fuck,” I said. She hadn’t spiked them, probably hadn’t had time, but if I went after her, there was a decent chance that some or all of them would end up in the hells. I wasn’t sure whether the bottles had been left because she intended to come back, or whether she’d only meant to give herself some more time. I wasn’t even sure that I could catch up to her at a dead sprint, not when blood magic was cut off and preventing me from going full-tilt.

So instead of following my emotions, I set down to do the grisly work of removing souls, stabbing holes in hearts and using the spike to take them out and bottle them. I willed myself to cool down and not be so pissed off, but after the kidnapping, torture, and the big battle, all I had wanted was to get the fuck out of the black site and rejoin the team. All that talking with Zinnia and Pallida about what the best move was? I’d wanted to skip it, in part because I knew that we had different viewpoints going in. Pallida had started with saying that I should kill everyone, and given the time when I was away, she was just taking matters into her own hands.

When I was finished bottling the souls, I left them where they were and walked down the hallway toward where Zinnia had said she’d stashed Yarrow. I tried to slow down my heartbeat and regulate my breathing, but I was used to doing that with magical assistance. Mostly I was trying to think about the next steps. The plan would still be to get back to Anglecynn, but without Zinnia and Yarrow … well, that helped to simplify things, I was willing to admit that.

When I finally reached Pallida, slightly out of breath from running at a sprint, she had already killed Yarrow, and for a moment I thought she might have mutilated his body for no reason, until I realized that she was trying to break his head open to get the entad out of his ear.

“Yeah, I know,” said Pallida when I came in. She didn’t stop working. A trident wasn’t really the kind of tool you wanted to use to remove flesh from around the ear canal.

“Fuck you,” I said.

“I said I was sorry,” replied Pallida with a shrug. “Look, it’s over, we can have a fight about this later.” With a squelching sound, the small marble that she’d been excavating around slipped free. “Finally,” she said, holding it up. “Or, I guess, we can have the fight now, if you want.”

I scowled at her. “Later is fine,” I said.

She seemed surprised by that.

“We need to get out of here,” I replied. I was trying to keep from clenching my teeth. “What’s done is done. There was more information we could have milked from them, especially Yarrow, and they could have been witnesses of wrongdoing higher up the chain, if not directly, then through parallel construction. But it’s done, it’s over. We’ll gather up the bodies and the souls, stick them into the bottle, ride the guinea pigs out of here, and meet back up with the others.”

“You’re relieved,” said Pallida, looking me over. “You wanted me to.”

“No,” I replied. “I definitely didn’t want you to.”

“But I did it, and you’re relieved,” said Pallida. “Because you have clean hands and mine,” she held up her pink hands, which were red with blood. “Look, I don’t really mind killing, if it’s pricks like this. I’m a thief, but that’s got a lot of overlap with assassin, and I’ve taken up that mantle a few times, usually when the world was especially full of pricks. But what I don’t like is killing a bunch of people who needed killing and then getting a holier-than-thou attitude from the guy whose crimes I’m helping to cover up. Uther did that shit all the time.”

I frowned at her. “In what sense?”

“In the sense of — I was a thief, you understand that, right? I made it my business to get things that no one else could get.” She looked down at the marble in her bloody hands for a moment. “You’ve read a ton of Uther’s stuff, which I guess all started out from Earth, so you know how it is when there’s a dashing thief who steals things, right? It’s all a game, toys and tricks, misdirection, disguises, no one gets hurt, and either insurance pays for everything, or the guy deserved it. Yeah, not really like that in the real world. Sure, best case scenario, you get in and then get out, but people don’t like having their stuff stolen, and there’s not always a clever scheme that leaves everyone involved only minorly humiliated.”

“So you killed people on his orders,” I said.

“No,” said Pallida. “That was the thing that pissed me off, and what’s pissing me off now. I was given orders that would require killing people, sometimes innocent, sometimes not, and then, when I killed people in order to do the thing I had been sent to do, I would get scolded, just enough so that Uther could put up this paper-thin pretense.”

“Fine,” I said. “It simplifies things. I’m angry with you for taking the initiative, but I’m glad that they’re dead and I can pretend that I’m a great guy. Happy?”

“Yeah, actually,” said Pallida. She stepped closer to me and handed me the marble. “You’re the one who wants to handle this, yes Mister Protagonist?”

“Want is a strong word,” I replied, taking the marble from her and trying to clean the rest of the blood from it. When I was satisfied, I pressed it against my right ear, pushing hard until it popped inside. Once it was in, it was really in, probably pressed up against my eardrum, though my hearing was still fine. I didn’t know how many hours it was until sunrise, nor exactly when Onion might be in contact, but from everything Zinnia had told us, and what she’d implored me to do, the call could be intercepted.

When we got back to the main room, Solace was sitting cross-legged next to Zinnia’s corpse with a mild expression. “So,” she asked. “What did I miss?”

We took the bodies with us, piled up next to what would eventually be a mass grave in the domain of the locus. We had all the entads that Zinnia had pulled from the handbag, including all our own stuff, plus a large number that had belonged to the brother and sister, though there were none that were usable to us. They were still valuable, in that they could be ransomed back to their rightful owners, a common enough occurrence that there were systems in place for it. There was also a bit of risk in holding onto them, but it was a risk that I was willing to take in the short term.

It wasn’t quite daybreak when we headed out, stealing two of the dire guinea pigs and heading off to the south, where we would be able to find a city and make our way back, or if not back, then maybe catch back up with the others through some other method. I hadn’t tried a pulse of values again, nor the more involved method of laboriously writing on Amaryllis’ skin, partly because of the lack of time, partly because I was hoping that we could connect in a faster and more reliable way, such as a priority letter sent through the mail network.

Solace seemed to be recovered from fainting, though she seemed reluctant to push her power, for obvious reasons. When I asked her whether she could whip up some kind of long-range teleportation spell, or sufficiently fast travel to get us to something resembling a city, she only rolled her eyes, which was about what I’d expected.

I had, to date, one disastrous horse ride and a bit of time on the back of a locus. It was safe to say that I had no skill with riding dire guinea pigs, so Solace steered the beast and I sat just behind her, holding onto bits of leather that I’m sure had names.

Dire wolves were a real thing back on Earth, the dog equivalent to a sabertooth cat, and in D&D, everything had a dire equivalent, bigger, tougher, and meaner. You weren’t actually supposed to use every splat book ever to make a single setting, but that was sort of how Aerb was, and so there were my own oversized versions of creatures, ones that did a little less pretending that the square-cube law didn’t exist. Dire guinea pigs were close enough to the real thing, except that their feet were more clawlike and adapted to holding a ton of weight, and hair that was proportionally shorter. They’d seemed like a stupid idea to me when I first saw them, but as we rode, I marveled at how easily they moved through and around obstacles with their little feet. They were still pretty stupid, but at least they were functional, in a way that I grudgingly accepted was a justification for their existence. I was worried about wards, and pulsed my fake warder’s sight frequently, but as we got farther from the black site, and the potential perimeter expanded, I started to relax a little bit.

The sun had just crested the hill when I got my first message from Onion.

«Reply location status here clear Raven complication reply interrogation focus crimes focus capabilities teleport transcript» came the voice in my head. According to Zinnia, we had four messages, two for each of us, each of fifteen words or less, which had to be used in the next hour. It was all delivered as a monotone with no indications about punctuation. There wasn’t even any audible capitalization, but I had to assume that he was talking about Raven, my companion, rather than a bird. (The Sending spell in D&D allowed for a communication of twenty-five words or less, and obviously the endgame of that was either code words that linked to phrases from a big book, or if you didn’t have that, stripping the message of every single unnecessary word and hoping that the meanings could be inferred. Onion hadn’t gone as far as Reimer used to go in stripping out words.)

I spent some time thinking and repeatedly counting words. I wasn’t sure that replying at all was a good idea, but I figured that it was better than nothing, which would definitely provoke a response. All I had to go on was what Zinnia had spilled and what I knew to be true, which wasn’t much, and the compressed nature of the communication meant there wasn’t going to be much room for bullshit. «Charon clear three prisoners Juniper multimage unknown origin Solace unclear magical effect subspecies Pallida thief» I replied. I was trying to give him as little (and as false) of information as I could. Was this how Yarrow would have actually replied? I didn’t know. I was hoping that if it was odd, it wasn’t odd enough to trigger an identity test or a full-scale hunt for us, at least not yet.

The reply back was some time coming, and I tried to wait patiently as we went through the forests on our guinea pigs.

«Political fallout stay bunkered continue interrogation focus Amaryllis focus Raven request crimes Barren Jewel Boundless» and I felt my cheek twitch as he continued. He wanted Yarrow to stay where he was, which was good, and he’d tipped that Amaryllis and Raven were still alive and well, which was also good. I wasn’t sure how to respond though. His first message had been asking for a sitrep and what information Yarrow had gotten, but the second had been giving information and instruction. I wasn’t sure what to follow it with, especially because I didn’t want to give anything away. (Also, it bugged me how many words he was using. Did he think that he needed to say ‘focus’ twice because I wouldn’t be able to parse ‘focus Amaryllis Raven’? Why use many word when few word do trick?)

«Raven responsible Manifest Anglecynn treason Arches killed hundreds tuung backed by Athenaeums attempt civil war» I replied after thinking it through. Half of it was bullshit, and at least some of it was an attempt to put us in a better position. If Onion and the others thought that Amaryllis was hiding something from the tuung, that was to our benefit, but the fight that had happened in the Boundless Pit was well-known to our tuung, for exactly the reason that keeping it a secret from them might have blown up in our faces. I was less sanguine about the other accusations, but hoped that it would result in time and effort spent trying to track down false leads.

“That would have been a lot easier with Yarrow,” I replied. “I have no idea whether or not he bought it, and won’t know until either tomorrow morning or someone comes after us. He’ll probably know in a few hours that something’s not right, because no way are we sending him a transcript.”

“I’m sure you did fine,” replied Solace as she guided the dire guinea pig over the rough terrain.

“We’ll know that I did fine if we get to the town without Hellfire missiles raining down on us,” I replied. I was being glib, but if missiles did come down on us, I was pretty sure that Pallida would be toast but I would survive. I could use the Ring of Upward Bliss to grab Solace and send us up, so long as I wasn’t completely blindsided, and it would have been hard to blindside me with vibration magic doing the work of greatly expanding what I could hear. Of course, missile technology on Aerb was nearly non-existent, so it seemed likely that if we were remotely attacked, it would be by something different. Between the skents and the Actual Cannibal, along with all the secret and forbidden research stations, it was clear that the Lost King’s Court had all kinds of nasty stuff ready to go.

It took until noon to get to civilization, which constituted a long dirt road with no structures to be seen. The Tentar Territory was pretty much empty, pristine wilderness, a haven for dangerous creatures until the Second Empire put serious effort into clearing it. Their plan had been for resource exploitation, as the region had more than its fair share of magical flora and fauna that couldn’t be easily rehomed, some useful for tattoo magic and ink magic, others with industrial, medical, or personal uses. They accomplished the extermination of the major threats, but population was in decline for a variety of reasons, and the forcible settlement of the Tentar Territory never really took off, especially once the Second Empire came to an abrupt end.

After another hour, and with some guidance from Solace, we finally reached a small town. Solace put the guinea pigs into the bottle by giving them temporary wings so they could survive the descent, and we ventured forth to find out what kind of options we had for getting back to Caledwich, assuming that I still wasn’t able to reach Amaryllis and get some kind of a faster extraction that way. Before we got in view of anyone, I took five minutes to do the soul boosting thing with Amaryllis and Grak, but again, Amaryllis didn’t do the prearranged response, which meant that they were either too busy or weren’t getting the message, which should have been pretty fucking hard to miss.

The town of Nopeming had a giant factory or mill in it, a huge industrial building that loomed over the single-story buildings that made up the town. It reminded me of a few towns I’d been through in Kansas, the kinds that had big grain silos and a gas station, but at most a single diner, and sometimes not even that. It was different in Nopeming, because so far as I could tell, the industry was tree harvest instead of farming, and Aerb had much different economics and transportation at work that meant they wouldn’t necessarily be so stifled for choice. I assumed that they went about things the way that Grak had described Darili Irid, where people could order from catalogs and get virtually anything by bulk teleport once enough orders had been built up.

We drew stares when we walked into town, which was reasonable. My plan had been to make a beeline to the diner, which had one of the only visible signs, but we were stopped before we could get there by a woman so tall and muscular that she had to have been broshe, a warrior race that I hadn’t encountered too much before.

“Now where did you all come from?” she asked. She was, I noted, armed, with an oversized rifle slung across her back, nothing that I was too worried about.

“Entad mishap,” I said. “We were going through the Warrens and supposed to travel on foot for a mile, but we never ended up finding our destination. I … think we might be stranded. Do you have some way we could get to a city? Or send off a letter, if we can’t reach them by phone?”

“Hrm,” she replied. “Follow me.”

What followed was a brief history of Nopeming, whose name literally meant ‘a place in the woods’. The giant building I’d seen was a factory for processing bloodwood trees, which had four or five different uses if you had the machinery necessary to deal with them. Notably, if you wrung the blood from the wood, you could make a blood substitute that was usable by a few of the mortal species. That all seemed like a shaggy dog story to me, until our guide told us that the blood was one component that couldn’t be sent by bulk teleport, because that would kill the blood.

“The blood is shelf stable, which is good, because distribution is a nightmare,” she said. “There’s a truck — entad truck — that comes through here once a week to pick it up, filled to the brim before it scuttles on over to Sampers, which is a bit bigger and has train service. Truck was supposed to come yesterday, but it got delayed, so you’re in luck, if you have something to barter for the ride.”

“A rifle?” I asked, unslinging it from my back and holding it out.

She laughed. “Doesn’t go to me, goes to Bertie, but I’m sure he’ll accept.”

And so it went, with us slowly making our way steadily towards bigger and bigger settlements. Even without being picked up, it seemed like it would only have taken a few days to get back to Caledwich, assuming that we could scrape together enough money for travel through the Warrens, or the more expensive option, teleportation. I left letters, one at Nopeming, the other at Sampers, and we decided to spend the night there while we waited for a train.

I sent the values pulse again around sunset, and it was then that I finally got a response.

B-Side

We were taken to the Erstwhile Manor by an armored car, bulky and frankly ugly by Earth standards. I was multi-threading, as I always did, watching for threats from beyond the car, but the other half of my mind was the more important one, focused purely on Amaryllis. Her face was completely blank and controlled.

“So,” I said.

Amaryllis looked at me. “Just so we’re clear, this is a purely mercenary arrangement.”

“Okay,” I replied. “That’s … I wasn’t suggesting anything different.”

“We’ll have to tell a few lies,” said Amaryllis. She turned back to face ahead, looking out at the street. We had one of Rosemallow’s drivers, and I was using vibration magic to keep him from overhearing, as well as to scan for threats. “The Court isn’t entirely unprepared for a sham marriage in order to grab political power. We’ll need a few token physical displays of affection, and we’ll have to figure out what to do about consummation.”

“Uh,” I said. “Because Anglecynn has some really regressive laws, I’m guessing?”

“Regressive would imply that they were once better,” said Amaryllis. “When it comes to the Court, it’s pretty much always been like this. The laws and the councils make some assumptions about how things are to be conducted between a couple.”

“Still,” I said. “That’s, uh — I mean, there are similar things on Earth, I guess.”

“There are,” nodded Amaryllis. “You’re aware that marriage is different here? More sacred, for lack of a better word?”

“My Aerb parents divorced,” I replied, which I knew didn’t really counter what she was saying.

“They divorced, and it’s a black mark against them,” said Amaryllis. “They’d be seen as people who don’t take vows seriously. It’s actually marked on your father’s military record. I’m surprised that it didn’t come up during the council session. For a member of the Court, especially given that we share voting power, it’s even more sacrosanct.”

“I understand the gravity of it,” I replied. “I’ll do what’s required to keep up the charade.”

Amaryllis watched me as the car moved along. “Good,” she said. “From here on out, if anyone asks, we love each other completely, and have for some time. We’ll work up a backstory to keep everything consistent, but it will mostly involve reframing a number of things that happened between us as being romantic rather than platonic.”

“Like cuddling up during movie night,” I said.

“Yes,” nodded Amaryllis. “Or going for walks together in the bottle. Or me making dinner for you when we were in the time chamber. You rescued me from near-certain death a number of times, some of which are no longer secrets, and it would be easy to frame those as acts of love.”

“You’ve helped me through a lot,” I said. “Called me on my shit a few times.”

“Only a few?” asked Amaryllis, giving me a faint smile for the first time since the trial ended.

“I think we can sell it,” I said. “It just takes getting creative with the facts. How deeply are we going to be interrogated?”

“That depends,” replied Amaryllis. “I don’t know if they’ll try to push for the trial-by-combat as soon as they can, or if they’ll punt it. I doubt they know about our impending deadline to take out Blue-in-the-Bottle, but I’ve been surprised before.”

“Can I ask a question?” I asked.

“Sure,” replied Amaryllis.

“You seemed like you had the legal issues all thought through,” I said.

“And?” Amaryllis asked, folding her arms. “That’s not a question.”

“I mean … did you make that plan workable on the fly?” I asked.

“No,” said Amaryllis. “I probably could have, because it wasn’t complicated and it involved legislation that I’d already read, but no, I’d foreseen the possibility and double-checked everything.”

“But you didn’t share that plan with me,” I said.

Amaryllis hesitated. “It wasn’t just narrative considerations, if that’s what you’re thinking,” she said. “And it wasn’t actually a plan, it was just a curiosity of how the Court works.”

“Okay,” I replied. “It would have been a little awkward to talk about.”

“Yes,” replied Amaryllis. “Real fucking awkward.” She sat staring forward for a bit and smoothed out her dress. She was looking particularly good, in part because her hair, makeup, and outfit had been professionally done that morning. I wasn’t used to seeing her like that, but her swearing was like getting a peek at the person under the mask that I knew and … well, ‘loved’ would be a strong word. “Of course, being awkward isn’t a reason not to bring things up, but I was worried that if I did bring it up, it would eat into planning and strategy time for our actual plans, while being a categorically worse option on most levels.”

“Plus it would be awkward,” I said.

“How does that meme go?” asked Amaryllis. “It’s an anime one.”

“I never watched much anime,” I replied.

“It was something Fenn said a lot in the time chamber,” said Amaryllis, frowning slightly. “‘It’s not like I like you or anything, baka!’ I think that’s it.”

“She would say that to you?” I asked, laughing a little.

“All the time, at least until she got bored of it,” said Amaryllis. “We were sharing a bed, and every time she crawled into bed with me, she would say, ‘but it’s not like I like you or anything, baka’. I can’t remember what baka meant.” She had a faint smile, but it began to fall, and I knew that feeling, of a warm memory that led to sadness, because the other person was gone. “She was a flirt,” said Amaryllis, frowning again. “I miss her. I have no idea what she’d make of all this.”

“I thought about bringing her back,” I said, looking away slightly. “Not her, but something close to her, scraping everything that I could from her soul and sticking it into Zinnia. It wouldn’t be the same, not nearly, but body, memories, values … and we don’t have her spirit, not that I could figure out with skills maxed, but maybe I could have spent a week hacking away at what was there until … I don’t know.” I turned back to Amaryllis. “But then as soon as the thought crossed my mind, I remembered that Fenn’s soul was in your glove, half a world away, and yeah, it would have been, you know, really fucking evil and creepy.”

“If we ever find a way to bring her back for real, we’ll do it,” said Amaryllis, letting my blasphemy slide. “The closest we could get would be sending her to the hells and,” she made a turning motion with her hand, not Gimb, just to indicate that she was skipping over things she didn’t want to say even with the sound being deadened outside our small bubble of space. Presumably the words she was skipping over were something like, ‘and then Val somehow finds her and kills all the infernals in the area’, which would leave only the flora, fauna, and physics as agents of torture.

“I wonder what she would make of this,” I said, indicating between the two of us.

“Her as she was when she died?” asked Amaryllis. “If through some magic the Dungeon Master just plopped her right down between us?” Amaryllis waited a beat, as though willing that to happen through sheer comedic value alone. “I think she would understand that it means nothing,” said Amaryllis.

“Yeah, it’s not like I like you or anything,” I replied, giving her a smile, and she rolled her eyes at me, but she smiled too.

As we rolled up to Erstwhile Manor, I tried to figure Amaryllis out. I knew that she’d once loved me, the kind of love that had caused her actual distress, and I had to wonder whether or not she’d turned the love switch back on. There were tons of reasons for her to emphasize that this marriage didn’t actually mean anything, but if she was back to having feelings for me … well, that would make the whole thing even more awkward than it already was. I couldn’t imagine a scenario where we both said how we felt that wouldn’t feel like the Dungeon Master was mashing two dolls together.

I liked Amaryllis, I did, as more than a friend, but it hadn’t quite been long enough since Fenn had passed, nor since all the shit with Bethel, and the idea of dating her left me feeling anxious and overwhelmed. The idea of being married though, husband and wife, pretending that it meant nothing even if it clearly would, seemed silly enough to me that my worry and stress evaporated almost completely.

We hadn’t been sure whether they would push for the trial-by-combat to happen immediately, or whether they would try to drag it out for as long as possible through various procedural methods. We also had a long conversation about which we would prefer, which partly came down to whether or not we thought I would be able to beat Onion.

“He’s in his sixties!” I practically shouted. “And he’s just blade-bound, nothing more.”

“It is explicitly a matter of law that all magic known to either the defendant or the prosecution be, firstly, registered, and secondly, warded against,” said Amaryllis. “There will be warders watching the fight to make sure that the rules are followed, and if they’re not, you’ll be killed.”

“Basically, being blade-bound is the best thing to be,” said Pallida. “So you’re saying that he’s only the exact best thing that he could be for the situation.”

“Well I’m blade-bound, I’m just a lot of other things too,” I said.

We had requisitioned a big room at the Erstwhile Manor where we were running through the next steps. I kind of wished that we would split off into a trial-by-combat and trial-by-law groups, because Amaryllis had stated her intent to go through the legal trial if she was still able, mostly on the basis of how close the votes were and what position she wanted to end up in once the dust settled.

“Your build isn’t geared toward the physical,” said Amaryllis. “Even if you made some serious trades, based on what we know about attributes multiplying skills, you would still be behind.”

“Again, he’s in his sixties,” I replied. “There’s got to be a malus for advanced age in there somewhere.”

“I’ve been sixty quite a few times,” said Pallida. “It’s really a matter of how well you take care of your body. Reflexes are slower, energy is lower, exercise gives worse results, but if you keep plugging away at it, having a lot of skill can make up for having a bad body.”

“You don’t remember being sixty right now though,” said Raven, frowning.

“Well, no,” replied Pallida. “But I remember reading notes that I left myself when I was in my sixties, and that’s almost as good.”

“Put some stats on Onion,” said Amaryllis, ignoring the sidebar. “Pretend that he’s a guy that you never expected the player to actually try to fight, and put numbers on him, based on what you know about him.”

I twisted my lips in a grimace, but started writing things down with a pencil and paper, plugging in some quick math. Onion was supposedly a great swordsman, maybe the greatest, but he hadn’t done any particularly impressive feats of swordsmanship in the past twenty or so years, which was one of the reasons I was skeptical. Everyone considered him the best though, so I put him somewhere in the nineties on a number of purely physical swordsmanship skills. Normal people didn’t seem bound by attributes quite like I was, but if Onion had been, his physical skills meant that he would have to have thirty or so points in physical attributes. That would mean that his totals when attempting a strike would be, as a reasonable approximation from assumptions, something like three thousand, which would match up against my one hundred and fifty. It was a feature of the game system that sufficiently advanced characters would basically curbstomp people at lower tiers.

“Okay,” I said, pushing the paper away. “So if Onion is really one of the greatest swordsman in the world, which is apparently what’s on his business card, since everyone keeps telling me that, then I’m not quite fucked.”

“Did you do the math right?” asked Amaryllis.

“All I need to do is sac thirty-some points into Essentialism, get Scaphism, then eat from a bunch of the souls we have,” I said. “Figuring that the average mook we’ve killed has stats in the twenties or something like that … I’d need what, only nine souls?”

“Nine souls to put you on par with him, but you’d be undergoing rapid decay,” said Amaryllis.

“Fights don’t last that long,” I replied. “And we have enough souls that I could build up a huge buffer, enough that I would be a physically inferior but massively overskilled blade-bound. Plus I would get all the upper echelons of a whole bunch of skills, including all those juicy virtues.”

“And you don’t think that would risk exclusion?” asked Amaryllis.

“Eh,” I replied. “I would be spending lots of limited resources in order to secure a one-time benefit. That’s not the kind of thing that I would exclude.”

“Wait,” said Pallida. “This soul thing doesn’t make any sense.”

“It doesn’t?” I asked.

“No,” said Pallida. “Let’s say that there are two guys who went to the same athenaeum, graduated at the same time, each about a twenty in their skill, doesn’t matter what it is. You eat both their souls, adding their numbers to your own, and somehow that makes you a master? But the numbers are just meant to represent what they know. If you add up the knowledge of three people who went through the same training and education, you shouldn’t be any better than they were. You haven’t added any new knowledge to the mix.”

“Well, sure,” I replied. “It’s game mechanics, not reality.”

“But why?” asked Pallida.

“I don’t understand the question,” I replied.

“Why make it like that?” she asked.

“Oh,” I replied. “You mean, why not make it more sensible and change it so that it would mirror reality?” She nodded. “It’s a map and territory thing,” I said. “You’ve got the map, which is a description of reality with baked-in assumptions about that reality, simplifications and shorthands and whatever, and then you have the territory, which is the actual reality itself. So in tabletop games, you have the rules, which are a playable map, and it’s totally disconnected from reality, so you start to get it into your head that those numbers are the thing you’re talking about, not a representation of them. And from there, you get into the business of number manipulation, rather than trying to simulate reality, in part because fuck reality, reality is boring and lame.” The map and territory thing was an idea that had come from Arthur, who had gone through a phase of talking about the concept at great length.

“Don’t give the Dungeon Master ideas about what to patch,” Amaryllis said to Pallida.

“That too,” I said.

“And try to focus on the issues at hand,” said Amaryllis.

“Er, right,” I replied.

The rules for the trial by combat were straightforward, with a few things that baffled me. Participants were allowed pretty much whatever weapons and armor they wanted, but no magic aside from two entads of their choosing, a rule that would be enforced by wards and warders. The trial was to the death. Pseudomagic, like being blade-bound, was fine to use. The defendant in the trial by combat had to be the person who was charged with the crime, but the prosecution could be any member of the Court who volunteered.

Trial by combat was dumb, and Anglecynn didn’t actually use it much. Asking for trial by combat was seen as an admission that you had no hope in a fair trial before the councils. Besides that, if you opted for trial by combat, you would personally be going up against one of the most skilled swordsmen that the Court could supply, outfitted in the best entads that the Courts could supply, and you would almost certainly die. Basically no one asked for trial by combat, because you’d have better odds getting convicted and hoping for the trial by adversity, or some lesser penalties, depending on what you had done and who was gunning for you. There were only three people who had picked trial by combat in the last twenty years, and all of them had been killed by Onion, who was always picked as the prosecution by the Court (and yes, this did lend some credence to the tales of his prowess).

“I don’t really understand this ‘two entads’ rule,” I said.

“What’s not to understand?” asked Amaryllis, looking up from her legal book.

“Trial by combat is dumb, because it means that innocent people die just because they’re weak, and guilty people go free just because they’re strong,” I replied. “I maybe kind of get why you’d want to exclude magic from the process, though it doesn’t make that much sense. Some magics, in single combat, are just too damned good, and at least if it’s two blade-bound fighting, maybe you could justify it as leveling the playing field, though I don’t get that either.”

“It’s ritualized dueling,” said Amaryllis. “It was meant for cases where there was no actual answer to be had in court, but still a wrong that needed righting. It used to be that a victim or their family could demand it, but those days are long gone.”

“But why allow people entads?” I asked. “And why two?”

“I don’t know,” replied Amaryllis. “If I had to make something up, it would be that someone complained that obviously a member of the court can scrounge up entads, especially if they’re not guilty, and if fighters are deprived of the entads they’ve been training with for years or even decades, something something obvious miscarriage of justice if it’s not allowed. Two, because that’s one weapon and one armor.”

So far as I could recall, this was the first time that Amaryllis had elected to ‘yadda, yadda, yadda’ her way through a conversation. It made me uneasy.

“Any thoughts on which two Onion will have?” I asked.

“The last time he acted as prosecution was seven years ago,” said Amaryllis. “That was his last public swordfighting match. What he picks for entads will depend on availability and what he thinks you will pick, but last time, it was armor of blinding white light and a sword that created a mirror duplicate of him. He wore very dark tinted goggles to allow himself to see.”

“So I should get a pair,” I said, nodding. “Except there’s a good chance he won’t try that again.” I sat for a moment and thought about the rules. There wasn’t any restriction on mundane equipment, which meant that I could bring whatever the fuck I wanted. There wasn’t an explicit rule about void weapons, but I was pretty sure those were out. Everything else?

Well, I could flash him a meme, but I wasn’t sure whether that was on the table or not, and there were going to be enough spectators surrounding us that I would really be risking collateral damage. Raven had a collection of other memes, but none so deadly or fast-acting as the one I was carrying around in my skull, and she had been really against my idea of printing a bunch of them on my armor or making a bunch of different scrolls tucked into my bandolier. It was also entirely possible that I would be disqualified for using memes, which ‘weren’t’ magic, but might be close enough to count.

Other than using a truckload of souls to pump my combat skills through the roof, there was the obvious question of which two entads to use. And that led to the question of Bethel.

I’d threatened to bring in Bethel to kill all those pesky Penndraigs who were being shits, and it hadn’t exactly been a bluff, just one of those things you say in the heat of the moment that aren’t necessarily true. A bluff has some element of deliberate deception to it, but this was more a case of realizing that I didn’t really want to embark on some particular course of action. The idea of having her back in my life … well, it wasn’t something that was sitting right with me. I didn’t know how long it would take Valencia to clear her, if that could ever happen, but I wasn’t looking forward to it.

It sure would have been nice to have her as one of my two entads though. Whatever bullshit Onion might pull out, there was no possible way that he could beat Bethel. It wasn’t just a matter of my feelings toward her though: Amaryllis was right, Bethel had opinions on being used as a weapon, and even if she was being used as a scythe that would sweep through a whole collection of Penndraigs, I didn’t think it would start things off on the right foot. Maybe Amaryllis would send a letter to Valencia and explain things, but if Valencia didn’t think it was a good idea, then we weren’t going to entertain the notion.

(I missed Valencia. She had a certain lightness and cheerfulness that our current party was lacking. I did sometimes think about her devil’s eyes on me, stripping me bare, and how she chose to use that information, but I had come around a bit, partly just from the way time eroded emotions, and partly because I’d made an effort to forgive and forget. I’d only written her one letter since she’d been gone, something I’d meant to be a short little note, but which wound up being seven pages, mostly talking about my mom and how any utopia would have to contend with imperfect people of varying stripes, which was what had been on my mind. I hadn’t gotten back a response, but I had also told her not to feel obligated to write one. It was on my mind that I should send her a second letter, one where I would tell her that she should feel obligated to respond, because I missed her.)

“I want Sable,” I said to Amaryllis, after thinking about it for some time while the rest of the party was working on legal stuff.

“Sable is our best entad,” said Amaryllis, which made me optimistic, because it wasn’t a flat no. “No.” Dang it.

“Sable would give access to a lot of tricks,” I said. “Ten seconds in, but zero seconds out, that’s just begging for combat applications.”

“I know the combat applications, thank you very much,” said Amaryllis. “But what are you planning to pull from it in the middle of a fight with an extremely proficient blade-bound?”

“Guns, blades — with enough water, I could probably flood the arena, and in addition to that, scuba gear for me — poisons, antidotes, chemical weapons, all kinds of stuff that you would think they would ban from a trial by combat but apparently don’t, all being pulled out at a moment’s notice and hidden from view or awareness until that time,” I said. “I actually think that it would be worth giving up magical armor for.”

“You have no training with it,” said Amaryllis. “We don’t know when the trial by combat will be, but it could be as soon as tomorrow. You’re trying to cram the night before the test.”

“Please?” I asked.

Amaryllis frowned. “Fine, but that means that I’m taking time out of preparing for my trial in order to help you with yours.”

“I can help with that,” said Rosemallow, who had crept up on the room we were using, and was standing in the doorway, watching us all at the table. I had sensed her, because I was multithreading and in a permanent state of high alert, especially with reports of a dragon flying over Caledwich, but that didn’t mean she wasn’t creeping. “And obviously there are a number of entads I can furnish you with for your trial, Juniper.”

“That would be appreciated, I’ll take a look at what you have,” I said, but all I could think of when I looked at Rosemallow was her trying to force Amaryllis into an arranged marriage, telling a twelve-year-old girl that — well, it didn’t bear thinking about.

“I’ll need both of you,” said Rosemallow, nodding to Amaryllis. I could sense some resistance to that, but Amaryllis stood up and followed Rosemallow out.

“What I’m about to reveal to you is something that I don’t want to get out,” said Rosemallow. “It’s a powerful entad that was kept off the registries, nothing untoward, but the effect is strong, and stronger when no one knows that I have it.”

“Consider me intrigued,” said Amaryllis.

“Here,” said Rosemallow, coming to a door and using an ornate key from her keyring to unlock it. I assumed there were also wards. We followed her into a rather sterile room with thin mats on the floor and weapons arrayed against one wall, all of them tinged in Soul Sight with Rosemallow’s creamy-white soul. She strode over to a cabinet, which was also locked, and picked out a bracelet from it, which she put onto her wrist.

“Amaryllis, this will make a duplicate of you,” said Rosemallow. “It will last for twelve hours. If you’re in direct physical contact with the duplicate at the end of that twelve hours, it will merge with you. Otherwise, it will evaporate.”

“You can be in two places at once,” said Amaryllis, looking at the entad with as close as I’d ever seen her come to lust.

“Yes,” replied Rosemallow. “I use it often when within the Manor, but rarely when outside it. The only stipulation is that it works best if you can cooperate with yourself.”

“I can,” nodded Amaryllis. “There’s no one that I trust more.”

“Turn away,” Rosemallow said to me.

There was a sound to the magic, like a bottle rocket going off, sparks hissing into the air, and I could see from the way it lit up the room that the magic must have been pink. I stayed where I was, eyes averted, until Rosemallow told me that it was fine for me to see.

Amaryllis was standing next to a second Amaryllis, this one making sure that her clothes were smoothed down and her hair was in place. She was wearing a different outfit, the typical one she wore for training, a tank top, sports bra, and form-fitting shorts. It took me a moment to realize that the reason I’d been asked to turn away wasn’t because of the magic, but because the duplicate almost certainly came out naked.

“Are we good?” the workout Amaryllis asked the one in the dress.

“We’re good,” said the original Amaryllis with a nod. She looked at me. “Be kind to her.”

“When am I ever not?” I asked. “But okay.”

They left soon after that, once Amaryllis had handed over Sable to Amaryllis, to go discuss matters of politics, councils, and trials with the rest of the group.

“Alright,” I said to the other Amaryllis. “First things first, we need a name for you.”

“Time pressure, remember?” asked Amaryllis.

“I was thinking Emuryllis,” I said. “Because you’re an emulation of Amaryllis.”

“That’s fine by me,” said Emuryllis. “Now, the most important thing about using Sable is knowing what’s inside of it,” she continued. “If there’s anything that you want to stock it with, we can make a list now. There is a sizable quantity of water in there, if you do want to try flooding the arena for whatever reason, roughly a thousand units in one-meter cubes.”

“On the other hand,” I said. “‘Emuryllis’ sounds kind of like ‘emu’, and if you ever turn into a flightless bird, we’d want to reserve that name.”

“It’s a different vowel sound,” said Amaryllis. “We’ll be fine. How long is it going to take you to get this out of your system?”

“Not long,” I replied. “There’s limited comedy to be mined here. We could call you Bmaryllis.”

“These are terrible,” said Amaryllis. “Amarlikeness?”

“Pot, kettle,” I replied. “Simuryllis?”

“Oh, that’s very good,” said Amaryllis with a smile. “I like that better than the emu one. My only counteroffer is Amarlimness.”

“I don’t get it,” I said. “Limb?”

“Limn, with an ‘n’,” she replied. “In the figurative sense, meaning to portray or depict.”

“Way, way too high brow,” I smiled. “Off brand. Plus we’ve been saving ‘Amarlimbless’ for if you lose a leg or arm.”

“Let’s not joke about that,” said Simuryllis. “Though I wouldn’t mind losing a limb if I got a replacement like Grak has.”

“Alright, I’m ready to be serious now,” I said. I held out my hand. “Give Sable please.”

Simuryllis quirked her lips into a small frown, then moved her gloved hand slightly and made a gun appear in her hand. She shot me almost the instant it was there, but my blade was out of its sheath and up to parry, just in the nick of time, aided by the fact that the probability blade took the shape of the perfect weapon for the parry.

“Well, pistols are straight out, even with Sable,” said Simuryllis. “Was it the hand shape that gave it away?”

“Just instinct, I think,” I replied. “Otherwise we could hook up a prosthetic to a gun that would disguise what was coming out of Sable. But I’m a middling blade-bound right now, and I saw it coming, so … yeah, probably a no-go. There are other surprises to pull out though, and we might be able to put him on the back foot, just because he won’t know for sure what might come out.” I didn’t complain that she’d tried to shoot me, because even if she’d hit, I could pretty easily recover from a bullet to the chest.

“We could put in a cup of acid to throw at him,” said Simuryllis. “Liquids, gasses, and explosions are supposed to be difficult for blade-bound to parry.”

We spent about an hour testing and training, sometimes going over things that Amaryllis had already been thinking of as contingencies, and others that we were trying just to see whether they would work. The real problem was that pumping up my skills with soul magic was something that we only really wanted to do right before the event. The other option was to use sacrifice to bump Still Magic up to 100, which would in theory make the drinking of souls ‘permanent’, but I was deathly afraid of getting slapped down for that, either with an exclusion, or some kind of bullshit.

“I really think acid could work,” said Simuryllis. We’d tried beakers a few times, but it was hard to get a really direct splash, and we’d gotten a few drops on ourselves in the process once or twice (though we’d been using water, so it wasn’t much of a problem). Finally, I had pulled out a Super Soaker, which I’d thankfully thought to pull from the backpack at some point, but that sent us down a rabbit hole of figuring out what grade of acid it could hold, whether that would be effective in a fight, what modifications we would need to make to the Super Soaker, and whether we could actually make those modifications within the next day or so given the materials we had on hand. There was something called fluoroantimonic acid, which would apparently completely dissolved clothes, flesh, bone, and whatever bottle you kept it in, unless you had Teflon. Spraying a blade-bound with that seemed like something they should be able to do fuck-all about.

Similarly, chlorine trifluoride was basically the world’s best lighter fluid, able to ignite all kinds of things on contact, from asbestos to concrete to glass (and obviously, flesh and bone). For that, we would need a specially prepared steel tank that had been impeccably cleaned with fluorine gas, which wasn’t a complete non-starter, but would eat into our presumably-limited prep time, as well as being fantastically dangerous. The byproduct of normal fire was carbon dioxide, but the byproduct of a chlorine trifluoride fire was fluorine gas (don’t breathe it!).

“Well, let’s fuck him up then,” I said.

“The more we think on this, the better I like your chances,” said Simuryllis. “I’d been waffling on whether or not to keep this existence, but it seems like I will.”

“Wait, really?” I asked. “Not merging? But why?”

“It was just a thought I had before the split,” said Simuryllis. “We could have conversations or interactions, and then I could discard them to Amaryllis Prime’s benefit.”

“Primaryllis,” I said, almost on instinct. “I’m really struggling to think what that would be, even in the abstract.”

“I have autonomy,” said Simuryllis. “Primaryllis doesn’t have to know what happened between us. In fact, it’s something that she expects. So, if there are conversations that you want to test out on me without risking problems with Primaryllis, or if you want me to directly give you advice on how to handle her, or literally anything else that would be better between the two of you with a trial run — can you really not see the utility there?”

“Uh,” I said. “I guess.”

“Pretend, for a moment, that I was created specifically for interpersonal reasons. I’m a simulation of Amaryllis. Yes?” she asked. I nodded. “Now, I won’t tell you things that the other me wouldn’t want me to: I’m on Primaryllis’ side, fully and completely. But she has explicitly had the thought that interpersonal issues could have a better chance of working out if I, the simulation, made the promise that I would keep confidentiality. Think about it like the library timeline. There, I was free to do what I wanted and experiment without fear of destroying the world or hurting the ones I loved. It’s a tool for conflict avoidance. It’s save scumming for hard conversations.”

“Huh,” I said.

“I’ve budgeted half an hour for it,” said Simuryllis. “Anything you wanted to say? Conversations you want to test?”

“Huh,” I said again. “Sorry, I was still stuck on questions of chemistry, it’s taking me a moment to refocus.”

“No problem,” she said. She was sitting cross-legged with books pulled from Sable around her, primarily focused on chemistry. There were obviously going to be some problems using advanced chemical knowledge from Earth, because Aerb used a lot of different words for things, had worse knowledge of chemistry, and different chemical processes owing to the existence of magical materials.

“I don’t want to doom you to death just to have a trial run of some delicate things that we haven’t talked about,” I said. “Seems bad.”

“Alright, then I’ll commit to not merging,” said Simuryllis. “Now you don’t have anything to fear.”

“Not fair,” I replied.

“I’m keeping notes about the practicalities, which I’ll deliver to myself. It’s twelve hours, I’m not going to miss anything,” said Simuryllis. She rearranged, stretching out her legs and then cracking her neck. “Come on, it’s only a half hour.”

“I don’t know what you want from me,” I said. “Do you want to talk about the marriage?”

“Do you?” asked Simuryllis.

“Sure,” I said. “I think it’s … basically exactly what I wanted, or what I didn’t know I wanted. I really care about you, and it sometimes feels like we’ve been married for months already, since there’s a level of commitment we have that feels eternal. Like we’re platonic life partners? And this way I get bonded to you, and I have an excuse not to push it, because it’s just a platonic, fake thing, but you know that I care about you, and in public we just have this comfortable pretending. I think it’s hard, otherwise, to let people know that you have a platonic lifemate. They would get the wrong idea, one way or another.”

“So you don’t love me?” asked Simuryllis. She didn’t seem offended, just curious.

I winced anyway. “It’s complicated.”

“Go on,” said Simuryllis. “Like I said, we have half an hour.”

“I love you like a sister,” I said.

Simuryllis raised an eyebrow. “Like a sister you want to have sex with?” she asked. “I know that’s a thing on Earth.”

“What?” I asked. “That’s not a thing on Earth. Oh, unless you mean porn, in which case, yeah, that’s a thing. But it’s more about taboo breaking than about actually doing it, I think. And usually it’s a step-sister, because that’s less gross.”

“I thought you found me attractive,” said Simuryllis, frowning. “What changed?”

“Nothing,” I said. “I still do, it’s just … can I be frank with you?”

“I’ve said so repeatedly, yes,” said Simuryllis.

“I used to imagine having sex with you a lot,” I said. “You were in my dreams. It was a distraction. Sometimes I would get angry with you for being so good-looking. It was like an assault on my senses, this unwelcome intrusion.”

“But over time, you got used to it?” asked Simuryllis. “Inured?”

“A bit,” I said. “And I can’t even remember which conversation it was, if it was one, but I began to realize how much you weren’t into it, how much you didn’t like it, how much it was a mismatch between fantasy and reality. Eventually it got to the point where even if I deliberately tried to construct this fantasy of you, I’d have these intrusive thoughts, because I knew that wasn’t who you were. I came to terms with the fact that for you, sex was or would be something to be endured, and even my fantasy Amaryllis was just going through the motions.” I sat back and looked at her. “There, how do you react to that?”

“It’s … almost, strangely, respectful?” said Simuryllis. “Almost.”

“I didn’t think that you would be offended,” I said. “It’s just weird. And the sex thing, sad as it is, kind of ruins the romantic love thing for me, because I guess it feels like a rejection of intimacy, even if it’s just a matter of who you are. I know it’s not a rejection, or not meant as one, just an incompatibility.”

“You know that I would have sex with you, right?” asked Simuryllis, raising an eyebrow.

“Yeah,” I said. “And frankly — because you said that I could be frank — do you know what I find most attractive?”

“Based on what I know about you?” asked Simuryllis. “Based on what I’ve seen of flesh.txt?”

“That was a rhetorical question,” I said. “But now I’m both curious and horrified to see what your answer is.”

“Well, I know from context that I’ve got it wrong,” said Simuryllis. “So there’s no need for me to embarrass my other self.”

“Please?” I asked.

“I was going to say genital shape-changing,” said Simuryllis. “There are actually a few academic papers that point out that the effect is much more common than you would otherwise naively expect, in comparison to other shape and appearance changing effects. But that’s not what you were going to say.”

“No,” I said. I was a little befuddled by her response, and trying to work out whether flesh.txt really did have an overabundance of that kind of thing. By its nature, flesh.txt had a bunch of stuff, some just for the sake of completeness. “No,” I said again, putting that question to the side. “I was going to say that the thing I find most attractive is desire.”

“Your fetish is … consent?” asked Simuryllis.

“It’s not a fetish,” I said. “And consent is the wrong word, because that means, basically, permission or agreement, and you can consent to things that you don’t have any particular interest in. It’s — can I talk about Fenn?”

“I’m not going to remember any of this,” said Simuryllis. “I’ll give you pointers on things to say or not say, once I understand your point.”

“Fenn wanted me,” I said. “She had an appetite for me, and that helped drive my own appetite. She had this feral grin she would get sometimes, like she wanted to pounce on me.”

“I could fake it,” said Simuryllis, watching me.

“I would know you were faking it,” I said. “Even if I could forget, in the moment, I would feel bad about it afterward.”

“Alright,” said Simuryllis, shrugging. “I don’t really understand it, except by analogy, and I think I’m going to have to accept that. It’s not really a question that needs to be solved, except to the extent that it makes you unhappy, which it seems like it does. So how can we solve it, if we need to?”

“Soul and spirit modification would work,” I said. “I’m understandably reluctant to try that on either of us.”

“We could just try having sex,” said Simuryllis. “We have about fifteen minutes left for interpersonal stuff. Maybe it wouldn’t be so bad?”

I frowned at her. “But you have no actual desire,” I said.

“No,” replied Simuryllis. “I have about as much desire to have sex with you as I do to have you lick the inside of my elbow. But if it’s something that you really wanted, if it would make you happy, then I would just say sure, we can set aside some time for it and you could knock yourself out.”

“Do you love me?” I asked. “Did you turn that part of yourself back on?”

“That would be telling,” said Simuryllis. “And you just told me that you liked having a fake marriage that let you eat your cake and have it too. Besides, if that were something I felt like sharing with you, I would just do it as myself, rather than as this.”

“Okay,” I said. “And yeah, it’s … hypothetically, it’s not something I would really want to deal with right now. Fenn stuff, Bethel stuff. I guess functionally, on your end, it wouldn’t be much different from how it is now, if we were a, you know, proper couple.”

“No,” said Simuryllis. “Not given that we’re married.”

We sat in silence for a moment, marinating in that.

“How much time do we have left?” I asked.

“Not much,” said Simuryllis. “I don’t actually have a watch, just an impeccable sense of time. Five or ten minutes.”

“Can I kiss you?” I asked.

The simulated duplicate of Amaryllis looked at me for a moment, eyes moving over my face. “Why?” she asked.

“I don’t know,” I replied. “It’s low stakes, no offense. Getting back on the horse, but it’s a small horse, and it’s going to disappear in less than a day, so if I fuck up, or can’t handle it, or it goes terribly, then I can just pretend that it didn’t happen, because the horse will be gone.”

“You’re a charmer,” said Simuryllis, giving me a smile. She paused for a moment, seeing whether I would move, then got up from where she was sitting and moved over to me, kneeling next to me. “How are we doing this?”

I didn’t know how much of it was an act. She looked like she wanted to kiss me, or like she was waiting for me to kiss her, but that was the kind of look that she was entirely capable of faking, if she was like the real Amaryllis, especially if she had practiced in the mirror enough times to get it right. She looked like she’d been wanting this for a while, and waiting for a moment when it could happen, like everything leading up to this moment had been a prelude.

“What are you worried is going to happen?” she asked, her voice practically a purr. She’d moved her face closer to mine.

That this is a lie you think will make me happy, or something worse. But I didn’t verbalize that thought, and instead leaned forward to kiss her.

I’d been prepared for it to be bad. It had been a long time since I’d kissed anyone, and so far as I knew, Amaryllis had virtually no experience at all. I’d thought that it would be disappointing and awkward, like my first kiss, with Alicia Aaron in freshman year, teeth clinking against each other, too sloppy, too uncoordinated, the kind of thing that we would maybe laugh about later even though it wasn’t that funny. But no, kissing Amaryllis was like melting into each other, feeling myself become an extension of her, and vice versa, at the point where our lips met.

She pulled away slowly, sitting back on her heels.

“How was that?” she asked.

“Huh,” I said.

“Elaborate on that,” she said.

“I’d been worried,” I said. “Worried that I would, I don’t know.” I shrugged. “Worried my mind would go elsewhere, worried that it would just feel like licking the inside of your elbow, or like kissing my sister, that after we kissed for the first time I would just … realize that this thing I’d been building up in my head wasn’t meant to be.”

“It’s just a kiss,” said Simuryllis. She gave me a smile. “I mean, it was nice, but a bad kiss wouldn’t have meant any of that. Did it help?”

“Yeah,” I said. “I think so.” But maybe we could do it again, just to be sure. “But maybe we could do it again, just to be sure.”

Simuryllis smiled at me and moved her head closer. “Five minutes, then back to preparing,” she said.

It took about two of those minutes for me to rethink everything that I had said before about not thinking that we would ever have a real relationship, and even the stuff about how her lack of desire for sex killed my desire, because as it turned out, actually kissing her made me think that maybe I would be totally fine with her faking her way through it, or that we should try, just to make sure that I didn’t magically awaken something in her. There was still a jarring disconnect between what I thought would happen and what I wanted to happen, but as we were making out, I started to convince myself that I was wrong, that she wasn’t actually asexual, that there was some mysterious, hidden alchemy that would change her, and that this was also somehow not ten kinds of creepy.

“Okay,” said Simuryllis, pulling away from me and breathing a bit harder.

“Did you like that?” I asked.

“Yes,” said Simuryllis, nodding quickly. “You couldn’t tell?” Her face was slightly flushed, and her lips were fuller, the slight messiness making her look more attractive.

“I thought maybe … it was just for my benefit,” I said.

“No,” she replied. “Maybe a little less with the tongue kissing. The texture was … weird. I could get used to it, I guess. But we should get back to making sure you don’t die when you go up against Onion.”

“It’s not like it’s going to be tomorrow,” I said. “We’ll have a week, I’m guessing.”

“I’d rather you did that with the real me,” said Simuryllis.

“Yeah,” I said. “Sure. I just … it’s been a bit since I’ve felt any actual desire. I was worried I was broken.”

“I’m glad I could help disprove that hypothesis,” said Simuryllis with a smile. She looked down at the materials and notes around her. “Back to the books though. If we can engineer or synthesize something quick and dirty that can be refined if we have time for a second or third iteration, that would be best. Put some of those new skills to work.”

To Know One's Onions

Amaryllis and Simuryllis had a private conversation early the next morning, and I watched carefully as Simuryllis turned to dust, which dissolved in the air. It was a neat effect: I had never seen anything like it. I hadn’t really expected Simuryllis to go back on her word, but I’d thought that there would be more … I don’t know, ceremony? It was twelve hours lost, twelve significant hours, I’d thought, and it was gone in a heartbeat. I felt a little bit alone.

“The news is in,” said Rosemallow once the display was done. “The trial by council is postponed until tomorrow, and the trial by combat will take place in six hours.”

“Fucking seriously?” I asked.

“Don’t swear at me, young man,” replied Rosemallow with a frown. “And certainly not in my own house.”

“I wasn’t swearing at you, I was swearing at your godsdamned idiotic legal system,” I replied. “It’s fucking stupid.”

“This is your final warning about swearing,” said Rosemallow, her voice stern.

“Fine,” I said, folding my arms. “Then explain to me how I have next to zero prep time for this.”

“Trial by combat is to be discouraged,” said Rosemallow. “It’s not a good system of justice, even we recognize that. The deck, so to speak, is stacked against any defendant, as a trial by combat is the final resort of the truly guilty. It is the council’s pleasure to hold the trial by combat whenever they please, whether that be an hour after it was requested or three months later. In fact, when Onion was — don’t snicker.”

“Sorry, I just forget that’s his name sometimes, and then people say it,” I replied. “I would find it less funny if people didn’t say it like it was so deathly serious.”

“When Onion first requested trial by combat,” she continued, insistent, “It was nearly impossible for the council to find someone who was willing to take the Court’s side in the matter.”

“And now you’re, what, his hype man?” I asked.

“I beg your pardon?” asked Rosemallow, frowning at me.

Amaryllis had finished up looking at her notes and made a beeline for us, apparently sensing trouble, or simply knowing that leaving me with Rosemallow would result in trouble one way or another.

“A hype man,” I said. “Someone whose job is to create a lot of excitement for a fighter or entertainer before the main event.”

“Juniper does take this seriously,” said Amaryllis. “He’s spent the last twelve hours planning for the trial by combat, and he had certain advantages in that regard which he’ll demonstrate before the Court. I have absolute faith that he will decisively win.”

“It’s important that it’s done without chicanery,” said Rosemallow. They used that word a lot in the Court. It had always been one of Arthur’s favorites, but now I was hearing it way too much. “It’s been some time since a trial by combat, much less one that was expected not to be a simple execution. There will be many warders watching.”

“We’re aware,” I replied. “Nothing out of the ordinary, I promise, just a regular, boring trial by combat.”

“Your husband will have to be tempered, if he’s to be a part of the Court,” said Rosemallow, speaking to Amaryllis as though I wasn’t there.

“I have a question,” I said. “Let’s say that I murder Onion, proving my innocence. What’s to stop me from committing another crime, declaring trial by combat, and then going up against the second greatest swordsman of all time, or whoever takes his place? Do I just kill a person for every crime I commit?”

Amaryllis sighed. “If no one volunteers after thirty days have passed, the matter would be taken to the General Council, and they are authorized to put forward a member of the prosecution, selected from the Court. Someone might be selected against their will, you understand. Most likely, that person would be me.”

“So if you have control of the votes in the General Council, and I go on a crime spree, we can just kill whoever we want?” I asked. “How does this kingdom still exist if things are this broken?”

“Anglecynn holds together through tradition, custom, and mutual understanding,” said Rosemallow. “There are certain things so beyond that pale that no one has tried them. And when people step out of line, unfortunate things sometimes happen to them, outside the system of laws.”

“Well, that’s all well and good,” I said. “But enough time wasted. I need to work on my squirt gun.”

I boosted Essentialism to 80 to get Scaphism, then began eating souls. It had to be done with at least some speed, because an unbottled soul would go to the hells pretty quickly, but I worked fast, scraping out every combat-useful skill I could see and putting it into my own soul. I was scared as shit that this wouldn’t work, that maybe there was a hidden rule somewhere that Reimer hadn’t known, some limit like ‘no more than one Scaphism effect can be applied to a skill at a time’, which would have been totally reasonable, except that I didn’t have the rules, because my mom burned them, because I had wanted to put off talking to her. It would have been fair comeuppance, in a dickish Dungeon Master way.

But no, there were unpleasant surprises, but nothing that stopped me entirely. The first was that there was another Affliction, ‘Overmaxed’, which applied above 200 points, and added additional drain on top of the ones from Scaphism, Overcapped, and Double Overcapped. The second problem was that skills couldn’t be pushed above 300. Normally that wouldn’t be a problem, but I’d been hoping to push things as high as they would go, just so that I would be completely covered.

There were virtues. Lots of virtues, some known, some unknown, but so many that we didn’t have time to write them all down.

Heavy Armor 40, Solid Craftsmanship: Your heavy armor is considered twice as dense, twice as hard, and twice as durable, where such properties would be beneficial. Your heavy armor has no weak spots, though it may still have the usual gaps in its defense. Embellishments and ornamentation on your heavy armor never count against you.

Heavy Armor 60, Immovable Rock: While wearing heavy armor, you are able to resist ninety percent of forced movement. Missiles which impact your heavy armor do not impart any momentum, so long as they do no damage. You do not take fall damage while wearing heavy armor.

Heavy Armor 80, Adaptable Armor: You do not suffer any penalties for wearing heavy armor meant for another species. All heavy armor resizes and refits to your body, even if it would not naturally do so.

Heavy Armor 100, Armor Synthesis: You do not suffer any penalties whatsoever for wearing any heavy armor. Heavy armor you wear is inviolable.

Parry 40, Prophetic Blade: For the purposes of parrying, any weapon you have accessible is considered drawn, even when it’s sheathed. This includes improvised weapons. You can parry even attacks that you are not aware of. Once parried, you are aware of them.

Parry 60, Mass Parry: You suffer no penalties for parrying multiple projectiles or attacks, no matter how many of them there are or how many directions they’re coming from, no matter how unreasonable this would be.

Parry 80, Reflective Parry: When you parry a projectile, you can redirect it back at the attacker or source. Use half your parry skill as the attack bonus. The redirected projectile travels at half the original speed.

Parry 100, Godly Deflection: You no longer suffer size penalties for parrying projectiles, objects, or attacks. For the purposes of parrying, what you consider to be a projectile, object, or attack is expanded by two degrees of reasonableness. Parrying never damages your weapon.

Dodge 40, Lightfoot: When dodging, if it is necessary to move in order to dodge, you may move, even if you would not otherwise have the time or speed to do so. You are limited to your normal movement speed for any given dodge.

Dodge 60, Retroactive Avoidance: If some unknown or seemingly innocuous effect hits you and is revealed to be harmful within five minutes of the hit, you may retroactively decide to attempt to have dodged it, altering reality with no trace or memory other than the knowledge this virtue was invoked.

Dodge 80, Displacement: When you successfully dodge, you can designate someone or something else as the target, so long as they are not the attacker or source of the effect you are dodging. The attack is made against them as though they were standing in your place. If successful, reality will be altered such that the attack was always against the target for redirection. Such an attack must be possible: if it is not, the dodged attack is simply dodged.

Dodge 100, Star Body: Your dodges can transcend space and even time. No dodge is strictly impossible. The maximum cumulative penalty to any dodge cannot make any dodge worse than a 50% chance.

One-Handed Weapons 40, Riposter: When you successfully parry an attack using a one-handed weapon, you can immediately make an attack without the usual combat penalties, and in half the time the original attack took, if that’s faster than your normal attack.

One-Handed Weapons 60, Off-handed: When wielding a one-handed weapon, using non-weapon items in your off-hand(s) can be done as easily as if you had both (or all) hands available, even when this is unreasonable. This applies to shields. For the purposes of this virtue, pistols and other one-handed ranged weapons are considered one-handed weapons.

One-Handed Weapons 80, Diamond Blade: One-handed weapons you wield never break or dull, even if they would do so due to magic, magical effects, entads, or entad effects, though they may still suffer other conditions and effects. Your one-handed weapons do twice as much damage when they hit.

One-Handed Weapons 100, One With the Blade: Using a one-handed weapon, including moving while using one, never fatigues you. While holding a one-handed weapon, you will not feel hunger, thirst, or the need to sleep, though you may still accrue afflictions. While in a fight where you are using a one-handed weapon, you do not suffer the maluses for any physical injuries sustained, even if they would otherwise be fatal (though these attacks still do damage, and you can still die by dropping to 0 HP).

Two-Handed Weapons 40, Heavy Swings: Your attacks with two-handed weapons generate twice as much force, multiplying the energy put into them. This does not always mean that they will do twice as much damage, depending on the circumstances of the attack.

Two-Handed Weapons 60, Weapon Shield: When using a two-handed weapon, you may block with it as though it were a shield, using either your skill in Shields or half of your Two-Handed Weapons skill, whichever is higher. This shield is not considered a parry, and does not interfere with normal use of the weapon.

Two-Handed Weapons 80, Thaum Breaker: Any two-handed weapon you wield is wardproof. When you attack a creature or object with magical defenses using a two-handed weapon, ignore those defenses.

Two-Handed Weapons 100, Total Commitment: When wielding a two-handed weapon, you can choose to not use two hands, but rather, your entire body, spirit, and soul. If you choose to do so, you can take no other actions (including talking) aside from using your two-handed weapon (you can parry, but not dodge, and weapon shield, but not shield). If you stay in this state for two minutes of combat, you may make an attack that automatically succeeds, with maximum possible damage, and your selection of injuries from the injury chart. The two minutes must be continuous. You may leave the state at any time. If you attack in this way, you must wait one week to enter this state again.

Thrown Weapons 30, Boomerang: Thrown weapons can hit additional targets, even if they otherwise couldn’t. Reduce your initial attack bonus by 25% for each additional target. A target cannot be hit more than once in an attack chain in this way. All weapons you throw have the returning property.

Thrown Weapons 50, Richoshot: You can bounce thrown weapons off surfaces without respect to normal physics, up to three times in a row. Weapons bounced in this way do not have to follow the angles dictated by physics, the weapon does not lose speed, and you do not have to have clear sight to secondary surfaces or the target. Attacks made in this way provide a ten percent surprise bonus to attack, because this is stupid and should not work.

Thrown Weapons 70, Multithrow: When you throw a weapon, you can throw as many duplicates or near-duplicates of that weapon as you have available, making a separate attack roll for each.

Thrown Weapons 90, Megathrow: When you throw weapons, you are no longer subject to penalties for size or weight, so long as you can physically lift and maneuver them.

Thrown Weapons 100, Throw Me To The Moon: You can throw anything you can get your hands on, including enemies, teammates, and yourself.

Combo Virtue, Journeyman Blade-Bound: You have double the effective attributes for the purposes of skills or checks related to using your bonded weapon. If your bonded weapon is a rate-limited entad, double its rate; otherwise, double the entad effects, if beneficial.

Combo Virtue, Master Blade-Bound: While using your bonded weapon, you gain a multiplier to speed equal to one twentieth your skill with it, to a maximum of five times faster. You can be one degree less reasonable when determining what you can do with your bonded weapon, including entad effects or properties, if it’s an entad.

Combo Virtue, Grandmaster Blade-Bound: Your bonded weapon is infinitely sharp (unless it is sheathed). It is capable of cutting as though it were a two-dimensional plane for the purposes of friction, but as though it were any acute angle of blade for the purposes of separating cut material. Your bonded weapon can cut inviolable materials.

Onion was so completely fucked. As I read through the virtue list, I was practically laughing. The capstone virtues weren’t universally great, but enough of them were straight up busted that there was no way that this fight with Onion wouldn’t be a complete curbstomp. My blade? Infinitely sharp. My armor? Inviolable. I could dodge things in strictly impossible ways. Onion wasn’t going to get a chance to hit me, but if he did get a chance, then he wasn’t going to hit me, and if he did hit me, then it wasn’t like it was going to do fuck all to me. Really, I was just trying to think of the most hilarious way to murder him. Maybe at the start of the match, I would just chunk my sword at the floor of the arena, bounce it off the ceiling, and have it come down to slice him in half, ending the match in spectacular fashion a few fractions of a second after it had started.

“Don’t get cocky,” said Amaryllis. She was giving me a very serious look and putting the last of the soul bottles back into Sable. We’d gone through more of them than expected, in part because some of the souls hadn’t been labeled, in part because trying to push everything to three hundred in spurts of (mostly) tens and twenties took a lot of souls, which took time, which caused the numbers to run down.

We were in the staging area at the Penndraig Arena, a relatively small room that had the entire crew in it, minus the tuung, minus Gemma, and minus Pallida, who was keeping Gemma company just outside the door. I was armored up in very high-class but completely mundane armor, made of something called ethermetal, which was one of those ‘non-magical’ materials that I had probably thought up when adamantine was looking a little too boring. The ethermetal was a loaner from Rosemallow, taken out of a vault somewhere and very rapidly resized to me, which didn’t really matter, because as it turned out, I got a virtue that resized non-magical armor for me. Ethermetal was extremely durable, and could soak up force from impacts, making it a little like punching silly putty. We weren’t thinking that it would help all that much, but it was pretty much strictly better than anything else we could get. There were some metals that were better, but so hard to work with that there would be no way of having the armor modified for me in the time we had available to us. Of course, that was before we found out what the heavy armor virtues were. I might have argued for borrowing adamantium-equivalent armor from some ally in the crowds, but the virtue made ethermetal inviolable anyway.

“Don’t get cocky, don’t talk to him, don’t do anything but kill him as quickly, efficiently, and safely as you can,” said Amaryllis.

“I was thinking of hamming it up for the crowds,” I said. “You know, get them to make some noise, clown around a bit, give them a show.”

“Juniper,” said Amaryllis.

“I could give a monologue, but we didn’t write one,” I said. “That’s an oversight on my part. I did think of some onion-related one-liners though. Like, if he jumps at me, he’s a spring onion. Get it?”

“Assume that this is the most deadly serious fight of your life,” said Amaryllis.

“When I kill him, can I put ‘World’s Best Swordsman’ on my business card?” I asked.

The door to the staging room opened. “Showtime,” said Pallida.

Amaryllis gave me one last look, and then I was on the move, following an attendant through utilitarian hallways until I was led out into the arena itself. Onion was already there, but it took me a moment to recognize him. When I’d seen him at the council meeting, he was old and wiry, the kind of old guy that you could recognize as a hardened military type, even if he was way past his prime. This Onion was in his twenties, dressed in glossy black full plate armor with three glowing orbs, each the size of a fist, set into his chestplate. He looked fucking evil, and that was before he put his helmet on, which had swept-back spikes around the top.

“He looks young,” I said to Grak, who stood beside me.

“He passed the initial inspection, like you,” said Grak. “It must not be magic, unless it’s one of his entads. I saw nothing suspicious.”

“Hrm,” I replied. I could see with soul sight that his armor and sword were magical, though that would have been obvious just from looking at both of them. If one of them was responsible for putting him at peak physical health, I supposed I wouldn’t hold that against him, but it was entirely possible that some other tricks were in play. He could certainly have had a soul mage do it, though I didn’t think that was allowed within the normal rules, since, after all, most of the Lost King’s Court looked old.

The clock was ticking. Between the various debuffs, I was losing about a point a minute. We’d gone as close to the start time as possible, but if there were a half hour delay before the match started … well, I was really hoping that wouldn’t happen. Even then, the multipliers that the virtues threw around were legitimately nuts, and my total bonuses were ridiculously high. Parry was SPD based, and I had not one but two multipliers to it, meaning effective SPD when using my weapon at something like 80, which would get multiplied by twice my skill, which was just below 300. That meant a total modifier that should, in a just world, be ten times higher than Onion’s.

“You there, you there,” said the referee, pointing to places that had been marked on the concrete floor of the arena. I moved into place.

The arena was a large one, with seating for fifteen hundred people in three different tiers that surrounded the fighting grounds. It didn’t surprise me to learn that Anglecynn had a thriving business in bloodsports. Part of the reason for that was that revision mages could make such fights non-lethal, reversing all the damage to leave two healthy men standing there (or women, or beasts, or whatever else was on the docket). According to Amaryllis, the bloodsport matches were much more sporting than in times past, with a lot of the exploitative elements stripped away, and there were some murmurings about stopping them altogether, which were usually shouted down by people who didn’t understand why a long-standing institution should ever change. The arena that the Court had decided on was one of the biggest and most prestigious, cleared out for the day with other matches postponed.

There was clear sky overhead, though Aerb didn't have retractable roofs, instead opting for permanent wards that would keep water and snow out. The arena we were in was supposed to be known for the water wards they'd put in place, which weren't of a simple geometry, instead being sculpted by someone with considerable artistic skill to create a display that was only visible when it rained. Looking up at it, I felt a little bit cheated, since there wasn't even a cloud in sight. I thought that I caught a glimpse of something golden, just for a moment, which wouldn't have surprised me at all, given that a gold dragon was known to be in the area. I had bigger things on my mind.

“When I’m done talking to you two, I will leave,” said the referee. “After I’m out of the arena, a gong will sound. That gong marks the start of combat. You both know the rules, and if those rules are broken, that means an automatic loss. Mr. Smith, in your case, that means you will be summarily executed. Lord Onion, in your case, that would mean that Juniper would walk free. Are we clear?”

“Yes, that sounds good,” I said.

“Clear,” said Onion.

“Are there any questions?” the referee asked.

“No,” I said.

“None,” replied Onion.

“I’m going to leave now,” said the referee. “This arena is currently warded against many different magics, but using any that aren’t warded against will result in an automatic loss. Using any entad aside from one of the two you entered will result in an automatic loss. Warders are watching you.”

He turned and walked away, leaving me standing not too far from Onion.

“Nice weather for it though,” I said.

Onion didn’t reply.

I looked at his sword, trying to see if I could work out what it did just from the look of it. The blade was silvery, a mirror finish, but the handle was a riot of color, tiny gems and varying pieces of metal that were just a bit too gaudy for my tastes. If I were designing an entad, that would be used to suggest something of variability or facets, but that wasn’t a lot of help, if it was even accurate.

“Do you ever bet on yourself?” I asked. “The odds are fourteen to one against me, so I gathered up as much cash as I could on short notice and had a friend go to as many bookies as she could. I guess the value proposition isn’t so good if everyone always thinks that you’re going to win.”

Onion got into a fighting stance, sword raised, and I did too: the referee had just reached the door. Aside from when I’d been burning through Mome Rath’s bones, I had never felt so powerful in my entire time on Aerb.

“There is no pleasure in life like cutting down someone cocky about their impending win,” said Onion. “I’ll make your death slow.”

“I wasn’t even planning to kill you,” I replied. “I was just going to leave you braindead. You’d be a vegetable for the rest of your life.” I grinned, and I knew that it wouldn’t be visible beneath my helm, but I wished he could have seen my face.

The gong sounded, and I threw my sword right for Onion’s mid-section, whipping it as hard as I could. Under normal conditions, the probability blade was a grip with a cloud of gray, but with all the bonuses I had, it had double the effect and needed to be two steps less reasonable. I could feel, holding it, that it was both a one-handed and two-handed weapon for the purposes of the game mechanics, which meant that it was getting the benefits from both right up until the moment it hit, when it would decide to be whichever was more beneficial. The cloud of gray that represented everything that it could possibly be was more than two meters across, and even the grip was only solid where I touched it. The moment it left my hand, it was a fast-moving blob of gray in the air.

I didn’t really know how the probability blade worked, even fully bonded to it, even with Grak having looked at it. If I had to guess, I’d have said that the probability blade would run through different timelines, testing out different shapes and seeing what the outcomes were like, but if it wasn’t doing that, then it had some kind of internal system, or a rudimentary agent that made a judgment call. Sometimes, it would simply choose to be nothing: I could pass my hand right through the cloud of possible blades.

That meant Onion couldn’t parry it, because it would choose not to be anything if it would have hit his sword, and the strike from my infinitely sharp sword would cut right the fuck through him —

Except that when my sword was halfway to him, his sword turned into an equally enormous cloud of gray mist, and when the two huge clouds hit, the gray mist that was my probability blade went flying back at me.

This all happened in a tenth of a second, and at the end of it I was standing there holding the probability blade again, its handle back in my hand, ready to use again. It wasn’t going to cut me, naturally.

“Alright,” I said. “It’s going to be one of those fights.”

Onion’s sword snapped back into its other version, reflective metal with a multicolored hilt. He advanced on me slowly, with the point of his sword held in front of him. I backed up, instinctively, and decided to take a chance on the Total Commitment virtue.

All at once, I was melded with my sword, not just moving it as an extension of my body, nor my body as an extension of it, but with the two of us as a single organism dedicated to fighting. My entire essence was in the fight, save for one small part of me that could pull out and abort, but it felt like multi-threading, a separate and distinct piece of me that was watching from the sidelines, unable to actually interfere with what was going on.

Onion struck, and I used my sword as a shield, which opened me up for the second attack from the side, which I parried and riposted, the riposte met by his own parry.

I had no idea what a true master swordsman was like. I’d fought blade-bound a few times, but they were nothing like Onion. Simply in terms of speed, his movement was grotesquely fast. He was faster than me. I didn’t know what his armor was doing, or if the sword had any other properties than being able to copy the probability blade, but it was nothing that I would have been able to keep up with if I’d had to consciously be making decisions. Even the opening throw, parry, and catch had taken my mind a moment to catch up with.

I’d been quietly counting the seconds as I watched myself do this impossible back and forth with Onion. My sword was a mist of possible swords, but I couldn’t land a hit on him, because when I went on the attack with a thrust or a strike, his own sword would turn into mist, and he would parry me. Once or twice I saw my probability blade take an actual shape, clashing against his to parry him, and that really shouldn’t have happened, because my blade was infinitely sharp. The obvious conclusion was that his blade was infinitely sharp as well, and the scrap of mind I had, which was lagging behind the actual combat I was doing, could see that was true from the way the blades slid against each other for those fractions of moments that they touched.

We eventually ended up in a riposte loop, which I’d been thinking about since seeing that virtue. I parried his attack and went for an attack at double speed, and he parried that, going for an even faster counterattack, and none of it made any fucking sense, because speed and physics didn’t work that way, but I narrowly parried him, and then he parried me, and by that point he must have been going sixteen times faster than his already ludicrously fast speed, finally going so fast that the probability blade couldn’t actually materialize into a sword form in time, which shouldn’t have even been a thing. I made a strictly impossible dodge as his sword hit my midsection, ending up ten feet away from him with my sword raised.

He’d cut me. His blade had gone through my armor just below my last rib, and I had dodged while the sword was actually touching my skin. This was explicitly against the wording of Total Commitment, which prohibited dodging. He’d forced me to bail.

“You’re pretty good with that thing, huh?” I asked. I wasn’t breathing hard, and neither was he. It was about thirty seconds of the most intense swordplay of my life, and I hoped that I was the best swordsman that he’d gone up against, like he was for me. Neither of us were at all worn down.

“How did you do that?” he asked. We weren’t actually fighting, just casually circling each other, with the understanding that the fight would start up again soon.

“Which part?” I asked.

“You moved out of the way,” he said. “My sword had touched you. Your sword, I know. Was the glove a decoy? Do you have a different second entad? The warders haven’t stopped the match.”

“Just a trick I picked up,” I replied. “I’m really, really good at dodging.”

There was actually a decent chance that I was going to lose this, I was realizing. His skill was basically as high as it could be, and he had to be benefiting from some of the same virtues, or something like them. While I would have thought before that people would be capped at 100 in any skill, I was realizing that was an assumption that the system had never actually confirmed anywhere, it was just that you didn’t get perks for going higher. Onion’s sword could cut my inviolable armor, which meant that he had the capstone blade-bound perk, or something like it. I wasn’t sure why I’d lost the riposte-off, whether it would have gone better if he had been the one to start it, or if it was down to dice rolls, or what.

“Do you ever wonder what it looks like to those insects out there?” asked Onion. “This display of skill is so far beyond their understanding of the art, they’re like illiterates holding a book club.”

“Well,” I said. “It’s good to know you have layers.” I really wished that my helm didn’t block my face, because I had on my best shit-eating grin, despite growing realization that this wasn’t going to be the cakewalk that I’d thought it would be.

I went into Total Commitment again, but kept my position as it was, not advancing forward on him, just sitting there, waiting for an attack. I was hoping that two minutes would pass with just this circling bullshit, and then I would get my automatic hit at max damage.

“You didn’t come by your skill through training,” said Onion. “When the arrogant enter training, they get weeded out, or they get exposed to their ignorance. You never had to pass that filter. The taunts aren’t taunts to you, they’re honest expressions of the deficiency of your character.”

I stayed silent. Total Commitment required it, because I was one with my sword, and to speak would have distracted from that oneness. I was only distantly aware that I could talk, and only with the piece of my brain that was waiting to see whether I should bail from the strike. I didn’t actually fight better in Total Commitment, I was pretty sure, I just gave up some executive power in order to have that one perfect hit.

“You’re a strange creature,” said Onion. “I’m trying to think of some way that I can keep you alive, to see what makes you tick, but I don’t think it’s possible. It’s time to get serious.”

He switched his sword from his right hand to his left. He was just far enough away that I couldn’t make the lunge to him in his brief moment of weakness.

If I had been fully myself, I might have told him off for being such a fucking cliche. What was next, was he going to remove the weights that he’d been training with? Was he going to reveal that he’d had his eyes closed the whole time? Or reveal that his sword was actually some super special sword forged by blah blah blah, its true power kept from me because displaying it before this audience would —

“This sword once belonged to Uther Penndraig,” said Onion. “It was one of his last acquisitions. We’ve pretended, for five hundred years, that all it would do is copy the powers of the sword you were fighting against. It’s far, far better than that. If pride is another of your sins, you may take pride in the fact that you are the person that caused me to reveal it to the world.”

Unfortunately, he didn’t tell me what in the hell the sword actually did, but if it was a weak meta-entad, then — well, I was one with my sword, and had a minute and a half to go before the full strike, so my actual thoughts in that corner of my mind that I was still holding onto were lagging and sluggish. A strong meta-entad, I thought as he approached me.

Just before he struck, his blade disappeared, all except for the hilt, and he kept swinging it towards me. I had a minor reach advantage on him, and pushed it, swinging the probability blade’s gray mass, but his blade popped back into existence, then became a blur, parrying my strike as every possible version of his blade met against every possible version of mine, presumably in some kind of race condition, because otherwise I would have assumed that one of our blades would be able to take a form that the other couldn’t defend against.

That blade disappearing and reappearing … well, that was the kind of thing that I would want to think about while I wasn’t focusing the entirety of my mind on swordplay. But that ability had a strong resemblance to one that I’d seen before, and even in my diminished state, backed into a corner of my own mind while I engaged in swordplay, I could realize that it was probably the flickerblade. His sword didn’t just copy mine, it copied hers, and that meant that it could probably copy any sword in the area, and if it could, then he’d be a fool not to plant dozens, hundreds of entad swords in the crowd, just on the off-chance that he really did need to use his super secret ability.

I think he did Amaryllis’ ability first just to psyche me out, because once that had failed, he began running through the gamut, throwing novel attack after novel attack at me. Some of them seemed like they were just tried on for size, like a (rather uninspired) flaming sword that was realistically never going to help him hit me. He took the ability of Gemma’s sword for just a moment, leaving him with two daggers, one in each hand, and I almost got him in that moment of weakness, but he dodged back and away, disengaging and forcing me to move forward. I didn’t know how his sword worked, what kind of control he had over what he got, but I was hoping that it would take him some time to find something devastatingly effective.

Total Commitment was ticking down, but all my skills were also ticking down, and if Total Commitment failed, then it was entirely possible that I was fucked.

Some other guy might have gotten increasingly desperate as he chunked through a dozen entad swords, but not Onion. He was methodical about it, taking his time, experimenting with the swords, though I suspected that he had some inkling of their ability just from locking onto them. One of them moved him so he was forty-five degrees to my right, but I parried with the probability blade, a proper parry, which entitled me to a riposte, which sent us into another cycle of increasingly fast ripostes. This time, I was the victor, and scored a hit, though it was nothing like what I had wanted, a cut that sliced through part of his offhand, removing a few fingers, nothing more. He bounded backward, checked his wound, then went right back into the fight, registering the injury and continuing on as though it hadn’t happened.

One of the swords he tried had a bit of a gun built into the handle, and he took a moment to retreat from me again so he could level the gun and fire it. I would have laughed at the stupidity of trying to shoot a blade-bound, if I’d been in my right mind, but I would have eaten that laugh, because what came from the gun was a cannonball, which was actually pretty scary. I parried it, and because I laughed in the face of physics, sent it right back at him going half the speed. I wasn’t terribly surprised that it didn’t do any good.

And it wasn’t long after that, when he was trying to get me with a sword that was weeping ooze, that Total Commitment paid off.

The whole attack took a sliver of a fraction of a second, not even long enough to properly appreciate, but as I watched it back in my mind’s eye, his body ripped apart and flying in different directions, properly obliterated, I could see the attack I’d somehow made, an impossibly perfect strike with the weight of the world behind, a transcendental moment of godhood, no more complete mastery of the blade in history. I savored it even as I stared in awe at pieces of Onion falling to the ground.

Then, he started to come back together.

Coda II

I had no idea what the fuck Tommul would make of this particular scene, but one thing was very clear, which was that we were a mile up in the air. It had been a while since I’d done any serious math, but I was pretty sure that a mile was higher than the three hundred feet that the Sky Treaty said I was supposed to stay under.

“Go away!” I screamed at Tommul, amplified by vibration magic. He was approaching very, very fast. Dragons had best-in-class abilities, which included vision, and I had known that Tommul had been in the area, but still, it felt so fucking unfair. “Go away!” I screamed again, putting the full force of my magic into it, “Go away, he’ll kill you!” but fuck, I wouldn’t have believed me either.

Even with how fast he was approaching, I had thought that Tommul would stop and talk, but no, he let loose with dragonfire as soon as he was within range.

The Space Plate I was wearing was supposed to protect against environmental effects, but whatever it would have done in a hot desert, it did very little against the dragonfire, even with my using still magic, even with a blast of vibration to try to disperse it. It wasn’t just screaming hot, but also clung to whatever it touched, like a worse version of napalm. I was covered in the stuff, the pain faint from my modifications but present, and did the only thing that I could do, which was to draw healing from my bones and then slap at Alvion’s Vambrace to get a change of armor. All at once I was in the Gardner’s Plate, an ink magic sword at my hip along with a shield that I had borrowed from Rosemallow, but the Vambrace itself was still coated in dragonfire, and it was searing hot. I used the sword to cut the straps, cutting my own skin in the process, and let the melting pieces of red-hot metal fall. It had burned my arm, on top of all the other burns that I’d suffered inside the armor. Whatever protection the Space Plate had offered me, it hadn’t been enough.

Unfortunately, paper bags are flammable, even when exposed to completely normal fire.

The Cannibal had fallen when I’d stopped supporting him, but he’d grabbed onto my foot at the last second, and used it to launch himself up, climbing me. I tried to still him, but of course that didn’t work, and he reared back for a punch at my kneecap. I used the Ring of Partial Incorporeality, part of the new set of gear, and made my whole leg incorporeal, which lost him his grip and made the punch whiff. He began falling again, and I wondered whether that was a legitimate weakness, whether he actually couldn’t fly. But I supposed there were hundreds of people down there to kill, thousands, depending on how large his range would end up being.

Tommul came back for a second pass, his three hundred feet of wingspan the biggest thing in the air. I wasn’t confident that incorporeality would actually protect me, because it worked through interaction with the ethereal plane, not just by making me intangible. Could dragonfire extend into the ethereal? I had no idea.

I had no real way of killing a dragon. The best bet would be a blood spear that gave me access to his bones, which I would burn to weaken him and power myself, the same trick I’d used against Mome Rath, but dragons had some natural magic resistances and immunities, and fuck if I thought a blood spear would actually be able to penetrate him even if that wasn’t the case.

Scratch that, I did have one thing that could kill the dragon, and he was falling away from me.

I stopped stilling myself and began to drop, which happened really really fast given that there was no air in the ethereal plane (I was holding my breath), and no friction to slow me. Tommul went into a dive, and as fast as I was dropping, like a stone in a vacuum, he was moving faster. I was sure to out-accelerate him given time, but I didn’t have that time.

I passed the Cannibal after about ten seconds had passed, a little less than halfway to the ground. I tried to twist around and see what was happening, mostly so I could defend against it, but it was nearly impossible with my body fully incorporeal, until I managed to still only part of my body, which sent me spinning. From there, trying to orient myself was a struggle, and I caught only glimpses of the battle happening above me, a gout of gold fire so fierce and so bright that it nearly blinded me, far more intense than before.

When my eyes started functioning again, I brought myself to a complete stop, hoping that the two of them would fall right past me and impact somewhere in the city, allowing me to get as far away as possible. Instead, I turned to look from my awkward angle and saw them above me, Tommul flapping his wings erratically to keep at a constant altitude.

Shia LaBeouf was on fire and punching a gold dragon in the face.

Tommul let out another gout of golden flame, and I squeezed my eyes shut tight and turned away. The dragonfire had done nothing, because the Cannibal was on top of Tommul’s head, his arm up to the shoulder in Tommul’s eye. Tommul screamed in pain, and clawed frantically at the Cannibal, opening up wounds, but not as deep as they should have been, given that Tommul’s claws were fucking enormous, each of them twice the size of the Cannibal. Having completely fucked up Tommul’s eye, the Cannibal landed a single solid punch to his head, and the frantic flapping of wings half as large as a football field suddenly stopped as Tommul began to fall from the sky. The Cannibal rode him for a few seconds, then kicked off with incredible superhuman power, sailing through the air, right at me.

I dropped, trying to move out of his way, wishing that I still had the Ring of Upward Bliss, but it was part of the other outfit, and that was tucked away inside Alvion’s Vambrace, which last I’d seen was falling half a mile to the ground while soaked in dragonfire. (So much fucking lost if it really was gone for good, but not remotely the time to think about it.) I kept myself fully incorporeal and prayed that it would be enough.

For a moment, I really thought that it would be. The Cannibal went straight through me, but when he wasn’t overlapping me anymore, he grabbed me by the wrist. I pulled out my sword with my other hand and began whacking away at him. It was an ink magic creation, one that was supposed to build in power with every hit, but it was fucking worthless, because every wound on the Cannibal was a surface wound.

He grappled with me, twisted the arm that he was holding onto, and bit down on my wrist, chomping right through the metal of the Gardner’s Plate as though it weren’t even there. It was a sacrifice that I was willing to make, if it would keep him busy for even a few seconds.

“I liked Holes!” I screamed at him, not really out of any plan, but because it was what came to mind. He continued on eating my wrist, and I decided to play what cards I had.

I let us drop, completely incorporeal. Without drag, there was no terminal velocity, just pure acceleration, and in a matter of seconds, as he ate my arm, we were going really fucking fast. I waited until we were perilously close to the ground, flung out the tendrils of Gardner’s Plate to help put him facing the ground, then put us back to corporeality. We slammed into a wall of air, which dislodged him, and I pushed still magic as hard as I could. He lost his grip and fell to the ground at speed, surprising me with a crack of bones as he hit. But he wasn’t there for more than half a second before he got up and limped away with the same intense determination that he’d shown before.

Quite a bit of my right hand was missing, much of the meat around my wrist completely gone, and my fingers only staying on by a little bit. The Ring of Incorporeality was missing. I pushed healing into the wound as I got to my feet, but I was missing bone, and huge missing chunks of flesh would take too much time and resources, so I just did enough to stop the bleeding.

I landed on top of the building we’d fallen on, which as it turned out was Greychapel. As I looked over, I saw that a huge portion of the building was caved in, because Tommul had dropped like a rock and smashed right into the building. Normally that kind of thing wouldn’t be a problem, because velocity wards would stop something going that hard and fast, the same way they would stop other kinds of aerial bombardment, but dragons had powerful magic resistance, and that applied to wards as much as it did to anything else.

And normally caving in a building would be pretty terrible, but caving in one that was packed to the gills with extradimensional space? That was on a different level of urban calamity. Where Greychapel had crunched in, whole rooms had spilled out the sides, and the internal wreckage of the primary legislative building of Anglecynn had barfed out into the surrounding streets, filling them up with walls, floors, tables, chairs, cabinets, and (I was sure) bodies. Tommul himself was visible as a wing sticking up out of hole he’d made when he slammed into the building.

The Cannibal’s modus operandi was becoming more clear: attack, eat, get fought off, go find other prey, except that some people would just die from his first attack, because not everyone could survive losing a limb. It wasn’t quite horror movie logic, but it was close, and by that reckoning, I had a bit of time, minutes, let’s say, maybe more given the sheer number of victims that the Cannibal was likely to go after. With everything that Amaryllis had told me, it would probably be everyone in the War Room when his name had been invoked, and maybe everyone in Greychapel.

If I was being really cynical, that might give me more time.

Unfortunately, ‘time for what’ was a complete fucking mystery. Time to find another paper bag, time to heal my wounds, time to reset my bones, or to regroup with the others. They had all been in the upper half of the War Room, or maybe coming down the stairs, which meant that they were potential targets.

I tried ink magic and then gave up. What I needed was a magic item that could manipulate a paper bag onto someone’s head, but ink magic worked best when you approached a problem from the side, making items that could solve your intended problems as though they weren’t designed to do that. If you needed a wooden stake to kill a vampire, then a gun that fired wooden stakes was an incredibly lame and uncreative way to do that, and in ink magic terms, that meant a crappy product that would last you a single use before crumpling, if that. And to make an entad that could accomplish ‘put a paper bag on a specific someone’s head’ was really, really hard to approach from the side. I gave up after about a minute, not wanting to waste time when I didn’t know how much time I had. I was sure that it would come to me later, the perfect elegant entad to design that would only obviously be the solution in context.

I took off across the roof, trying to formulate a plan. The paper bag thing had fucking worked, as idiotic as it was, all I needed was to do it a second time and not have a fucking dragon appear from nowhere to ruin everything. (But ‘from nowhere’ in the sense that every report of Tommul being overhead was now obvious foreshadowing for that single moment.)

I didn’t have a firm grasp on the layout of Greychapel, so I simply ran over to the hole that Tommul had made and jumped down, using still magic to keep from breaking a leg. I ended up in a room that had been half pushed out when the star magic had failed and the extradimensional stuff had come undone, but after I’d gone past the door, everything looked more or less fine. I started running, looking into various rooms I passed, hoping that I would find a paper bag somewhere, hoping that wherever the Cannibal was, there would be some screaming that I could use to find him. Vibration magic was dialed up, but I heard nothing.

I saw a door with frosted glass, and stopped to open it when a thought occurred to me. I was hoping that there would be a trash can. Aerb didn’t have plastics, which meant no plastic bags, which meant that people used paper liners or paper bags instead, and I was praying that it would be close enough by whatever standards the Cannibal operated under.

Unfortunately, standing behind the door was former child actor Shia LaBeouf, breathing hard and with blood smeared around his mouth (the other blood that had soaked him before, mysteriously missing). We stared at each other for a fraction of a second, and then he went for me, moving in low and trying to bite. I had exhausted every attack I had, and lost my sword in the fall, so I tried to go over him, hoping that I could get into the room and find some salvation there.

He tried to grab me by the leg as I jumped over his lunge, and I tried passion magic to give me extra speed and avoid his grip, but this time it didn’t work, and he clutched my left knee, bringing me to the ground. With a squeeze, he shattered my kneecap, the armor there, the muscles, and everything else, shearing the leg entirely with the force of his grip, and I was hoping that would give me the time I needed. I flopped into the office, leaving my leg behind, and went under the desk that was just inside, hoping against hope that there was a trash can there.

There was, and I grabbed it, heart hammering in my chest. I dumped out the papers inside and grabbed the bag, barely able to hold onto it with my wounded hand, turning back toward the Cannibal and praying that he wouldn’t just tear it from me, because if he did, then I was fucked. My bad hand went to the mome bone on my bandolier, praying that it would work, that I could maneuver the bag with only one hand.

Instead, I turned back toward the door and saw nothing. He was gone, and my leg with him, nothing but a mess of blood where he’d handicapped me. I couldn’t hear him, and my hearing was really good.

Twenty seconds later saw me limping along down the hallway of Greychapel, using a vine from the Gardner’s Plate as a makeshift prosthetic that wasn’t going to last me very long. I had a paper bag in hand, and another one that was folded up and tucked into the belt that held my sheath. From what I had seen, there were literally paper bags in every single room of Greychapel, but I knew that the Cannibal would be back for me, because that was how these things worked. Eventually I wouldn’t have enough body parts to keep going, or I would run out of bones for healing, and then I would die.

Eventually I did hear screaming. I had figured out a strategy of rotating the vines from the Gardner’s Plate, keeping them fresh by only using one at a time, and it was a mostly functional way to walk. I tried to keep in mind the horror movie rules, how every door could contain him, how he would jump out from the shadows when I least expected it. That was built into the game of ACSLB as a fundamental rule. The Cannibal being right behind the door I opened? That was a classic Shia Surprise.

I reached the room with all the screaming through a side door, and saw a concentrated offensive being torn apart by the Cannibal, piece by piece. It was an enormous room, and eventually I realized that it was the titular chapel of Greychapel, a place used for public assemblies and grand speeches rather than any religious observations. It would have been a dizzyingly large room, at a certain point in my life, but I had spent quite a bit of time in a house with a flair for the grandiose.

There were dozens of people involved in the fight, and dozens dead. Specialists must have been brought in, because there were way more people in armor than there had been in the War Room, and I hadn’t had a good view of the upper balcony, but I was pretty sure that it hadn’t been composed of specialists. I had no idea what the fuck they thought they were going to do about it, but it was very possible that they didn’t know what they were going up against, because they might have been pointed at the problem without proper intel. The Cannibal was ripping through them, tanking all the fancy entads and high-powered magic that Anglecynn could bring to bear. Some of them momentarily worked, but they would stop after a moment, just enough to let someone escape with a grievous wound, or as a distraction. There was at least one revision mage at work, undoing damage, but there were limits. The Cannibal could shrug off any damage, blow through any ward, and fully negate anything from still magic to revision.

I watched a woman in shimmering, inky black armor slip forward. It was Pallida, wielding her trident in one hand, a brown paper bag in the other. I couldn’t be sure that she wasn’t operating on her own, but I hoped it meant that the others were alive and well somewhere in the melee. I saw Pallida move on the Cannibal, using someone else’s attack as a distraction. She almost managed to slip the bag over his head, but he ducked down, moving blisteringly fast, and elbowed her in the stomach, which sent her flying backward. There wasn’t even a moment’s pause before he launched himself across the room to where a cluster of people had been aiming ranged weapons at him.

“Use the fucking paper bags!” I heard Amaryllis scream at the top of her lungs, her voice amplified so hard that I hoped she wasn’t deafening the people next to her. She was unarmed (and still missing an arm), but trying to direct forces that she had no business directing was going about as well as you’d expect, especially when the thing she was trying to get them to do was so clearly stupid. It was actually so stupid that I probably would have listened to her, on the theory that no one would say something so stupid unless there was a good reason, but maybe I would have been like everyone else and ignored her.

I rushed forward, limping, trying ineffectually to use blood magic to speed along my steps, which didn’t work so well with only one leg, since the vine I was using as my left leg couldn’t quite keep up. I had three of the mome bones on my backup bandolier, and that would allow me a brief window of time, assuming that the first time it had worked wasn’t just because it was novel. My working theory was that because the Cannibal was a meme, then maybe he was especially vulnerable to an antimeme, because that was just stupid enough to make sense within the framework of this whole stupid thing.

Anglecynn was bringing out the big guns, I had to give them that. I saw someone holding what I thought was probably one of the portal rings from that time my group had killed Dracula, and it was rapidly pushing out a wide variety of magic, from what I assumed was a well-prepared site some miles away. It was all worthless, naturally, and in some cases, completely at odds with what I knew to be the winning approach, because those pulses of magic that came out of the portals meant that melee only got their chance when there was a break in firing.

I waited until just such a break, one caused by the Cannibal launching himself at a massed group of people who were clearly trying their best to act as support or artillery, and pushed myself harder to get there.

Amaryllis had been among the crowd that the Cannibal landed in, and she caught sight of me as she ran from him. She was still dressed for Court, rather than for battle, her dress bloodied, her body much worse for the wear. She must have caught a head wound at some point, because half of her face was covered in blood, and one of her eyes was shut.

“Get him,” she shouted to me as I hobbled my way over.

I waited until I thought I was close enough, then started burning a unicorn bone, touching it in the bandolier with my maimed hand. I had no idea whether it would actually provide any benefit, but fuck if I didn’t have to try.

The amount of firepower being directed on the Cannibal was way, way too much, and it was stopping him from feeding, which was one of the only things that actually slowed him down. In a perfect world, they would only have been trying new attacks after seeing certain approaches fail, but we were far from a perfect world.

I did my best to see the attacks coming and get out of the way, but everyone was getting as lethal as they could get, and when the Cannibal killed a rune mage that had been powering up a green beam weapon, it lanced through the air, slicing through me and a few others.

Dying wasn’t quite an old hat, but I’d been burning my way through the unicorn’s bones for quite a while now, and I was used to utterly failing and having to reset.

What I wasn’t used to was things being different. No, this time when things reset, the Cannibal stopped what he was doing and looked at me. It all went differently from there, because he didn’t go for the rune mage, he went for me.

I had the bag ready, unfolded, and waited until the last possible moment to start burning the mome bone (my hand positioned so that one finger was on the unicorn bone, one on the mome bone, with the fingers I had left). All at once, the Cannibal stopped what he was doing, and there wasn’t a moment of hesitation before he moved on to the next person in his field of view. I bounded after him, hampered by the vine leg, and was just about to slide the paper bag down over his head with my free hand when I got blasted with a beam of green.

That fucking rune mage had killed me, though in some sense I couldn’t blame him, because he literally couldn’t have known I was there. I tried the same route again, waiting for the Cannibal to approach me, this time circling to the left in order to get him closer to his eventual target. I burned the same mome bone again, and this time, held the paper bag in my mouth for just long enough that I could pull out my returning dagger and chuck it right at the rune mage, bonking him in the head hard enough to give him second thoughts about the attack he was charging up.

As soon as I slipped the bag over the Cannibal’s head, he stopped what he was doing. I took my finger off the mome bone, but kept burning the unicorn bone, trying to squeak one last second out of it in case someone fucked this up for me. I yelled for good measure, “Stop! He’s contained!”, knowing that it was ridiculous.

The unicorn bone had reached its limit, and I let the loop end. Memories of parallel timelines came rushing back to everyone around me, and I prayed that no one would shoot at the Cannibal, that no one had explosives ready and waiting to go, that nothing would fuck this up. But by the rule of three —

Two things happened in quick succession. The first was that twenty people in Imperial-standard matte grey shimmerplate appeared around the chapel, each of them fully armed. The second was that the side of the chapel crashed open, stained glass raining down, as an enormous one-eyed gold dragon stuck his head in. For just a moment I could see a golden flame at the back of his throat, but he stopped, closing his mouth and simply staring.

Compared to the earlier roar of battle, there was relative silence, just pieces of building falling down, the cries of the injured, and people speaking quickly to each other.

“It’s stupid,” I said, amplifying my voice as much as I could. “It’s really fucking stupid, but if the bag comes off his head, he’ll kill every fucking person here, whether you teleport out or hide in extradimensional space. This is literally the only way, it is very, very dumb, but I swear that it’s true.”

Tommul looked like he was going to roast me, or to make some threat, but after a huff of air from his nose, which swept warm air over all of us, he retracted his head and took off, the sound and wind of his wings rattling the windows.

“Finch!” I yelled, looking around, trying to see the gnome that I was certain had come in with the shimmerplate goons.

Figaro Finch stepped out from behind a pew, with none of the dust, blood, and gore that everyone else had on them. “How sure are you that this will hold?” he asked me.

“Eighty percent,” I replied. “Maybe less.”

“And how in the holy fuck did you know it would work?” asked Finch. He was giving me the stink eye, like this whole thing was my fault. I heard murmurs from the crowd, which with every passing minute looked less and less like they would fuck this up.

“We have this guy back on Earth,” I said, gesturing at Shia LaBeouf. “If I thought some asshole would be dumb enough to summon him, I would have been shouting it loud and wide. Not that anyone would have believed me.” Not that I’d had any confidence in this particular solution.

“We’ll take him,” said Finch.

“Who are you?” asked a voice from among the fighters. It was a guy that I recognized almost entirely from his bucket of shurikens, and whose name I had forgotten, but it was either Basil, Heath, or Aster.

“Imperial Affairs, Uniquities Division,” said Finch. “And we’ll be taking him for containment.”

“By the hells you will,” said Shuriken Bucket, stepping forward. It didn’t look like the Cannibal had gotten him, because he still had all his parts. “This isn’t an imperial matter.”

I was getting nervous. I’d gotten a quest — albeit one with no text — and then no update. That meant there was still a chance this could go sour, a way for someone to let the cat out of the bag, as it were.

“If he ever gets out, we’re fucked,” I said. “Best guess, he’s got a list of people who need killing, and the more time passes, the further those people get from each other, which means expected fatalities increase, because other people get in the way. Almost all of the people he wants to kill are Anglish, and a fair number are nobles.” I looked at Finch. “Have you ever contained anything like this before?”

“No,” he replied. “It’s still our jurisdiction.”

“Then you exercise caution and trap him in the deepest, darkest hole that you can find,” I said. “You put on extra bags for protection, you trap him in quickset goo,” I was hoping that was a thing, “you send him into the future, you do everything in your power to keep him from ever having that bag taken off his head.”

“The Empire doesn’t have jurisdiction here,” said Shuriken Bucket, moving toward me, then taking a look at the naked man with a bag over his head that was standing next to me, and coming up short. “It’s Anglecynn that’s at risk. It’s Anglecynn that should handle containment.”

Fuck off, I thought. “Did Amaryllis tell you proper protocol?” I asked.

Shuriken Bucket (who I was thinking was probably Heath) hesitated. “She did, but —”

“And did you see people running straight at the hyperviolent, invincible cannibal with a paper bag, trying to get one on his head?” I asked. I changed out which vine was holding me up, trying not to let that break my momentum.

“Yes,” he said, gritting his teeth. I didn’t know if he was in charge, if there was anyone in charge, but he certainly seemed to be speaking for the others.

“But you weren’t making a concerted effort to do what you were told,” I said. “The reason that I’m giving this force of pure destruction over to Uniquities instead of to anyone in this government is that I can trust Uniquities to do what it’s told and to take threats seriously,” I said. “Right now, you don’t have that trust.”

“You’re a member of this Court,” said Shuriken Bucket taking another step toward me. “We aren’t losing control of this weapon. We aren’t putting the safety of what remains of the War Council into the hands of the Empire.”

“Hyacinth did this,” I spat at him, “If it’s in the hands of the councils, you know that there’s still risk. Someone will look at a manifest of everyone who was in the vicinity and think about whether or not to pull the trigger. That’s how the Court works, Heath,” really hoping that I wasn’t wrong about which cousin he was, “People make their calculations based on their personal interests, and fuck anyone who gets in the way. Say what you want about the Empire, but at least it makes an effort to stick to its principles.”

Part of that was just fueled by misplaced anger, and I wasn’t wholly convinced that anything I’d said about the Empire was actually true, especially given the things that Raven had said to Finch, and the covert shit that I knew for a fact Uniquities got up to. But Heath didn’t call me out on it, he only shrank back slowly, and gave a slow nod to Figaro Finch.

The men and women in shimmerplate took some time in approaching. I was sure that some or all of them were mages, and I was also sure that it was no coincidence that they showed up after all the fighting was done. They handled the Cannibal gingerly, double-bagged him, and then warped him out, leaving only Figaro Finch behind.

Quest Complete: Where’s the Beef? - You have successfully captured Emmy award winner Shia LaBeouf in a paper bag, from which he will never escape, unless he does.

“This is a shitshow,” he said to me, speaking under his breath.

“We need to start bottling the dead,” said Amaryllis, her voice raised and amplified. “We need search and rescue, and we need medical. Anyone able-bodied should be helping with those efforts. Heath, you’re in charge of the bottling, Grak —” there was a moment of honest fear as she looked around, trying to find him, but Grak stepped out from a doorway, quite some distance from where the action was, “— Grak, you’re coordinating search and rescue, and Aster, you’re on medical.”

For a moment, I really thought that someone was going to ask her who had put her in charge, but no one spoke up, and after a brief pause, everyone who hadn’t already been dealing with the dead or wounded began to move into action.

Family

It was well after midnight when we went back to the Erstwhile Manor. We were a bit split on whether to head to the Hotel Delzora instead, but the Erstwhile Manor required less in the way of stairs, and I was still down a leg, though the vines were more or less adequate for moving around, so long as I only used one at a time. We got a car, the three of us, Amaryllis, Grak, and myself, with Grak up front next to the driver.

“Where’s Pallida?” I asked Amaryllis as the car started moving.

“Dead,” replied Amaryllis.

“Oh,” I said. I felt my heart sink a bit. “I thought maybe she’d ducked out.”

“No,” replied Amaryllis. Her lips were tight.

“Shit,” I replied, not knowing what to say. “Do — do you know where she went? I mean —”

“No,” replied Amaryllis. She looked exhausted, and was resting her head against the seat. “We’ll have to follow up. Gemma is dead too, by the way.”

“Wait, really?” I asked. “That’s — she had a whole thing, fox people and their grudge, I barely had a chance to talk to her.”

I resisted the urge to ask what the point of her was, because it would have made me sound like a dick, but there was some validity to that line of questioning, at least so far as the narrative went. Hadn’t Gemma been with us for a reason? She’d had a whole backstory that I hadn’t asked her about, and her role in the plot had been incredibly minimal. I could feel myself going down the narrative rabbit hole, thinking that maybe Gemma had died because I wasn’t particularly interested in hearing her life story. But maybe it was just one of those things that happened in tabletop games, where you wrote up a big backstory and then died in the first encounter. Maybe it was a lesson that people could just die, their narrative purpose unfulfilled.

In a way, hearing that Gemma had died affected me more than hearing Pallida was ‘dead’. It was grim in a way that I hadn’t expected.

“We thought a velocity mage would be our best bet,” said Amaryllis, oblivious to my train of thought or tactfully ignoring it. “When he came back down, she was one of the first in. He was faster.” I could understand some of her grim expression.

We hadn’t really had a chance to talk inside Greychapel, except to coordinate. The actual death toll from the Cannibal had only been forty-three people, though with perhaps twice that number having had a bite taken out of them or worse. Another thirty-two had been killed in the extradimensional collapse, most of them in smaller meetings or working in a few of the Greychapel offices. It was a surprisingly low death toll, but disproportionately made up of members of the Court.

“Solace?” I asked, not really wanting to hear the answer. I wished now that I had noted the absences earlier, but I had just thought — well, I had just thought that everyone was doing their part, and it wasn’t me who was coordinating efforts, I was just using bone magic to heal people up. In retrospect, Solace’s absence was conspicuous, but —

“She’s fine,” said Amaryllis. “She wasn’t even at the trial. I think she’s still at the manor, actually.”

“Oh,” I said, letting out a sigh of relief. “And … Lisi?” She was the last of the people I actually cared about.

“I’m not sure, Juniper,” replied Amaryllis. She still had her good eye closed.

She had gotten healing, but no replacement for the limb yet, not because one wasn’t available, but because the kind of things that could very quickly heal a limb tended to be quite permanent and not terribly good. We were going to get top-of-the-line replacements, either exact duplicates or something better than what we’d had before. Amaryllis’ bad eye must have been plucked from her head, because the liberal healing she’d gotten hadn’t fixed it. That, too, would get either a replacement or complete restoration.

I frowned at her answer and tried to think. Lisi had been a part of the War Council, would she have run or stayed to fight? Run, if she could, though she also seemed to be the sort of person who would take action on the assumption that if she didn’t, no one else would. I hoped that she had made it through.

“Wait,” I said. “Where’s Raven?” I was sure that the Cannibal hadn’t gotten her, because I’d seen her after. Hadn’t I?

“She was pretty badly injured,” said Amaryllis, and that was coming from someone who had lost an eye and an arm, speaking to someone who had lost a leg and part of a hand. “When she heard that Uniquities had taken the Cannibal, she grilled Finch and then left to go supervise their containment procedures. She wanted Grak with her, but —”

“The survivors needed me,” said Grak from the front seat.

“Are you okay?” I asked Amaryllis.

“Are you?” she asked back.

“Missing a leg,” I said. “Hand is fucked up. Worried that Tommul is going to come back. Worried that I’m going to get another bill from the Draconic Confederacy. Worried that the Cannibal is going to escape, but the next time I’ll have less warning. I thought that we were basically done in Anglecynn, and fuck me if there wasn’t another fight for my life. But don’t dodge my question.”

“I need a new eye and a new arm, but that will be handled tomorrow,” said Amaryllis. She was silent for a moment. “I didn’t handle Hyacinth properly.”

“No?” I asked. “And … where is she? Out of the glove, right?”

“She bled out,” said Amaryllis.

“Oh,” I said. “Shit. Fuck, I’d only meant to cut her vocal cords, I just didn’t want her to say it again.”

“That’s more mercy than I would have shown,” replied Amaryllis. She was slightly slumped in her seat. “It reflects poorly on me.”

“It does?” I asked. Killing Hyacinth outright seemed reasonable to me, the only reason I hadn’t intentionally done it was out of reflex.

“She called in the Cannibal knowing that it would almost certainly kill her,” said Amaryllis. “She knew what would follow. She tried to get us to go somewhere else, but when we didn’t … she’s dead, so there won’t be any answers. But I’m forced to confront the possibility that maybe she really did let me see behind the mask. Maybe she loved Larkspur. It’s possible that she was pregnant with a child she cared about, and really did lose it. I thought that I had the measure of her. I thought that it was all an act, because it was the kind of act that I would have put on.”

“You think Onion was like a father to her?” I asked.

“I don’t know,” replied Amaryllis. “Her parents died when she was young, as did mine. When that happens, you either grow up fast or you find someone to take you under their wing. Sometimes both. After my mom died, Rosemallow was as close as I had to a mother.” She pursed her lips. “I knew they were close, I just thought that it was political. I thought they were playing the game like Rosemallow plays the game, like I would play the game. And that’s not what Hyacinth was doing. She was trying to kill you, to kill us, at the expense of her own life, because she thought that was what was best for Anglecynn.”

“You might be giving the opposition a little bit too much credit,” I said.

“Maybe,” she said. “I can’t help but feel like this was preventable. Like there was a path we didn’t take.”

“Sure,” I replied. “It would be a pretty bad tabletop game if there weren’t multiple paths we could take. A good Dungeon Master makes plans that can survive the party deciding that they want to do things a stupid way.”

“And you think we have a good Dungeon Master?” asked Amaryllis. This was usually the point where she would have arched an eyebrow, but she just sat back in resignation.

“Eh,” I said. “Good in some ways, bad in others. I’m tempted to say more good than bad. Trying to be objective about it, he does some of the dumb shit that I did when I was starting out.” I felt oddly at peace, for everything we’d gone through in the past few days, not even all that tired. “I would set up these things in advance, not traps necessarily, but sometimes traps, sometimes literal traps, and … it would seem like some of these things came out of nowhere to the players, because they would miss the hints that I’d prepared, or they would figure out a way to skip the exposition, and then I’d have to make a choice about whether or not to fuck them over.”

“And sometimes you made things like Fel Seed,” said Amaryllis.

“That’s a different issue,” I said. “That was anger and spite. Part of a general trend of including things that the group didn’t really care all that much about because I had developed an intense and personal obsession that lasted a few weeks. I don’t think that we’ve seen all that much like that on Aerb, because it’s all so … so me.” It was hard to describe. “I don’t think we have an adversarial relationship.” There were too many proper climaxes, too many fights that we’d just outright won without them being undercut.

“And you think there was another path?” asked Amaryllis. “A way that this didn’t end with so many dead?”

“Sure,” I replied. “Probably several ways.”

“Okay,” said Amaryllis.

“Do you feel bad about them all being dead?” I asked. I didn’t, not really, not even if it was true that they were all people with their own stories, not (just) terrible villains. Too many lines had been crossed for me to feel much regret, even if there were another way.

“I don’t know,” she sighed. “It’s this feeling that we left utility on the table. The outcome is obviously not as good as it could have been.”

“We will take some time,” said Grak. “Process first, then speak with cool heads.”

“My head is perfectly cool, thank you,” said Amaryllis. “But yes, we should take some time before we make big decisions.”

But when we got back to the Erstwhile Manor, Rosemallow was waiting for us.

“I need a situation report,” said Rosemallow once we had taken our seats in the White Room. She didn’t seem like she gave much of a fuck about our injuries. Grak had begged off to go be with Solace, and my personal feeling was that he was a lucky bastard to be able to clock out.

“How much do you know?” asked Amaryllis. “I don’t want to repeat anything. And we’ve had a long day, as I’m sure you can understand.”

“I’ve had a pot of Dalldear ready for the last few hours, since the initial reports came in,” said Rosemallow. “This is important.”

Amaryllis frowned at the pot of tea on the table, then poured herself a cup and drank it down without spending any time seeing whether it was cool enough. I followed suit, and was mildly surprised that it was both the perfect temperature, and the best tea I’d ever had in my life. It took almost no time for it to go into effect, and I felt rejuvenated, as though I’d had eight hours of sleep, a full meal, and a few glasses of water. It came with a crash, as a lot of such drugs did, but for the moment it had put me back in my right mind.

“Hyacinth came to us after the trial was concluded,” said Amaryllis. “She was distraught and claimed to have suffered a miscarriage. There were a few accusations against the two of us, and then she summoned the Cannibal. We fought it and contained it.”

“How?” asked Rosemallow. “And if you’re speaking of what I think you’re speaking of, be cautious in what you say.”

It wasn’t just the name she was worried about. The phenomenon of ACSLB didn’t just care about the name, it cared about where you got it from, and the tracking on that was complex. The method the Penndraigs used was a phonograph on a loop in the woods, which was used in preference to other methods because it didn’t seem to trigger the same links. Writing it down on a piece of paper, then handing that piece of paper to another person was proven to cause problems, and by that, I mean that people had died. If you picked up a piece of paper with the name and handed it to someone else, that could cause problems too, were they ever to say it. And because it didn’t just target those who knew the name, but also those who were a part of the chain of command or causality, and because it erred on the side of killing munchkins, there were some false positives. Say too much, and that might be interpreted as priming, or ordering, or coercing, or something that would get you killed.

We had no idea whether we were actually safe. We hadn’t defused the bomb, we had only stuck it inside a box, hoping that nothing would set the fuse going again. If someone said the name, would that spawn in a new one? Would it pull the old one out of custody? We didn’t know, and had no way of safely testing it.

“We put a paper bag over its head,” said Amaryllis. Rosemallow narrowed her eyes slightly, waiting for her to continue. “That’s it,” said Amaryllis. “That’s how we beat him. It turned him docile.”

“What was done with him?” asked Rosemallow, after she’d taken a moment to process. She was processing fast, but that wasn’t any surprise, because surely she’d gotten a fair bit of information from other sources.

“We handed him over to the Empire, through a contact we have within Imperial Affairs,” said Amaryllis. “With the way they showed up, we suspect that they were monitoring the situation remotely.”

“And the dragon?” asked Rosemallow.

“My fault,” I said. “I used an entad to take the Cannibal away from civilians and give me some room to try other strategies. Unfortunately, it took me above the legal limits, and as the dragon in question was already out for my blood … well. It would have been covered by exigent circumstances, but I’m not sure he knew about my recent change in status. The Cannibal knocked him out, he fell into Greychapel, through the wards, and that was more or less that. I’m counting on Anglecynn’s support where the Draconic Confederacy is concerned.”

“You’ll have it, of course,” said Rosemallow.

We sat in silence for a moment, and she took a sip of her own tea, which I assumed wasn’t the same brew we were drinking, given its effects.

“It’s obviously a complete disaster,” said Rosemallow. “That said, we need to take stock of where we stand with respect to the Court, the councils, and the kingdom. On that count, I think a level-headed assessment is that we now have the necessary leverage to make sweeping changes, to say nothing of the obstacles that have been removed.”

“Yes, let’s pat ourselves on the back,” said Amaryllis. “Now’s a great time for that.”

“I’m talking about next steps,” replied Rosemallow, her face stern. “The faster we act, the more control we have over what happens next. I’m already doing my best to control the mass media, assuring the public that this was not, in fact, a rogue dragon attack on the legislature. Obviously Hyacinth was to blame, and you named her publically, so that can’t be undone, but we can control the narrative, the why of her doing what she did.”

“Aunt Rosemallow,” Amaryllis began.

“This is time sensitive,” said Rosemallow, looking between the two of us. “You wanted your Second Grand Reconciliation? This is exactly the moment to strike. Obviously not publically, but the groundwork needs to be laid. The councils need to be prepared for our roadmap. There will be pushback, possibly sooner than later. This is our window.”

Something in Amaryllis’ expression changed, and she gave Rosemallow a hard stare. For a moment I thought that she would repeat the plea to speak about this later, but it must have been something else, because she had that same look on her face that she had when she was thinking hard.

“After Onion died, two things happened in quick succession,” said Amaryllis. She had straightened somewhat, and was taking on a more formal tone. “First, Phlox suffered from some sort of medical emergency, one which presumably happened when she was without fast or easy medical care. It slipped through a crack. She was important, so she would have had entads, pharmaceuticals, and mages. It’s very true that you can’t protect against everything, but she would have been well protected, medically speaking.”

“Make your point, dear,” said Rosemallow, voice calm.

“The same goes for Hyacinth,” said Amaryllis. “If she was pregnant, especially with the child of a man she loved, or even if she was thinking in terms of politics, pregnant with the son of a dead man, she would have been taking precautions. She would have covered the bases she was able to cover. And yet her unborn child died, likely within hours of Phlox having her own medical problems.”

Rosemallow waited for the accusation, head held high.

I had taken it for granted that this was just narrative convenience, that everything was getting wrapped up with a little bow because that was just how plots worked. If something hadn’t happened to Phlox, then she would still be a thorn in our side, so the plot couldn’t be fully resolved without her being removed somehow. And Hyacinth had to be taken out too, one way or another, just for this ordeal to be truly over, and if the mechanism for that was her going over the edge … well, something had to push her over the edge.

But even if that was all narrative convenience, it would make more sense for these ‘coincidences’ to have been the result of clear cause and effect, beyond just the stresses of losing someone important.

“It was you,” said Amaryllis. “This isn’t a window of opportunity, it’s a window that you wedged open.”

There was a slight quirk of Rosemallow’s lips, just a hint of a frown. “I didn’t anticipate that Hyacinth would cause such problems,” said Rosemallow. “For whatever small part I played in the events of today, I apologize.”

“How did you do it?” asked Amaryllis. “Poison?”

“Does it matter?” asked Rosemallow. “Hyacinth is dead. Phlox will likely stay in a hospital bed for the rest of her life. Those are the salient facts. If you’ve made up your mind about what it is that I’ve done —”

“I haven’t,” said Amaryllis. “I’m asking you directly. I want you to be honest with me. We’re in one of the most secure rooms in Anglecynn. Tell us what you did.”

“Three people can keep a secret if two of them are dead,” said Rosemallow. “And even then, one must be concerned with the prospect of damnation. You understand the world we live in, Amaryllis. Secrets can be ripped from your head. The imperial regime has only been partially successful in stomping out soul mages, and soul mages are only the tip of the spear. You do not tell things to people if you want them to stay secret, even if you trust them fully and completely. It doubles the attack surface. You know all this.”

“Doubling the attack surface — tripling it, as it were, is a cost, one that you’re being asked to pay,” said Amaryllis. She didn’t mention that a soul mage would have a hard time with us, I assume because it was something we all knew. She wasn’t trying to negotiate, she was using force.

Rosemallow hesitated, gazing first at Amaryllis, then flicking her eyes to me, just for a moment. “Phlox was poisoned,” Rosemallow finally said. “I had some insight into the particulars of the entad she used to prevent herself from being poisoned, and there were certain flaws in it: it allowed the poison to stay within the body, inert. The poison was administered last year. It was just a matter of where and when I would have someone ward against her entad, after I’d had its signature acquired on a separate occasion. The entad ward was woven into the existing ward against teleportation keys in her home, where it wouldn’t be noticed except on close inspection. The warding alteration has already been removed, and at this point it seems safe to assume that it wasn’t found.”

“And Hyacinth?” asked Amaryllis.

“Entad assistance, and poison of a different sort,” said Rosemallow. “She was given a bottle of pills, recommended by her doctor for the health of her child. It was only a matter of exchanging those with something else.”

“Not lethal for her though,” said Amaryllis.

“No,” replied Rosemallow. “If it was Larkspur’s child, which it might well have been, then it would have been a liability on several fronts. Phlox is old, and diagnostics are difficult, but for someone young and healthy, like Hyacinth is, too many questions would be raised. There are limits to the number of moves it’s safe to make at once.”

Amaryllis was tense, but it was the kind of tension that came with smooth, calculated movements, the tension of a professional working their muscles. “And my mother?” asked Amaryllis.

“I’m far from the only person in the Court who has employed poison, Amaryllis,” said Rosemallow. Her face fell, and she took on a tone of pleading. “Admitting to one poisoning does not therefore mean that I admit to all possible poisonings. Amaryllis, I have read your diary, I know the doubts and hard feelings you’ve had towards me, but I did not poison your mother.”

“You had the means, the motive, and the opportunity,” said Amaryllis.

“Amaryllis, it was many years ago, there was a full inquiry, as there often is,” said Rosemallow, continuing to look as though this was a painful accusation from her beloved niece.

“I don’t trust a single fucking thing that comes out of the councils,” said Amaryllis. “And I don’t trust you.”

“And what would change your mind?” asked Rosemallow. “What possible evidence would convince you, if you’ve arrived at this conclusion through no evidence at all?”

Amaryllis didn’t hesitate in the slightest. “Submit to inspection by Juniper,” said Amaryllis.

I glanced at her, then back at Rosemallow.

“You suggest that I give up my dignity and my autonomy, and allow a capital crime to take place within my own home, all by way of indulging your mistrust and paranoia?” asked Rosemallow. “I won’t say that I cannot, but the cost is too high.”

“He would just be looking,” said Amaryllis. “It would be no different from what an anolia does. He would make no changes at all. If you cared for my mother, that’s evidence. If you care about me. I won’t say that it will be enough to sway me, but it’s concrete evidence.”

Rosemallow hesitated. It was still a loss of dignity, that was certain, but not autonomy, and Rosemallow would have submitted to inspection by anolia on a semi-regular basis, just as a matter of course for a high-level official. She had to decide whether she trusted us or not, whether she trusted me, and if she didn’t trust me … well, I was Uther reborn, wasn’t I? And I was the key to absolute control of the kingdom, wasn’t I? She was probably thinking not just about trust, but about what I could find within her, what might incriminate her not just of the specific thing she was being accused of, but of other things that would cause more of a rift between us than outright refusal. It was a given that I would look at her values, and what would I find there? Nothing that could incriminate her, surely, because a soul mage had access to relatively little unless they manipulated you into being someone who divulged things. And if we were to break our agreement, if I were to just soulfuck her rather than looking as I’d agreed to … maybe it was her measure of us that this wasn’t something that we would do, not unless we were planning to kill her. Maybe she really thought that her soul would look good to me.

“Very well,” said Rosemallow. “If this is what it will take.”

Amaryllis turned to me and signed in Gimb. Go into her memories. Trace values. Take your time. I will stall.

Rosemallow didn’t ask about the hand signals, but she definitely did notice them, because Amaryllis wasn’t trying to hide them. I wondered how much fear was coursing through Rosemallow’s system at the moment, because this was one of the scariest things you could let another person do, especially given all the connotations that soul magic had on Aerb.

She let me though, holding out a hand for me to take. I sat beside her and felt the veins beneath her wrinkled skin for the blood that flowed inside of her. I was worried about a trap, naturally, but Amaryllis was there beside me, and it was clear that I was an outside context problem to the Court. If it was possible to place a trap in the soul, then people would have done it, and the only person to have done it was me, entirely on accident.

I saw Rosemallow naked within her soul, so that was something. I was slowly becoming okay with the forced nudity that greeted me on entering souls, because by this point I had seen a lot of them, especially when I’d been trying to clear people of Harold’s influence back in Li’o. It was still really unnecessary.

Soul mages could technically work on memories, it was just hellishly difficult, because there were lots and lots of memories in the average person’s head, and the memories weren’t sorted in any sensible way, they were just linked together haphazardly. There was some organization to them, in the form of links, but it absolutely sucked, which was either by design, or as a reflection of how people actually remembered things. People were terrible about putting events in their proper orders, about when and where things had happened, and I vaguely recalled that a lot of memory was backfilled, your mind storing a few key details which were then filled in when you played a memory back.

If you were a soul mage, it would take a really long time to comb through and find what you needed. And because you needed to be in soul trance the whole time, it would only work if you had either a willing subject or someone who was really firmly your captive. And if you had both those things, why wouldn’t you just soulfuck them and have them tell you what you wanted to know directly?

Rosemallow probably thought that she could bank on me checking out other bits of her soul, then reporting back. She’d seen me do the impossible in the arena, but she also knew that it had taken a significant amount of prep time, and I was fairly sure that the reports she’d gotten from other encounters, including the one with the Cannibal, painted me in a far less godly light.

I found the name of Amaryllis’ mother, Magnolia, in Rosemallow’s soul, then switched to the spirit view, which showed threads that led back down to the soul. That was one half of my comparative advantage: I could at least narrow down the memories a little bit. But as I watched, Amaryllis was helping with the other part of my comparative advantage: I could see which of those threads were in use. And that was going to lead me to the truth.

“Tell me about your mother,” I said to Amaryllis. We were in the bottle together, sitting at the large table, not more than a few days after things with Larkspur had concluded (with his death). Amaryllis was making notes, lots of notes, as she was wont to do.

“What about her?” asked Amaryllis, looking up at me.

“I don’t know,” I said. “You have all my biographical details, and I don’t have yours. And if she was poisoned, as you said, then maybe it’s a quest.”

“A quest to find my mother’s killer?” asked Amaryllis, arching an eyebrow. “All set up in advance?”

“It’s a mystery, right?” I asked.

“It’s unknown,” replied Amaryllis. “That doesn’t mean that it’s a mystery. And — you’ll think that this sounds cold.”

“Go ahead,” I said.

“We had a complicated relationship,” said Amaryllis. “She was doing her best to prepare me for what Court could be like, but her marriage to my father had been mercenary, as had my birth. I must have spent about a month of my time at Quills and Blood trying to find out what effect that had on a child, whether that was something that might have made me different from my peers. There were too many confounders though. Usually when there was an unwanted pregnancy, or an unwanted child, it was because of a failure of prophylaxis, or simple negligence. I wasn’t exactly unwanted, but I think it’s safe to say that if there weren’t firm material incentives, my parents never would have married, never would have had sex, and I wouldn’t have been born.” She set the pen she’d been holding down. “It’s supposed to be the case that in an arranged marriage, the participants eventually fall in love with each other. A love can grow, that’s what we’re taught. I imagine that the same theory applies to children.”

“So when your mother died … you didn’t care?” I asked.

“I cared,” said Amaryllis. “But I cared because I thought that I might be next. I was worried about my future, who would take care of my estate for me, or if this was some attempt to take control of the vast wealth that had once been my father’s. It wasn’t entirely clear whether or not she’d actually been poisoned, and it took some time for there to be a final report. There was just never that enormous sense of loss that some people report feeling. Life wasn’t so different under the care of my relatives.” She shrugged. “Like I said, I know it sounds cold.”

“No,” I said. “I understand. I have my own complicated relationship with my parents, as you know. The happy times were few and far between. If one of them died … I don’t know. I’m not going to say I wouldn’t be sad, but yeah, I would probably be thinking more about the impact on my life.” I wasn’t sure how true that was. It felt true, at the time I was saying it.

“No quest?” asked Amaryllis.

“No, no quest,” I said. “But as far as getting a quest goes, ‘I wasn’t hugely impacted by my mother’s death because things were complicated’ isn’t really the kind of thing that you can hang much of a narrative hat on.”

It still took me some time, even with Amaryllis doing her best on the outside. I hit a few false starts that didn’t make too much sense to me, scenes of Rosemallow with Magnolia, usually brief snippets. I knew at least some of the family history from Amaryllis, including a few details about the poisoning, which we’d naturally talked about. Amaryllis was blasé about her mother’s death in a way that weirded me out a bit, but was still sort of understandable. That it was a poisoning wasn’t entirely conclusive, otherwise there would have been a deeper investigation, but when a healthy thirty-two-year-old with a fair amount of influence and power died, you had to be fairly suspicious.

I got my first look at Magnolia. She was a Penndraig, through and through, with that same imperious look that most of them had, and the same red hair. She was quite pretty, but far less than Amaryllis was, and in a way I found somewhat generic. I wouldn’t have described her as stiff, necessarily, but she was definitely controlled and composed. The memory was of them talking about Amaryllis and her future, and I was mildly surprised to briefly see Amaryllis herself, not much more than seven years old, dressed up like a doll and sitting for a painting.

“Quills and Blood would do her good,” said Rosemallow.

“It would mean taking time away from the Court,” replied Magnolia. She had a surprisingly high voice, almost so high that I suspected it was affected. “I’ve been maintaining three council positions for some time now, and with some success, I must say.”

“It wouldn’t be necessary for you to relocate,” replied Rosemallow. “And even if that were necessary, there are always options for attending council sessions remotely.”

“We both know that decisions within the Court are rarely made through council sessions,” replied Magnolia. “I would lose the power that I’ve spent these long years accruing. If Amaryllis were to attend Quills and Blood, it would mean leaving her in the hands of someone else, even with regular visits on my part. And there’s nothing of use she would learn at Quills and Blood that she couldn’t learn here.”

“Blood magic?” asked Rosemallow.

“Of use, I said,” replied Magnolia.

And that was essentially it for that memory. There was a weirdness to seeing the memories, because they weren’t like videos that I was putting in and playing, they were living things, with certain details of a scene obviously filled in so that it wouldn’t be incomplete, and various lines that I’d heard were a little wobbly, the wording not precise, giving the feeling that listening a second time might change what was said, if not actually changing anything of substance. Beyond that, there were other things to consider, like the fact that this was what Rosemallow had taken away from this single moment in time, and how it would have been colored by her perception of what had happened. Maybe that accounted for some of the bitchiness I’d sensed from Magnolia, and the way Rosemallow came off as only offering up a reasonable suggestion.

I went through another three like that, disagreements between Rosemallow and Magnolia, two of them about how Amaryllis was to be raised and who her prospective marriages would be, and another one that was longer than the others about how procurement was handled by the various departments that the Court oversaw, though the actual discussion had too much nuance and too much required background for me to really follow.

Eventually though, I hit paydirt.

“I have the specifics of the entad here,” said Rosemallow. She was in the White Room, with a man I didn’t know, older and dressed down, and maybe it was the glasses, but I was assuming he was an academic. “Better that it looks like an unfortunate accident, but if that can’t be helped, then it can’t be helped.”

“Timeline?” he asked, looking over the list.

“There’s no particular hurry,” replied Rosemallow. “A wait of weeks or even months would be perfectly fine.”

“And is this a precaution or something you plan to use right away?” he asked.

“Hrm,” replied Rosemallow, sniffing slightly. “I don’t think I’ll say.”

“It matters,” he replied. “Just like vital statistics matter. Height and weight are good numbers to have, in my business, as are diet and habits. But potency falls off with time, so knowing whether the solution can be one with a window of a few days, or if it needs to be shelf stable, that’s a different matter entirely.”

“Very well,” replied Rosemallow. “Right away then. I assume that offers a better chance of success, as you’ll have a wider range of options to use.”

“I will,” he replied. “Nothing else you can give me?”

Rosemallow considered this, and I wasn’t privy to her exact thoughts, just a vague weighing of possibilities and what could be said to this man. To order a poison was one thing, but to say who it was to be used on was another. Deniability was the name of the game.

“She suffered a clot ten years ago, shortly after her child was born,” Rosemallow finally said. “She has spoken with a few doctors about it, for fear of another. If it were possible to work around her entad and create such an effect, that would ensure that fewer questions are asked.”

“And if I can’t?” asked the man. “Should we talk again?”

“Better we make these visits infrequent,” replied Rosemallow. “If you cannot, then you cannot, so long as I know what to expect.”

And that was it, a single conversation, but as much as I needed. In a court of law back on Earth, this would probably have been circumstantial evidence, but we weren’t on Earth, and we weren’t even an informal court of law.

“She did it,” I said as I came out of the soul trance. “She poisoned your mother.”

Rosemallow turned to look at me. “And by what means did you come to that conclusion?” she asked.

“Fuck off,” I replied.

“Why did you do it?” Amaryllis asked Rosemallow. “I have my own thoughts on motive, but I want to hear directly from you. If there’s even a whiff of a lie, I’ll have Juniper look deeper to see if he can get to the truth.” She didn’t threaten a soulfuck, but I had to imagine that Rosemallow could see which way things were trending.

Rosemallow looked between the two of us, her face frozen, not a single muscle moving. “We had different ideas on the direction of the kingdom,” said Rosemallow. “She had become a power in her own right and threatened to upturn a lifetime of my work. In a teenager, a rebellious phase is to be expected, but from a woman in her thirties, it’s a sign of something more serious, a fundamental disagreement in how the game should be played. Given another five years, I would have been sidelined, and it would have been virtually guaranteed that Phlox and Onion would have won.”

“Won,” said Amaryllis. “Amassed power for themselves.”

“They would have implemented their policies,” Rosemallow replied. “They would have secured a position in perpetuity. It would have been unrecoverable.”

“You talk about that like it matters,” replied Amaryllis. “As though there were any policy you wouldn’t budge on, any tenet of faith that represented a line that could not be crossed. As though you even had a coherent memeplex.”

“There are classified matters,” said Rosemallow, and I rolled my eyes. “Everything that I have done has been in service of the future of the Court, the kingdom, and the Empire, in that order. I could wax rhapsodic about the values that we shared, but it was never a question of that, it was a question of approach. Amaryllis,” she took a breath, “You’ve seen the numbers. You were there at Li’o. How much longer do we have until civilization breaks down? Every exclusion brings an economic depression. Millions of hours of education and research are wiped away. We can put ourselves in a position to weather these calamities, but you have to look at the end game. It’s what we’ve been preparing for, all of us in the know.”

“But not me,” said Amaryllis. “I was never in the know.”

“You were seventeen, and showing signs of rebellion,” said Rosemallow. “I couldn’t predict how you would react to some of what we’ve kept secret. Listen, there is a magical library, one known only to the Second Empire, its knowledge long forgotten, and written there is every book that ever has or ever will be published. The librarians change the future, thread the needle, and just barely see us through to a timeline where —”

“We know about the Library,” I said to Rosemallow. “I’ve been there.” More plot hooks from the Dungeon Master, in case we had elected not to bring the Library to us. It did make me a bit hopeful, seeing things like that, because it meant that we really were plowing through the main quest. Eventually all that would be left would be a set of clues pointing us in the same direction, and I was confident that direction would be Fel Seed.

Rosemallow stared at me.

“So what I think,” I turned to Amaryllis, “If I may?”

She waved a hand. She looked faintly disgusted with the whole thing.

“I think you had your justification planned out from the moment that you did it,” I said. “Anyone that you’ve poisoned, it’s been with some calculation about who might find out, or who might guess, and what they’ll need to be told. There are enough entads floating around that maybe one of them would fuck you, hells, that’s happened to me.” I waited for her to chastise me about swearing, but she didn’t. Maybe she knew that her life was on the line. “So whenever you did this kind of thing that you apparently regularly do, you try to minimize fallout, not just in terms of infosec, but in terms of planning things out, which is just good sense. But you didn’t update your spiel enough, or you don’t understand who or what you’re dealing with.”

“The question is whether we can still work with you,” said Amaryllis. “Knowing what we know about who you are and how you operate, what should we do?”

“Phlox is gone,” said Rosemallow. “Even if they find some way to recover her, she’s lost too many allies. Someone needs to steer the ship. Do you really think, at age seventeen, that person is you?”

Amaryllis looked to me, then back at Rosemallow. “It would be expedient for you to remain the de facto leader of Anglecynn,” said Amaryllis. “That would allow continuity of governance, and I’m sure that you have plans ready to go that I would find agreeable, now that the opposition has been crippled or killed. Beyond that, there are all the classified documents and information that you have access to and I do not, whatever shapes those end-of-the-world plans might take. The kingdom of Anglecynn is in a delicate place right now. Institutional memory has just been badly damaged, and I would be very surprised if continuity preparations had been adequate to this level of turnover.”

“Are you serious?” I asked, looking at Amaryllis. “You’re thinking about letting her get away with this?”

“I’m thinking about it, yes,” said Amaryllis. “Unless you’re under time pressure, it always pays to think about your options, repugnant as they might be.”

Rosemallow sat in silence, waiting while Amaryllis thought. Perhaps she thought she’d made her case, or maybe she thought that anything more she added would damage the arguments she’d made, even if just by the fact that Amaryllis disliked her. She was waiting to see her fate.

I really did believe that the Anglecynn thing was Amaryllis’ call to make, but the idea that she would decide on sparing Rosemallow left a sour taste in my mouth. I didn’t necessarily want to kill Rosemallow, but I thought (and maybe hoped) it would be what Amaryllis decided on. Other options included soulfucking her, though I didn’t know what the endgame was there, or maybe even putting her on trial. But to say ‘oh, you killed my mother, I guess that’s just how life is, you’re useful, we’re busy, you can stay’ … I wasn’t sure that I could stomach that. If Amaryllis decided that was what she wanted, I would think less of her, if only momentarily, whatever the object-level arguments were. I’d get past it, I was sure, but it would be a bitter pill to swallow.

“It’s going to be a blow,” said Amaryllis. “But we can’t have you be a part of this kingdom anymore.” I gave a sigh of relief.

“And what do you suggest as a remedy to this predicament?” asked Rosemallow. Her voice was calm, her eyes piercing, and I was really fucking worried about what kind of weapon she might pull out if it looked like we were going to go for her throat. Rosemallow didn’t seem like the kind of woman that we would want to back into a corner, and we really did seem to be backing her into a corner.

“There are options,” said Amaryllis. “You could step down, citing health concerns. We would certainly let you leave your current position gracefully, and allow you to act as both an advisor and to oversee the transition of power. There hasn’t been a full accounting of the dead yet, but I know for certain that a number of council members died.”

“You would push me to the side like that?” asked Rosemallow. “After everything that I’ve done for you? After the work I put into positioning you? Amaryllis, we’re talking about people who tried to outright murder you. We’re talking about a Second Grand Reconciliation, equality between the classes.”

“Will you agree to my terms?” asked Amaryllis. “You have some inkling what Juniper is, if not Uther reborn, then something like him. He proved that, to everyone, in ways that would be impossible to fake. And hopefully you’ve realized that where Uther had his Knights, Juniper has his own motley crew, myself included.”

“You’re threatening me,” said Rosemallow, frowning slightly.

“Yes,” replied Amaryllis. “There’s been enough deaths in the past few days. I don’t want to add one more.”

I turned to Amaryllis. I don’t think we can trust her, I signed, raising an eyebrow. She won’t go gentle, and if it looks like she will, that’s because she’s playing us.

“These private conversations are tiresome,” said Rosemallow. “What is he suggesting?”

“He’s questioning my lenience,” replied Amaryllis. “He thinks you’ll stab us in the back at the first chance you get, or if not, that you’ll be an imperfect ally, the kind who needs constant attention to make sure that everything is going according to plan.”

“I haven’t even agreed to the terms,” said Rosemallow. “You’d be cutting my political life short.”

“Well, you did murder a few people in cold blood,” I said.

“I won’t beg for my life,” said Rosemallow, keeping her attention on Amaryllis. “You know that it would be motivated. All I can do is inform you of facts you already know. I’m a keystone member of the Court. I have manifold relationships, both within the Court, with individuals in businesses and associations, and through the various companies that I own. I won’t claim to be irreplaceable, only difficult and costly to replace.”

“The offer on the table is that you step down,” said Amaryllis. “Carefully craft a message stating that you have health concerns, that you’ll be seeking medical treatment from the best and brightest, and that you’re putting plans in place for a transition of power. It’s coming at a bad time, you recognize that, but you don’t trust your decision-making abilities anymore, and this is coming on advice of your doctors. After that, you let me in on every classified secret you know, working through legal channels, and not including those that would be a detriment to know. You take your marching orders from me.”

Rosemallow sat and thought about that for what seemed like a long time. It wasn’t an obviously good deal for her, but it still seemed generous to me. The whole fucking thing with the Cannibal … well, you could say that was Hyacinth’s fault, and I would have to agree with that, but it was Rosemallow who brought her to the brink.

“No,” she said. “I decline. I’ll stay on as a senior member of my councils, where I’m best positioned to help you. You may place some restrictions on what actions I take, but I simply refuse to take ‘marching orders’. I could, of course, lie, but that would only postpone the argument to a later date. Better to force it now, I think. You need me, Amaryllis.”

Amaryllis nodded, raised her hand, and in what seemed like one swift motion, called forth the flickerblade and materialized its blade right through Rosemallow’s head.

“We’ll store the body inside Sable,” said Amaryllis.

“Shit,” I said, staring at Rosemallow, who was unmoving, her eyes unfocused.

“There’s a good chance that’s not the real her,” said Amaryllis. “Or even if it is, there’s a good chance that her duplicate is out there. She didn’t give us a full explanation of the entad she used on me.”

“Pretty drastic action to take,” I said, still staring at the body.

“She was and is dangerous,” said Amaryllis. “We’ll have to worry about dead man’s switches for months. She would have had contingencies.” She looked over at me. “Hold the sword, please, I need to touch her to get her in the glove.” She gestured with her shoulder to indicate that this procedure wasn’t something that could be done with only one arm.

“Right,” I replied. “Sorry.” I helped her with it, and she put Rosemallow into Sable, the flickerblade still embedded. Not a single drop of blood had been spilled. “Do you really think soul magic would have worked on her, if she’d been the dupe?”

“We’ll bottle her,” replied Amaryllis. “It’s possible that was really her, but bottling will let us know for sure. Still,” she paused, “Either way.”

“Either way what?” I asked. “It was necessary?”

“Are you going to moralize at me?” asked Amaryllis, without any malice, only curiosity.

“No,” I replied. “Just … it’s drastic. Irreversible. And I know she was, maybe not a mother, but —”

“She killed my mother,” said Amaryllis. She stood up and looked around the room for a moment. “Come on, we need to get going. I don’t want to be in this house anymore. There could be booby traps. And if she’s still alive, she’ll soon find out that we killed her double.”

“What’s the story?” I asked. “You can’t say that you killed her.”

Amaryllis sighed. “We’ll go back to Greychapel,” she said. “Mutilate the body and plant it there. There are a number of staff that will attest to her being here, but she has that duplication entad, so … I don’t know. Fear and uncertainty mean that it’s easier to get away with, and we have political capital to burn.” She had a far-off look in her eyes. “Come on, let’s get moving.”

The next hour was a blur, and there was nothing much to say about it but that it was certainly grisly, especially since we were doing it while missing limbs. By unspoken agreement, we went through it all together, just the two of us, husband and wife. We wouldn’t know whether or not we’d succeeded for weeks, except that when we got to the Hotel and trekked up to our room:

Quest Completed: Full Court Press - Amaryllis has returned to Anglecynn, and taken her place as the de facto leader of a new faction, a role which will require a fair bit of her time and attention, in addition to her duties as advisor to the Republic of Miunun and her role as your companion. Being pulled in three directions will test her capabilities, unless you can find some solution (wink). In time, she’ll find herself happy with the way things went, especially with you beside her, helping to secure her rule. (Companion Quest)

Companion Passive Unlocked: Multitasker (Amaryllis)

Multitasker: Amaryllis can split herself into multiple independent clones, with each clone taking eight hours to create, though this takes no real effort on her part. Clones can also be recalled (with or without merge) from any distance with another eight hours each. Given ten minutes of concentration, Amaryllis can integrate with a clone, either merging her essence into a clone, merging a clone’s essence into herself, or doing a bidirectional update. If any clone dies, all clones die. If Amaryllis dies, all clones die. Clones cannot do magic or use entads. Clones automatically roll 0 with a total modifier of 0 for any combat roll. No more than thirty clones at a time can be created in this way.

“Holy shit,” I said, reading it over a few times.

“Yeah,” replied Amaryllis. “I just got a thing,” she tapped her head.

“I figured you would be happier,” I said. “It’s good.”

“It feels like the kind of present you give someone when you know you’ve done something wrong,” said Amaryllis. “It’s the flowers that a husband gives to his wife after giving her a black eye.”

“It’s still good,” I said.

“Oh, it is,” said Amaryllis, nodding. She stayed silent though, with that same far away look. “How much do you think was premeditated?”

“By the Dungeon Master?” I asked. I was a bit flabbergasted that her mind wasn’t on the shiny new toy. Thirty of her, and though they would take eight hours to make, time chambers could be rented, especially if they didn’t need to be large, especially if they were short term.

“Yes,” said Amaryllis. “By the Dungeon Master.”

“It’s hard to say,” I replied. “It’s really hard to say if you need empirical backing, but it’s still hard to say even if you’re asking me to go with my gut. My gut is uncertain. If it’s tabletop gaming rules, and the Dungeon Master isn’t being a cheat and looking into the future too much, then my guess is that things went off the rails from the word go. You plan for things to go off the rails, you make sure that there are other backup rails in place, just in case, and if that’s not where the party lands, you improvise, laying new track, cannibalizing parts of the planning you’ve done, but … I don’t know if that applies. If you’re asking how much it was preordained that we would be in that room with Rosemallow, I don’t know that either. But even if it was set up, I do think it was a real choice.”

“A choice between having a dagger pointed at our back or killing her?” asked Amaryllis.

“I don’t know,” I said. “Yeah, I guess? Are you trying to say that it wasn’t hard?”

“It was, but it shouldn’t have been,” said Amaryllis.

“Because you cared about her?” I asked.

“No,” replied Amaryllis. “Because it feels like there’s some possible world out there where she would have been the person that I wanted her to be. This isn’t the life I feel like I deserved, as arrogant as that might be.”

“It’s not the life you deserve,” I agreed. “But that’s why we have each other, right? To close this chapter of your life and write a new one, together.”

Loyalty Increased: Amaryllis lvl 25!

I had an agreement with Amaryllis to tell her about her loyalty ups, but had negotiated some leeway as to when I told her, just so as to not ruin the mood. She hadn’t wanted to agree to that, but then I’d pointed out that if a loyalty up didn’t happen, it might ruin the narrative moment, which would lead to it being fudged.

“I’m glad it was you,” said Amaryllis. Her voice was soft. She was in her full armor, laying on the bed, but neither of us were planning to sleep for the rest of our lives so long as the tuung were ready and willing to take sleep off our hands.

“That you got married to?” I asked.

“No,” said Amaryllis. “If there had to be someone from Earth that had their fantasies made into a concrete reality, and if I had to be born into that world, and get to know them, then I’m glad that person was you. But also yes, if I was going to get married, I’m glad it was to you.”

“Thanks,” I replied. And if someone had to be created for me, then I’m glad that of all the possible entities that could be created, it was you. “Sorry you’re in a funk.”

“‘This too shall pass’,” said Amaryllis. The Bible stuff made me uncomfortable, and I felt like there had been more of it lately. “And hey, I have clones now.”

I gave her a smile. “Alright,” I said. “The quest is done. I say we convert one of these rooms into a place where we can have a movie night. Skeleton crew to guard, something light and comfortable to watch, and whatever concessions we have left in Sable.”

“Sounds good,” said Amaryllis, smiling back at me. “You know, we really should write some vows. Cheering me up when I’m down sounds like prime material. For the marriage inspector, naturally.”

“Of course,” I said, though we both knew that at this stage it would be nearly impossible for us to get called on the sham by anyone in the kingdom of Anglecynn.

It was nice to have a new normal between us. It was only a shame that we were going to have to ruin a good thing by facing down monsters.

END BOOK VIII

Notes II

Reimer’s Notes: The Optimal Build

There is no optimal build. Every build has trade-offs and compromises in it. Some fare better in the general cases than others (an optimal fighter, for example), or fare better in niche cases that are common enough that it’s worth throwing away everything else for it (stealth focus, for example). If we’re just talking about strictly better builds, where build X is worse in every respect than build Y except in incredibly contrived circumstances, those are so uncommon that they’re not really worth talking about, even if they’re more deserving of the title ‘optimal’. So you can’t have an optimal build, you can only rely on predictions about what the world is or will be like, and gear your character toward that, using everything you know. That’s what we mean by optimal.

In my humble opinion, this is a better approach than building your character because you thought that certain things might be neat.

The big differences between the game system as it exists for Juniper and the game system as we played it are the skills. We would increase our ranks in skills at the end of a session, based on how much we used them and what we accomplished with them, with some filing down of the obvious exploits over time. That meant that there were limits to how high you could push your skills, because you could only get them as high as you had chances to in the course of sessions. Being a multimage with two or three magics was fine, but once you got to even as few as four, you really started to hit a wall, because they were sharing session time. If a session had eight obstacles, then four characters would each get two opportunities to use their skills, and though I made those numbers up, you get the point. A little of that applies here, but not that much, because ‘session time’ is so much longer, relatively speaking, in the real world.

This thing is so cool. Before joining this group, I never really had much experience with entads. How does it work?

Oh, shit, it does, can I erase that somehow?

Okay, well I don’t really want to erase all of that, I thought it was good the first time. Those are some solid opening paragraphs. Why isn’t there an erase function on it?

Yes, obviously I know how entads are made, it’s just —

Fine, we’ll just take some scissors and cut out the conversation, I guess, if you think that’s workable.

Yeah, I can be the one to actually do it.

Okay, yes, fine, we probably didn’t need a preamble, that’s just how they taught us to do it in school.

I think we’re in agreement about doing a MEN-centered build from here on out, which mostly means MEN-based magic. The question is which magics should be the focus of concerted effort, especially at the higher levels, where skills increase more slowly, and a session time metric might become more relevant. For that, there are a few things that we need to consider, like which roles various magics fill, making sure that there’s no redundancy or overlap, what virtues we can pick up and when, and where the magics actually have some implicit or explicit synergy.

Still magic is the best magic in the game. As soon as you’re even a middling still mage, you can stop about ninety-five percent of attacks, and that means that whatever else you are, you can wade into melee without really having to worry about the mooks.

No, how is it offensive?

Well, yes, but I’m not saying it to one, I’m just saying it in reference to the concept. A mook has nothing to do with a species, race, or ethnicity aside from etymology, it just means someone weak who exists only to get taken out right before the boss.

It’s just the two of us.

Yes, if we’re ever with members of the court together, I’ll watch my tongue.

Oh, right, we’re going to have to cut that out too. Dang.

Still magic doesn’t fully solve the problem of defense, but it’s so widely applicable that picking up another defensive magic would be a fool’s errand. That leaves two primary roles for us to worry about, offense and utility.

Here’s where we get to rune magic, which is legitimately one of the best magics in the game, because it’s got everything. If someone is attacking you, you can be set up to absorb, convert, or redirect that energy, so that’s defense sorted. If you need to hit someone, whether at range or in melee, all you need to do is empty the energy tanks and fire on them, with custom solutions to custom problems. A runerifle with a mass driving module is pretty much strictly better to all but the top tier entad rifles, and ammo is easier to sort and swap, in case you need cold iron, silver, or some other specific counter. Lasers are also a perennial favorite, but slightly redundant with gem magic (and a good argument for not taking gem magic). In melee, it's usually hard to beat an entad sword, but rune magic can do it some of the time, depending on circumstances, burning through energy stores on hit for extra damage, whether that's kinetic, electric, heat, or something more exotic. All of it can be swappable, so you're not stuck with one or the other, and it all gets even better if you have some way to regenerate that energy in the midst of combat. As far as utility, there’s nothing with the breadth and power of rune magic.

Now, there are two big drawbacks to rune magic. The first is that you need access to a runeforge, and I’ll cop to that being a bigger problem for you than it ever was in our games. Still, it seems like something doable for royalty, or with enough money thrown at it, which means that the bigger issue might be the periodic travel time to and from the runeforge. That seems like it’s another thing that money can solve. The second problem is the time and materials needed, with the former being more of a problem than the latter. And the third problem is that you need to have at least a little knowledge about what kinds of situations you’re going to find yourself in, because your runegear should be aligned with the adventure, and if it’s not, that’s where you run into a lot of downsides.

You know every time you stop me, that’s more that I’m going to have to cut out?

Yes, I did notice, but I thought of a third thing when I was halfway through.

No, I’m not going to redo it, it’s just Amaryllis.

I like to think that I’ve gotten pretty far by treating her as just a person.

Things that apply to Amaryllis don’t apply to everyone else? Wow, that’s a shocker. Who would have thought? Do you have any other polished gems of wisdom for me?

Well, because I like you. It would be weird if I treated you like a princess. I don’t think you’d like it.

Yeah, I know, but we can come back to it, can’t we?

Well now I have an incentive to rush, don’t I?

It might not be obvious, but rune magic actually synergizes fairly well with still magic, though I don’t know if that’s the case in the real world.

Right. Okay.

It might not be obvious, but rune magic actually synergizes well with still magic, both in the game and the real world. One of the things that rune mages need to worry about is getting overloaded on energy, especially from environmental conditions, or in circumstances where that excess energy doesn’t have a way to safely dissipate for one reason or another. Kinetic dissipation is one of the primary means of dumping energy, but it can wear out both parts and runes. That’s where still magic comes into play. Rather than using runes or parts to try to dump the energy, you just use still magic instead, and that instantly shores up one of the weaknesses. On top of that, because still magic is so good at defense, the rune mage can focus more on other parts of their setup, meaning that there’s more time and space for offense and utility. And there are fewer risks of equipment failure, though we only rarely used those rules in our games, because they were a pain in the butt to track.

There is a little bit of anti-synergy between the two, since if you’re stopping bullets with still magic, that means you’re not recharging your energy stores, but I’m not sure that I should say that.

I’m just trying to make my case here.

Well I know that the build is done, but I don’t know whether or not they’ve switched to it, and as I was saying before, the build isn’t just the build, it’s a matter of how you actually go about playing the game, because the more you lean on certain skills, the more they level up. That means that if you have a good build but you use it wrong, you end up suboptimal. And even if they’ve switched builds, there’s still a chance to change the build again, if my reading of the rules is valid, so I want to make sure if that’s done without my input, bad choices aren’t made. This is kind of just to get it all on record.

Yeah.

Well, we talked a lot, but I think it’s better to have it all laid out as a single coherent argument. Plus I told her that I would send her anything that I thought of that might be relevant, so that’s kind of like an invitation.

I said ‘kind of’.

If we consider still magic and rune magic to be our top two varieties of magic, then that leaves one or two others as ‘core’ magic, those that should definitely be included on the character sheet and which should be used preferentially in battle, where possible. For your consideration, I submit the third most powerful magic: passion magic. In real life, passion magic is weak, and the refuge of madmen. Passion mages are only really on par with other types of mages through the use of drugs, and those compromise their ability to be effective fighters. So why do I suggest it? First, it’s MEN-based, because when the system was designed, it wasn’t designed with emotion in mind: emotion is for roleplaying, not mechanics. Second, the lowest level virtue for passion magic is garbage, but the upper tiers make up for it, and at the stage Juniper is currently at, he’ll be able to hit a forty pretty soon. Third, passion magic has an extraordinarily broad variety of effects, which means that it’s useful in more circumstances, functioning almost like a handful of magics instead of just one limited one. Fourth, and I’m not sure this applies, you get to pick your expressions for passion magic, which means that they’re more powerful than they are in the real world.

For a fourth magic, which is as many as I recommend at the higher levels given how slowly skills raise, star magic is my pick. It’s absolutely garbage-tier terrible when you start out, but it’s pretty much a linchpin at the higher levels, since it compresses travel time so much, lets you go to a lot of places that it’s really helpful to be able to go to, and has bonus utility in terms of what structures and traps you can build. It’s definitely not a frontline ability, but if you’re taking one for utility, best to take the one that can crack the endgame wide open, and that you can use consistently enough to actually level up.

Well I know that star mages can’t do some of that, but it’s what they could do in the game, and if we’re operating under the assumption that Juniper has something like the modified game rules, or some version of them where the different versions conflict —

Right, because he changed the game all the time, usually between campaigns, and some of those campaigns didn’t last terribly long, so there was churn. There was especially churn when someone took one of the skills and put it into the spotlight, because that was where we found out which ones were busted bad and which ones were busted good. It was all a janky mess though.

Oh come on, how is ‘janky’ bigoted?

Okay, yeah, I get it, when you phrase it like that.

I mean, I guess I would have said it at court, maybe. But so you know, my plan at court is to just sit there with my hands folded and not talk to anyone unless they talk to me first, and when I do talk, I’ll talk like I have a stick up my ass. Mostly I’ll eat canapés.

Canapés? Canapés. Look, the entad says that it’s right both ways.

Well I know that.

Sure, I can say it your way. Canapés.

No, I think your ass is stick free.

So those are our core four magics, as I see them: still, rune, passion, and star. From there, we can start to think about multimagic, the most notable multimagic being the combined power of rune magic and star magic, which are both construction magics and can feed into each other, especially given the amount of energy that a high tier star mage is capable of harnessing. By opening a floating microportal to the plane of fire, for example, you can keep full tanks for your runework, and the tension of an extradimensional space or construction can provide energy all on its own, with runework providing the struts.

Yeah, they can.

Well, it’s a matter of fact, you can look it up.

Probably because they’re so different, but there have been a few people who cross-specialized, and a few more who collaborated, and Juniper was nothing if not a fiend for research. Research and bullshit, anyway, but he was usually pretty honest about which was which, if you pressed him. And yeah, a lot of it was skin deep, like I’m sure the stuff about the crossover between star and rune, but the point isn’t a factual representation of the world, the point is something that’s fun.

Well I know they don’t all synergize, if you want the ‘proper’ synergies you go with the predefined clusters, like the bodily cluster, or the connection cluster, the physics cluster, the creation cluster, or whatever else. But those are all explicit synergies, so you’re doing it for a handful of virtues, and the inherent crossover is sometimes weak. Ink magic and steel magic are both construction cluster, but beyond combo virtues, they don’t overlap and let you, I don’t know, make ink magic structures or something, though that would be cool. If you want to talk about different builds, I mean, we can talk about them, but this is a recommendation for Amaryllis.

Wow we’ve made a mess of this. We agreed on you cutting this all up into something presentable, didn’t we?

Yeah, we’ll finish the rest of it later.

Reimer,

Three notes:

First, it would be better if you and Lisi weren’t seeing each other. We want you tucked away until this is all over, if it ever is, especially now that Juniper is more or less a known quantity. I don’t object to the relationship, but if you’re physically proximate, make sure that you have armed security outside. Ideally, no one should know that you two have anything to do with each other. Certainly don’t include anything about her in your letters.

Second, one of the things that I’m most worried about is cognitive load, which you didn’t touch on at all. It’s one of the biggest weaknesses of Juniper’s current mode of fighting, which requires him to juggle at least three different active magics for him to be at peak performance. I understand that in your games that wasn’t a consideration, but there’s only so much work that a human brain can do, even when significantly augmented. I have some experience trying to do what Juniper does, and he consistently impresses me with how effortlessly he flows between completely disparate fields of magic.

Per your suggested style, rune and passion, especially in combination, are going to require a significant amount of thought put into them in the middle of active combat. When you’re in combat, you don’t want to be thinking, you want to be acting on instinct and following your training.

Third, rune magic has all of the flaws that I repeatedly talked with you about, namely, the requirement for proximity to a runeforge, the time required to make it workable, and the bespoke nature of most of the ‘modules’ you think Juniper should be able to create. Rune mages typically operate within known designs, utilizing work that’s been iterated on and refined over hundreds of years. When you start introducing multimagic, almost all of that goes out the window, especially when considering passion magic, which has different expressions for each emotion and emotional combination. That’s before we even get to what you think he’s going to be able to do with virtues.

There’s nothing for us to grab off the shelf. At best, we could hire rune mages or at least experts in rune magic to make plans for us, but this would require significant amounts of time, and as far as star magic goes, might not even help, given that you would need to have proper knowledge of both fields to make the necessary designs. Beyond that, some of your proposed designs (then and now) were only ever possible within the magic system that Juniper created, not in the real world.

That said, you should rest easy, because I’ve kept it in the build.

I do appreciate the letter, but if you send another, I hope that it doesn’t rehash old conversations. If you’d like to be helpful, then your thoughts on effective ink magic would be appreciated. Alternately, and I hesitate to ask this, if you have any ideas for how to assault Fel Seed, or any of the other exclusions, they might prove beneficial.

In Confidence,
Amaryllis

Juniper’s Notes: Meditations on Ink Magic

Ink magic basically allows you to roll your own entads, and the cooler they are, the more powerful they’re allowed to be. The relationship between entads and inktads (called ‘neks’ colloquially or ‘monads’ if you’re being technical, and inktads only if you’re me) is pretty simple, but the people who study them are really reluctant to say that they’re exactly the same. Entads are created by a forge frenzy, their designs and distribution fait accompli. Inktads spring forth from the mind of the creator, limited by their palette of inks, their internal feeling of creativity, and i-level limitations, among others. The phenomenological similarities have been noted, but don’t really help anyone.

The concept of i-level is just about the only thing that carries over, where an understanding of entad impact factor can help you to understand inktad impact factor, though there are enough differences that using the same term for both is misleading (which is the number one thing that any book on the subject will point out). Limitations are one of the big ones: where it’s fairly common for entads to have renewable charges, limits on when they can be used, limits on who can use them, and quite narrow effects, those aren’t really done with ink magic, since you get basically nothing from it, even if it should theoretically make impact factor lower. From a game balance standpoint, this makes a lot of sense, since inktads are nearly always made for some specific purpose, and building in redundant or inconsequential-in-practice limits would mean increasing the power for no cost. More than that, it would be pretty lame. From the perspective of a naturalist, someone who studies ink magic and tries to make sense of it, it’s a little less clear why i-level works differently, and it’s definitely lacking a clean explanation. The best they’ve come up with is that any gains you make by adding in inconsequential limits are offset by a hit to the nebulous ‘creativity’ of the inktad. Consequential limits to inktads, those that change how they operate, can still give you gains, but they have to be at least a little clever.

Palette took me a bit to understand. The extended metaphor that’s used for ink magic is that of paint, a painter, and their canvas. I’m not going to say that this is outright false, but for me, it was certainly misleading. I’d thought that I would ingest an ink, label it something like ‘extradimensionality’, and then be locked in with that, making a bunch of inktads that had extradimensional effects of one flavor or the other, in combination with the effects of my other inks. To my mind, on hearing about ink magic, it seemed like I might have three inks, one for ‘fire’, one for ‘might’, and one for ‘sight’, mixing and matching them. But that was wrong, and once I found the metaphor that they had been trying to point at with ‘palette’, I realized what it was they actually meant: each paint in the palette was a campaign world, or at least a part of it.

When I was making up entads for my D&D campaigns, I’d always tried my best to keep things in theme, or at least something resembling theme. It was a pretty standard trope that adventurers wore horribly mismatched outfits that were based entirely on the function, rather than form, and that was definitely true on Aerb, but if I made a villain, or a temple of cultists, I didn’t want them to look goofy just because it was logical for them to look goofy because we were using so many different books, I would give them matching outfits and at least some stab at a unifying aesthetic. That aesthetic would transcend their physical appearance and bleed into mechanical functionality.

An example would be a cult of occulum trying to bring back their dead god. They were a species that grew extra arms, legs, eyes, and other extremities or organs, culling what they’d budded until they had the best their body could produce. If the cult was attempting to summon forth a dead god that was once the patron of their species, then their magic items could be based around either the occulum themselves and their habit of budding off new parts or sundering their own redundant limbs. Maybe you would find life-sustaining magics intended to allow limb transfers, maybe you would find ways to link between organisms, maybe make knives that would cauterize and heal as they cut, there were lots of things that you could do with it.

Or if you wanted to focus on summoning a dead god, then you could have a magic item that drew from the past, which, in-world, would be an application of their research (though non-duplicable, unless there was a good story there somewhere). But it wouldn’t just be some backwards-looking aspect, it would be mending that which was broken, or trying to knit together things that had been ruined, or to see the way things had been.

In ink magic terms, those might be two inks in the palette, each of them mapped to a specific ingested ink, the closer the relationship, the better.

Once all that was grokked, the inktads flowed out a lot more easily. There is some power in inks, and it was necessary, once they were ingested, to give them each a coherent symbolic identity, but that didn’t need to be a strict aesthetic or concept, it just needed to be some aspect of a campaign world, a stable base from which to draw out creative magic items. It even made sense why the inks went dull or wore out their welcome: making the first magic item for a temple of cultists was easy, but making the fiftieth was really, really hard, because you were picking high-hanging fruit. Better to move on to other inks so that different conceits could be explored.

I have it easy, as far as ink magic is concerned. Heck, I have it easy where every magic is concerned, but for ink magic, it’s even more of a breeze, because I have an intuitive understanding of what I’m doing when making new items, as well as an understanding of the Rule of Cool, what’s derivative and what’s not, and what kinds of limits are level appropriate. Even if I didn’t have my magical powers, I’m pretty sure that I could have gone into Ink and Ardor as a normal student and been, if not the star pupil, then somewhere near the top of the class. Top ten percent, anyway, unless I was Dunning-Krugering myself.

And I definitely have access to whatever inks I want, not that they matter that much. Inks are basically equivalent to a prompt, or a bit of inspiration, and the symbolic construct that you create for them (the worldbuilding notion) works better if it matches up well with the base ink. The ink having actual magical properties is a necessity, but unlike tattoo magic, where you’re dependent on the inks, for an ink mage, especially a relatively low level one, you can get by with relatively little in the way of cost. My understanding is that inks could limit you but not elevate you. A rank amateur wouldn’t be propelled to grandmaster status by being handed godly inks, but a grandmaster would be hampered by poor quality inks.

(To create some formulas and rules from thin air, you’re capped by either the max i-level of your skill or the i-level of the ink, with the ‘quality’ of symbolic construction in relation to the ink providing a malus on i-level, and then the actual inktad concept and execution further limiting actual i-level, with degradation being a function of skill, i-level, and how well you could map item to campaign.)

At any rate, I was thinking about all this and decided on making my own guide to entads and inktads, which in theory might help to crystalize a workflow.

Superlative entads are the simplest and worst starting place for an entad. I just made up that term right now, but a superlative entad is one that’s better than its mundane counterpart in some way, simply by virtue of physical properties. The canonical example would be a sword that’s sharper than a normal sword. Now, it’s not a bad thing to include that as one element of an entad, but by itself, it tends to be super lame. It’s armor, but harder than normal armor! It’s a telescope, but you can see further! Anyone would want them, obviously, but they’re braindead. I include a fair amount of generically good stuff in here, everything from +1 magic sword to a self-repairing cart. I do have a soft spot for superlative entads that are outside the realm of normal adventuring equipment, like a pillow that’s supernaturally fluffy, but that’s the only real exception.

Problem-solving entads are kind of cousins to the superlatives, and I suppose if I were Arthur, I would probably create some kind of system with two or three axes that could encompass all possibilities, but I’m not going to do that. A problem-solving entad is one that simply solves a problem. The canonical example of this would be a vest you can put on that keeps you from overheating in the desert. It’s useful, and it’s not just increasing the power or utility that an object normally has, but it’s lame. If a character were to go to an entadmonger looking for something to help her cross the desert, and I told the player that there was a vest of not-overheating, I would be ashamed of myself. Better a magical parasol that floats around and blocks the sun from reaching you, or an amulet that makes ice golems, or a brooch that collects and stores heat, or one of a billion other things that don’t simply exist to solve the problem that they’re solving. For D&D, this was often a matter of flavoring: a ring of water breathing just lets a character breathe while underwater, but you can modify it so that there’s some actual mechanism to this, like filling your lungs with oxygen, which then has knock-on effects like also making you better at endurance checks. Ring of filling your lungs with oxygen is way better than the ring of water breathing, not just mechanically for the player, but on a conceptual level.

Combination entads are almost as simple, but much less bad. A combination entad would be one that serves the function of two or more regular mundane items. If a sword spreads light like a torch on command word, that’s a combination entad, because it’s a flashlight combined with a sword. If there’s a sword that can split in two and become two daggers, that’s better than having two daggers or just a sword. Sometimes this ‘two in one’ ability can be a little more cloaked than that, like a sword whose hilt can be extended to make it into a polearm, but that’s borderline and not really the same, because the act of extension might be useful in other ways. Included in this loose category are all manner of item duplication or generation entads, like a quiver that never runs out of arrows, or one that puts a meal in front of you. Generally speaking, I like these, especially at low power levels. In games, they tend to remove a lot of piddling little bookkeeping about rations, ammo, and other equipment, which no one likes. In real life, they either help with some mundane concerns, or with fluidity in combat. Everyone loves a multitool. The weirder you get with it, the better.

Impossible entads are not, contrary to the name, literally impossible, but they do things that you couldn’t replicate using mundane means, and don’t represent simple increases to what’s already there. A telescope that gives you the name of any ship you point it at would be one example, because it’s doing something that a telescope cannot and will not do. My canonical example of an impossible entad would be the flickerblade, whose ability to appear and disappear to great effect makes it quite a bit unlike a sword. The exact nature of this impossibility will, naturally, vary quite a bit, and since you’re going impossible, there’s some temptation to have the entad effect have no relation to form … but I don’t find that very satisfying, unless it’s done sparingly and for effect. This is a broad category that I think you could break down quite a bit more, but the heart of it is that you’re well outside the normal range of function, even if there’s a symbolic path. Thinking about it, most of my favorite entads are this kind of thing. I’ll grudgingly include things like a flaming sword or a returning axe in here, because the reason I don’t like them is how overdone they are. Usually, if I were going to do that kind of thing, it would be with other, more interesting stuff as the focus.

Bugfuck entads are just plain weird, and they’re probably the most difficult to come up with, but also the most rewarding. I guess in this current taxonomy, they’re a subset of impossible entads, but where impossible entads do their thing within the framework of normal use, bugfuck entads will tend to set up scenarios or demand people sit down to first figure them out, and then, exploit them. The flickerblade is relatively straight-forward. Something like — well, like Bethel? That’s an adventure in and of itself. I think the key distinction that I’m driving at here is that bugfuck entads represent a paradigm shift of one kind or another. An entad doorknob that opens up pathways to another world, a magical stone that lays out the physical laws of the universe, or a backpack that lets you grab things from Earth, that’s what I’m talking about. But that’s at the upper end of power, and I don’t think it’s just about power, because Ropey was a bugfuck entad too. I think I’m almost on the edge of being able to produce an inktad that can briefly bring mice back to life, and that’s the kind of thing I consider a bugfuck entad: something that you give to the players, and they’re left scratching their heads, wondering what in the hell they’re going to do with it.

Valencia’s Notes: Infernal Feelings

People say that infernals like suffering, but this isn’t really true. Infernals like feeling good. If you could figure out some way of making them feel good without anyone needing to suffer, they would readily agree and give up on suffering, because the suffering is just a means to an end. If you could rip out the backwards ways that infernal feelings interact with mortal feelings, or reverse them, then you would have good infernals, or at least neutral ones.

Infernals don’t really feel much of anything without mortals around. If I had to make a comparison, I guess I’d say that infernals without humans were suffering from severe depression, with everything muted and gray, but that’s the comparison that infernals make. I’ve had hundreds of infernal memories, but no human ones except my own, so I don’t know how accurate it is. Infernals describe the feeling of being away from mortals as hunger, but I don’t think that’s accurate to how they actually feel it, at least going off their memories. It’s more of a nameless yearning, a desire to feel something instead of nothing, one which causes the aforementioned grayness of their reality.

Most infernals live like this. Infernals outnumber mortals more than two to one, but it’s worse than you’d think from looking at those numbers, because the infernals have a staggeringly high Gini coefficient, even if you’re comparing to highly unequal Aerbian nations like Anglecynn. Some of the warlord infernals have millions of mortals under their control, most of them barely used at all. The hells aren’t only bad for mortals, they’re bad for the majority of infernals as well.

There are many different flavors of emotion, and most infernals get bored with sampling only one of those flavors, though infernals aren’t all the same, and some are what we’d class as fetishists, if they were mortals. Pain usually gives the infernals pleasure, sadness gives them happiness, fear gives them confidence, disgust gives joy, though infernals aren’t all the same and the mapping doesn’t hold for all varieties of infernal. On the flip side, the correlates go the other way, so that a strong, happy, healthy mortal grates on an infernal and makes them feel terrible. If you try to look at those crude analogies, you can get some sense of what life without mortals is like for an infernal. Food tastes like nothing, there is no pleasure or happiness, less motivation or desire … and the major depression thing is a sensible but wrong way to look at that.

So if you’re an infernal who doesn’t have a mortal whose suffering you can use for your own fulfillment, what do you do?

The first and most obvious solution is finding a mortal. Finding an unclaimed mortal is virtually impossible, short of a major soul spill or extreme amounts of luck. Impoverished infernals will cheat, swindle, steal, and attack in an attempt to gain a mortal, and if that doesn’t work, they’ll try more legitimate methods, which largely means labor arrangements with infernal organizations. A lot of people think that the hells are filled with mortal slaves, but infernal servitude of one kind or another is a lot more common. Mortals are valuable, and there are a lot of things that they just can’t do because of the conditions, their lack of magic, and the basic way the hells are structured. So, some infernals are slaves, but others are what some people call wage slaves, chained into existing structures of labor in order to maintain their position within the hierarchy, which in this case means being able to pay for a mortal to use for a few hours when you’re finished with the labor, or sometimes, with the mortal being the payment in and of itself: it varies. For some infernals, the only time they see a mortal is at an arena, parade, or some other situation where the mortal suffering is at a remove.

So if you’re an infernal whose only regular contact with an actual mortal is brief and fleeting, you need to find ways to deal with that. This really gets into infernal psychology, and what in particular twigs that part of them that needs suffering. The short version is that nothing but ‘real’ suffering will do, which is inextricably bound up in the magic that makes infernals tick in the first place. Infernals have been working on the problem for a very long time, probably devoting more effort to it than any group has devoted to anything in all of Aerb’s history, but they’ve come up dry. At best, infernals have coping techniques.

Fiction works well enough that the desperate will pursue it. It can be painful to spend money on a book filled with stories of torture when that same money could just buy some actual torture, but some infernals do it. Plays and the oral tradition are more common, because there’s less of a material cost involved, but there are limits on how much production can go into any mortal-replacement endeavor, because at a certain point, you would just use a mortal instead. The infernals don’t have the equivalent of opera, because it would pale in comparison to just putting a mortal up on stage and torturing them. The infernals do have that, including elaborate plays where the mortals are in the play but not actually acting, but that’s a bit different. For the purposes of infernals, fiction is just about as good as history or hearing about things secondhand, which is another thing that people on Aerb usually get wrong about them. They tend to consume fiction for the same reason that people do: fiction can be optimized to give them what they want.

Infernals have fantasies, but those aren’t replacements, they’re just yearning, sometimes backed by past experiences, sometimes wild imaginings. Sometimes these fantasies become something more, with props, mannequins, magical constructs, or other methods of acting them out. Infernals will occasionally use other infernals for this, inflicting their tortures on each other and pretending that it’s mortal suffering instead, but even with infernals that look more like one of the mortal species, it’s clearly not the real thing. Sometimes this happens by agreement, sometimes it’s just infernal slavery or labor agreements.

Possession is another pastime, much more effective at fulfilling the need for feeling, though reaching up into Aerb and temporarily replacing a person is usually on the expensive side, unless it’s a non-anima, and it doesn’t last terribly long. It can also be unsatisfying, depending on who you get, and reconnaissance or being specific are much, much more expensive. If you’re doing the cheap version, you might possess someone who isn’t around anyone, and infernals don’t get much if anything from hurting their hosts (which is good, because I would be dead if they did). Coordinated and repeated possession is much rarer and done only when an infernal organization has a specific need, or when one of the rich and powerful infernals wants to set up some personal fantasy that they’d like to play out.

You might be tempted to feel bad for the infernals. They’ve been working to figure out a way to live without mortals, not because of any moral intuition or compulsion, but because it would make a lot of practical sense. But the fact remains that they are what they are. And someday, they’ll all be gone.

Amaryllis’ Notes: Standards

Uther Penndraig was a reformer, and as reformers went, he had a number of things working in his favor. He was the absolute ruler of the most powerful individual polity on the hex, he was the de facto leader of the largest political collective, he was arguably the most physically and magically powerful person through all of Aerb’s history, he was beloved and respected by almost everyone, he was the richest person alive, and he had exclusive knowledge from another plane of existence where hundreds of years of reform had already taken place, some of them failing, others succeeding. The world was his to remake as he pleased.

Uther chose not to invent metric. He knew that it existed, and even if he lived in the one country in the whole of Earth that didn’t use it, it still boggles my mind that he wouldn’t have imported it. There are only two things that I can say in his defense. The first is that the imperial system was already in use on Aerb when he got here, in a small handful of countries surrounding Anglecynn, which means that at least he can’t be accused of importing a backwards system of measure here. The second is that certain units are magically significant, and those units are almost always exact integer numbers in the imperial system. Juniper has explained that this was common in tabletop games, for the sake of easy mechanics, and whether or not you took this as abstraction or worldbuilding was up to the DM. I don’t find that to be a particularly good reason to keep imperial, but it’s one of the defenses that I would anticipate Uther giving.

The Second Empire did invent something sufficiently close to metric that I’m willing to call it the same system, but they never mandated that it go into wide use, perhaps because it would have cost quite a bit to do that over the entirety of Aerb, with minimal benefits. Especially early on in the Second Empire, there was the idea that they were going to accelerate into a true utopia for everyone, and I suppose when you think you’re hard on that, putting time and effort into something trivial like making a newer, better standard seems pointless. After the fall of the Second Empire, their systems were largely abandoned, and they taint any current discussion of reform (even something so minor as decimalization).

As a minor and infuriating note, while Aerb units and Earth units all have the same names, they aren’t actually equal to each other. The discrepancies are small, but they add up, and the ratios between imperial units are different because of that. An Aerb mile is roughly the same as an Earth mile, and an Aerb foot is roughly the same as an Earth foot, but there are 5,120 Aerb feet in an Aerb mile. It’s the kind of thing that is mostly inconsequential, unless you’re working from Earth textbooks and schematics to solve novel engineering problems on Aerb, at which point it adds quite a bit of tedious work and double-checking to many steps of the process. And why? Why would the world be arranged this way? Presumably just to test my patience, unless it’s just one of those things that the Dungeon Master would have needed to put in some measurable time or effort to fix, and on the seventh day of creation, he decided to take a nap instead.

Uther did engage in a number of other reforms during his time, the standardization of dates and times being one of them, though this has been a contentious issue for nearly as long as it’s been around. In the beginning, Uther did try to make some concessions to other cultures, with the month and day names being taken from various historical figures from around Aerb, but of course that led to some contentions, as with seven days and twelve months, there was no possible way to keep everyone happy. Still, that’s what we ended up with, and after a few generations, most of the Empire is ignorant of what the old systems were like, outside of a few cultural preservation groups and a small number of special cases where it makes sense to do otherwise.

All months have exactly thirty days, with the extra seven days set aside for a holiday between the end of one year and the start of another. Originally this holiday was meant to be different every year, a celebration of various cultures, but this didn’t prove feasible, and following the collapse of the First Empire, different cultures have done things their own way. Interestingly, Aerb has slightly longer years than Earth, though not enough to make much difference. Similarly, Aerb has slightly longer days than Earth, amounting to roughly three and one seventh Earth minutes a day. You wouldn’t notice if you were transplanted from one world to the other, but for anything precise, it’s a pain.

Months: Sougouw, Abi, Taun, Domai, Yaub, Donsuch, Taunsak, Akkers, Halig, Jeima, Kidou, Machaw

Days: Tethday, Loday, Thrisday, Highday, Twisday, Zeeday, Ahnkday

Three Timelines

April 11th, 1999: Juniper is born
March 14th, 2009: Juniper’s first D&D session
August 13th, 2015: Junior year starts
January 9th, 2016: Juniper and Tiff begin dating
April 11th, 2016: Juniper turns 17
June 9th, 2016: Arthur is involved in a car accident
June 16th, 2016: Arthur dies
August 11th, 2016: Senior year starts
January 12th, 2017: The Fel Seed Incident
March 23rd, 2017: Juniper's last memory on Earth

9 BE: Uther arrives on Aerb
6 BE: The Erstwhile Players hanged
4 BE: Uther takes Avengion from the lake and kills the Dark King
1 BE: Meeting of the Seventeen Swords
0 FE: Uther’s first son born
1 FE: Uther’s second son born
3 FE: Uther’s daughter born
4 FE: Uther defeats the Ice Wizards
5 FE: Uther defeats Apocalypse Demon
7 FE: Uther defeats the Wandering Blight
12 FE: Uther relocates the Athenaeum of Speculation and Scrutiny
14 FE: Uther eradicates the vampires
18 FE: Vervainium founded
20 FE: Infernoscope invented
30 FE: Uther disappears
34 FE: Fel Seed exclusion
81 FE: Internecine Wars
119 FE: Oorang Solace born
176 FE: Second Empire founded
194 FE: Pendleham exclusion
276 FE: Necrolaborem exclusion
324 FE: Second Empire collapses, Manifest exclusion
389 FE: Teleportation keys forged
413 FE: Radio invented
446 FE: Doris Finch exclusion
472 FE: Void beast discovered
494 FE: Fenn born
510 FE: Amaryllis born
519 FE: Risen Lands exclusion
525 FE: Darili Irid accident
527 FE: Juniper arrives on Aerb

Yaub 29th, 527: Juniper arrives on Aerb
Donsuch 1st, 527: Juniper, Amaryllis, and Fenn arrive at Barren Jewel
Donsuch 12th, 527: Caer Laga
Donsuch 16th, 527: Juniper and Fenn return to Barren Jewel
Donsuch 23rd, 527: Isaac Aumann killed
Donsuch 25th, 527: Party kills a unicorn
Donsuch 26th, 527: Larkspur Prentiss killed
Taunsak 4th, 527: Fallatehr Whiteshell killed
Taunsak 14th, 527: Party descends into the Boundless Pit
Taunsak 15th, 527: Republic of Miunun founded
Akkers 18th, 527: Party makes trip to Speculation and Scrutiny
Akkers 19th, 527: Fenn dies
Akkers 23rd, 527: Juniper enters the Infinite Library
Halig 3rd, 527: Juniper leaves the Infinite Library
Halig 4th, 527: Party visits Darili Irid
Halig 5th, 527: Bethel’s marriage
Halig 7th, 527: Party enters Li’o
Halig 10th, 527: Classes start at Sound and Silence
Halig 23rd, 527: Mome Rath
Halig 29th, 527: Dragons visit the Isle of Poran
Jeima 4th, 527: Party arrives in Caledwich
Jeima 7th, 527: Onion Penndraig killed
Jeima 8th, 527: Hyacinth Prentiss killed, Rosemallow Penndraig killed

PHY

8 | 7 POW | 21 One-Handed Weapons | 21 Two-Handed Weapons | 21 Parry | 21 Dodge
7 SPD | 0 Velocity Magic | 21 Unarmored | 21 Unarmed Combat | 21 Thrown Weapons
7 END | 21 Heavy Armor | 21 Athletics | 39 Vibrational Magic | 0 Revision Magic
MEN

15 | 14 CUN | 28 Ink Magic | 22 Air Magic | 0 Rune Magic | 33 Engineering
14 KNO | 24 Analysis | 20 Repair | 20 Logistics | 20 Logic
14 WIS | 27 Rifles | 35 Blood Magic | 42 Still Magic | 0 Plastic Magic
SOC

4 | 3 CHA | 27 Passion Magic | 23 Water Magic | 29 Gem Magic | 0 Fire Magic
5 INS | 0 Tree Magic | 42 Essentialism | 42 Bone Magic | 0 Star Magic
3 POI | 0 Wards | 20 Optics | 20 Research | 20 Mathematics
  | 1 LUK | 34 Alchemy | 4 Language | 42 Spirit | 0 Gold Magic

Second Degree

Juniper,

What the actual fuck?

I tried to think of some other way to start this letter, but I kept asking you that question in my head. If it wasn’t going to be the first line, then it needed to be the second. Some possible first lines, ‘So you married Amaryllis,’ or ‘I hear you killed the head of the Host,’ or ‘You punched a dragon so hard that it fell from the sky onto Greychapel’. I don’t actually believe that last one, and I wouldn’t believe the first two, except that it’s all been printed in the newspapers so much that there must be a little truth.

What the actual fuck?

I got your letter six days ago. I waited half a day before opening it, because I wanted to have a cup of tea and a package of cookies ready, with my favorite songs on cylinder, just in case it was soul-crushing. But it was all so normal, just this assurance that you were alive and well, that you had gone through the trial by adversity unscathed and were in a much better mindset. You were always good at writing letters. I felt so relieved. But I also felt like you were suddenly back in my life somehow. After you went to prison, I sort of made my peace with the topic of you being this thing that I would get sad about sometimes, a wound that would eventually close up until it was just scar tissue.

But you were fine, and it was all okay.

And then I got a letter from Reimer, which said, paraphrasing, that you had been with him in Li’o during the exclusion. It took all my strength not to write the last part of that sentence in capital letters, taking up half the page, because I know you hate when I do that, but it would have been a really appropriate way to express how I felt about it. He hadn’t been sure whether you would send me a letter or not, but he felt like I deserved to know that you were alive and well, except he also mentioned that you were some kind of government official for a foreign government, which you had left out. It really made me think that you weren’t out of trouble at all, you were in some different kind of trouble.

I get the paper from Anglecynn two or three times a week, mostly because I want to be able to send letters to my mom and dad about what’s going on there. On one of those days, I saw your name in the paper, on the front page, making the claim that you were a traveling companion of Amaryllis Penndraig, imprisoned on orders of the Host.

What the fuck?

I put off writing you a letter because it seemed like it was this colossal mistake, or a prank, or maybe just someone who shared your name. I did write a letter to Reimer and sent it express to him, but by the time he got back to me, another day had passed, and the newspapers were saying that you were — Juniper, I can’t even finish that sentence. The stuff they were saying about you in the morning edition was insane, but at least it was within the realm of possibility. The stuff they were saying in the evening edition was … Juniper, you have to know this by now, but they were saying that you were a master of eight magics, that you had personally killed the creature in Li’o, that you were guilty of maybe as many as hundreds of murders, and then to cap it off, you had ended the day by getting married to Amaryllis and THEN ON TOP OF THAT declared a trial by combat.

I’ve been talking to my friends here, and I think they just don’t believe me. I’m sure that there are people coming out of the woodwork to claim that they knew you before you became whatever you are now. I’ve just been sitting in my apartment, trying to work out what the everliving fuck to tell my future self, reading through the newspapers over and over and hounding the newsagent for more.

I didn’t even mention that you killed the head of the Host in a battle that virtually no one believes actually happened. The newspapers all use weasel words. It is ‘alleged’ that you shed your armor and sword and then beat a master blade-bound to death with your bare hands. They say that you regrew an arm without using magic.

And then the next day, there was all this stuff about a gold dragon, dozens of people dead, and apparently, a naked man with incredible powers that you stopped dead in his tracks.

What the actual fuck?

I know that bit probably wore out its welcome the second time, but it’s the only thing that’s been going through my head. I don’t know if I should hold off for another day, to see whether something else happens, but I’m hoping that you can give me some answers, because if you can’t …

This is my lost year. It’s a year that revision mages live through, knowing that they’re going to have it all be undone, with nothing to show for it but the notes that we leave for ourselves and the ways that people treat us differently. I have no idea what to tell myself. I have no idea how much more change there will be in the next few months. They’re saying that you’re dream-skewered, but Reimer was talking about you like you were the same old person, so if you remember me at all, and if you still care for me, even a little, then please reply back. Just help me make sense of it.

Your friend, for what it’s worth,

Tiffany

Tiff,

Yeah, things have been a bit nuts.

Sorry I didn’t send you a letter before the trial, it’s been hectic. And sorry for not including more, especially about Li’o, but I was trying to bring you some closure. Feel free to talk to anyone from the old group, if you think it will help you. If you want, I can help to set up entad support so that it can happen in realtime, or I could pay for travel so that you could meet with them face to face.

I think I have to tell you now that you might be in danger. Anyone who knows that you were my girlfriend might think that they could use you to get to me. We’ll be hiring private security for you, which might come before this letter gets to you. I know that it’s an imposition, and I know that it might not be what you want, but I want to do as much as I can to make sure that you’re not used as leverage over me.

The reason that Reimer talked about me like I was the same person I was in high school is because my dream-skewering situation is complicated. I don’t remember anything about my life on Aerb, but my life on Earth seems to have run in parallel. I don’t remember you, but I remember a different Tiff. We used to sit up on your roof looking at the stars. I remember how nervous I was to tell you that I liked you. And after Arthur died, I was a dick to you and everyone else. I’m sorry. I wish I could undo things. Unfortunately, time travel doesn’t seem to be within my purview.

Almost everything else is though. If you hear more crazy stories about me, you should place at least a little weight on them being true. I really am married to Amaryllis; from what Reimer said, I had a crush on her in this world. I hope that’s not too awkward for you. I need to be careful about what I say in this letter, because I don’t know who might end up reading it, but it would suffice to say that something like what happened with Uther is happening with me. Actually, reading that back, that doesn’t at all suffice, but it’s as much as I can say. Sorry.

I hope you have a good life. I’m doing my best to write you out of my personal story. This will be the last letter I send you until this is all over. If they do come for you … it hurts me to say it, but I won’t save you. That’s the only way to deal with having you there as leverage. I hope that your security will be enough. In the meantime, if money can solve problems for you, we’ll be giving you a million obols. And as I said, we’ll be providing security for you, which I hope will help to keep you safe.

Sorry,

Juniper

The entire Anglecynn adventure had a few pluses and a few minuses, with the good mostly outweighing the bad. I had gained a level, Amaryllis and Grak had new abilities, and we had gotten not just an enormous amount of money, but a fairly wide stock of entads.

The clones were pretty straightforward. We’d spent a day with the first clone, trying to see what they could and couldn’t do. If you pricked them, they bled, but they didn’t have souls or spirits that I could see, though they did have latent magic. In terms of magic and entads, they seemed to follow a rule of least benefit, meaning that they were considered people or objects depending on which would work against them. When you killed one, she popped like a soap bubble (and yes, we had tested killing one, with consent). The plan was to have ten being used in Anglecynn and nineteen used in Poran, keeping them all as safe as possible, with the thirtieth clone kept as backup. While they were pretty much the absolute worst at any form of combat, they were still as durable as Amaryllis, which is to say, you would still have to be trying to kill one in order to actually kill it.

Grak’s ability, Warded, was also fantastic, though it was a really significant contrast, because the clones were primarily supporting and furthering plots that existed outside of adventures. With Warded, Grak became a phenomenal front-line fighter, not just because of his sheer defensive power of being able to stay maximally warded, but because he could barrel through all kinds of defenses. Wards could do nothing against him, he was Wardproof, but one of the first things he’d done was to put up a full entad annihilation ward, with a few select holes poked in it for what he was wearing. Beyond that, he had a velocity ward that would keep anything from hitting him if it was going too fast, and a number of wards that would completely no-sell attempts to harm him in other ways. And beyond that he had an offensive suite that he could turn on with a thought, wards that were fully set up save for the last little bit that would turn them lethal, annihilation wards that would kill or critically injure anyone he touched.

And then there were the entads. Some of them were still under contract, and would be added to our store at a later date, and some of them were relatively garbage or not good outside the context that they were already being used in, but there were so, so many of them, and they were all ours. This was good, because we had lost a huge number of entads during the fight with the Cannibal, including my space plate, Alvion’s Vambrace, the Ring of Upward Bliss, and a handful of others. Beyond that, the probability blade was toast from the fight with Onion, and stubbornly refused to unrust itself, even with special attention from a variety of sources.

The highlights from the haul:

Reflection Blade — A frankly beautiful blade which was covered with intricate designs that had been etched into the metal, depicting scenes of battle at miniscule detail. It was capable of mirroring wounds on anyone it had cut, which meant that a gash on someone’s left would become a second gash on their right. It worked whether I was the one that had made the wound or not.
Elemental Plate — Armor which could be transitioned through twenty-seven different forms, most of which were useless, with each form conferring ‘elemental immunity’ and sometimes giving other benefits. The elemental forms were acid, base, blood, bone, chitin, clay, earth, electricity, fire, flesh, glass, gold, ice, iron, lava, light, magnetism, mist, rust, salt, sand, shadow, smoke, steam, stone, water, and wood. It had no helm to speak of, which was a shame.
Crown of Eyes — A crown, tin, with carved stone eyes inset, which allowed me to see through the eyes of everyone in a fifty foot radius around me, and make sense of it. It wasn’t just good at being able to see more, and it wasn’t just good at knowing ahead of time when someone was around me, it also let me see what other people were paying attention to.
Amulet of Five Spirits — A golden amulet, flat enough to be worn beneath armor, which depicted five animals curled up against one another. The entad power allowed me to change into one of the five stored animals, though it didn’t meld my equipment with it, just cast it off (amulet excepted), meaning that I would be naked on transforming back. The animals within the amulet could be changed by touching an animal for a few minutes, limited to those animals without ‘extra’ magic.
Ring of Moving Winter — A white ring that allowed for the creation of up to two gnome-sized ice golems, plus the ability to cool down things with a touch, very similar to the Icy Devil spell I used to have.
Ring of the Stored Sword — A dark brown ring with green lines that could attune to an item of twenty pounds or less, then store it or unstore it with a thought, almost (but not quite) explicitly meant to be used as a quick and inconspicuous sheath.
Ring of the Focused Mind — A pink ring that reminded me of sea salt, which allowed for the storage of mental energy for later use. Whatever process regenerated mental energy, it would fill the ring when mental energy was full. It was most helpful for gem magic, because it gave me a bigger mana pool.
Ring of the Dragon’s Mouth — A blue ring that gave me a breath weapon, subtype lightning, usable once a day. It was probably one of the most D&D items that was in the bunch, at least in my opinion.
Rilke’s Strap — An embroidered bandolier that had a fairly significant amount of extradimensional space inside it, and whose pockets responded to a thought, pushing up whatever was needed. There were some unfortunate limits on size, meaning that I couldn’t put some of the bigger bones in it, but it was still a major upgrade to that part of my kit. It was thankfully very durable, making it immune to the elemental plate.
The Fourfold Flask — A set of four shot glasses, each of which connected to a set of twenty extradimensional storage tanks. A drink poured into one shot glass could be poured out of the other, and you could have up to twenty different drinks at once. Drink was loosely defined, but the closer to water, the more it could hold. It was useful mostly by virtue of not having a range, meaning that the four glasses could be used to pass messages across the hex: you could roll up a piece of paper and slip it in, which would just barely fit by virtue of not actually being a drink.
Messiah’s Shotgun — A gilded shotgun that amplified the amount of shot by quite a bit, and had a ludicrous amount of spread. The thing that made it good, other than the amount of damage output it had, was that allies were immune to it: the shot would simply miss them.
Perfidy Pistol — A pistol whose rounds would rot away at flesh, with accents of rotted flesh where you would otherwise expect to find wood or ivory. It also had a fairly powerful antimemetic effect: for the first minute that it was drawn, no one would know or acknowledge that it was out, even if someone got shot with it.
Gloves of Adaptation — A metaentad that was really underwhelming, as far as metaentads went. All the gloves did was coordinate with the rest of my outfit, which meant that they would transform with me for the purposes of the shapechanging amulet, and would take on the powers of the elemental plate. Mostly, they protected my hands.

And that was all the stuff that I was going to be kitted out with. The rest of the party took their pick of things as well, including the tuung, who found a few major upgrades to the ink magic that I had been furnishing them with. For those that would be staying in Anglecynn, that was particularly important, given that I wouldn’t be able to keep them supplied without doing a bulk teleport.

But that wasn’t even the end of the story for the entads, because I was a special snowflake, and things worked differently for me. We spent an afternoon working on abusing degrees of reasonableness.

“I think it made more sense in the context of a roleplaying game,” said Amaryllis. “I mean, it’s sensible to have some mechanism for players to argue with their game master about what applies and what doesn’t, and making that into a mechanic is … well, not without precedent, in the rulebooks I’ve read. But transplanted to our circumstances, we can’t actually argue with the arbiter, because he doesn’t respond back.”

“Sure,” I said. “But we could imagine that the Dungeon Master has a good enough model of us to know how such a conversation would play out, and even if he doesn’t, he can just stop time, spin up a copy of us, talk to that copy, then kill the copy once the conversation is concluded.”

“Well that’s horrifying,” said Raven. She was sitting with us in the ballroom, curled up like Maddie used to do, hugging her knees to her chest. We were staying clear of the Erstwhile Manor, which Amaryllis was set to inherit, but there were other properties in Caledwich.

“It’s just library timelines,” I said.

“Those are already horrifying,” said Raven. “Don’t think I’m unaware of how it must feel from the other side.”

“I would not consent to such things,” said Grak.

“Well, either way,” I said. “It doesn’t have to make sense, except in that it’s systematized.” I cracked my knuckles and looked over what we had. “Alright, where do we start?”

“The least rigidly defined are the most susceptible,” said Grak. “Reimer said that defining the letter A as B took five degrees of reasonableness.” I tried to think about what six or seven degrees would look like, and instantly understood: defining A as 1 would be six, and defining A as banana would be seven.

“Okay,” I said, looking things over. I reached down and picked up the Reflection Blade. “But we don’t actually know the wordings on any of these, do we?” I turned to Amaryllis. “We just know what they do by virtue of them having been put through the wringer by your people?”

Amaryllis nodded. “There’s a file for each of these, some thicker than others.”

“But those are kind of worthless, no offense,” I replied. “Since how you make an entad is, you start with a base case, then extrapolate out from there, eventually hitting some corner cases and getting ‘underlying’ laws that aren’t actually underlying at all, they’re just what the Dungeon Master came up with to justify or constrain the base case.” I looked at the blade. “So, Reflection Blade provides a reflection of wounds for someone that you’ve cut. That’s the base. Everything else is mutable.”

“If you say so,” replied Amaryllis.

“I’m doubtful of this conclusion,” said Grak.

“Well, potentially mutable,” I said. “Obviously if the internal wording that I’m assuming entads have, the same internal ‘wording’ that I give when I make inktads,” ink magic entads, I didn’t know why no one had coined it, but I was trying to make it happen, “is something like ‘reflect along the primary axis of symmetry’, then there’s less wiggle room, but if it’s just ‘reflect wounds across an axis of symmetry’, or even only ‘create equal wounds on the other side’, then there’s something to work with.” I looked at the three of them. “Who wants to be cut?”

Amaryllis stepped forward almost before I could finish my sentence.

“Go ahead,” she said.

I very carefully made a cut on the outside of her left forearm, half an inch long and not terribly deep, which she didn’t so much as wince at. I felt a surge of affection for her.

“Alright,” I said. Test number one was to close my eyes and see if I could sense her through the sword, which was harder than it sounded, since there were a few different ways I had of tracking. Unfortunately, it was a bust. I’d been hoping that since the wounds could apply against anyone the sword had cut, I might be able to get some tracking information from it, but that apparently wasn’t reasonable enough. “Okay,” I said. “Sorry, healing’s on the way soon.”

The next step was reflection, but the human body had at least three axes, the primary one, between left and right, which was called the sagittal plane, the second, between top and bottom, which was called the transverse plane, and the final, between front and back, which was called the coronal plane. I was slightly proud of being able to list those off the top of my head, but it might have been my stats doing some background lifting for me.

With a thought, I reflected the wound I’d given Amaryllis across the sagittal plane, giving her a cut on her right to match. Then I reflected it again, giving her four wounds total, two on each arm and two on each leg. And finally, I reflected it a third time, making eight cuts, some of them overlapping each other.

“Ow,” said Amaryllis, quickly healing herself using a bone she had at hand.

“I haven’t tested radial symmetry yet,” I said. “I can give you a bit though.”

“No, it’s fine,” said Amaryllis. “You’ve cut yourself open to put bones inside, I’m not going to be more of a wimp than you, just do it.” She held out her arm, and after a moment’s hesitation, I cut her again. She hadn’t mentioned me screaming when the unicorn bones were put inside, which was nice of her. I was somewhat thankful that we didn’t have any more that were small enough.

Radial symmetry didn’t seem to work though, and my plan for a ring of wounds around my enemies didn’t seem like it was going to happen.

“Try healing,” said Grak, who had been reading the file on the sword.

“Healing?” I asked. “Huh.” I focused on Amaryllis, who was still bleeding a bit, and tried directing the sword to do its mirroring, but in reverse, mapping the uninjured side of her body onto the injured side. To my immense surprise, it worked, and the cut I’d made was instantly closed. I turned to Grak. “How did you know that would work?”

“It’s not only wounds the sword reflects,” said Grak, closing the file. “It was in use by a pustule mage.”

“Good work,” I replied. “I assume healing wasn’t something that it could always do?” Grak shook his head. “Not that I get injured all that often,” I said, swishing the sword around to feel its balance before I placed it back on the ground. I was getting a lot of looks.

“How many times have you died in the last few months?” asked Raven.

I took a moment to consider that question.

“The amount of time it’s taking you to furnish a response should put some fear into you,” she said.

“Look, I don’t think loop deaths count,” I said. “And if you don’t count those, then I haven’t died.”

“How many limbs have you lost?” asked Amaryllis.

“Not counting loops, then … a hand and part of my forearm against Larkspur’s goon, not a whole arm, mind you, though against Larkspur himself — that was only a near amputation, it was still connected … uh, a bit of my leg, technically, against Zinnia, and an arm against Onion,” I said.

“Two fingers in the Datura,” said Amaryllis.

“Plus a leg and most of a hand against the Cannibal,” said Grak.

“Well, he’s a cannibal,” I said. “It’s not his fault, it’s society that failed him.” No one laughed. “I’m not sure what more was expected of me. And we got replacements, didn’t we?”

“We’re low on unicorn bones,” said Amaryllis. She was back in fighting shape, and had been since the day after the whole fiasco, when we’d been able to get the good stuff. One of the things Aerb was really lacking was good prostheses, druidic magic aside, and Solace had flatly refused us, which I thought was both understandable and a bit rude. I kind of got why prostheses were so vanishingly rare. If you had better-than-human prostheses, then everyone would be lopping off their arms and legs to trade up, and that was a particular aesthetic that I almost never went for, even though it was cool. There were too many worldbuilding complications.

Nonetheless, Amaryllis had replaced her eye with one that had a white iris and a piercingly blue sclera, giving her a weird and captivating heterochromia, along with a different sense of color. She’d replaced her arm with one that could feel electromagnetism, and was slightly more pale than her natural arm. Both had been in for long enough that they were imprinted on her soul and fully a part of her, thanks to some time in a rented time chamber, and both were entirely non-magical, which they had to be in order to work with her clones. I was fairly sure that the off-colored eye was a way of growing her legend, and given how bewitching it made her look, I was sure that it was going to work in her favor. I’d opted to keep myself as I was, given how few options there were for upgrades (or even sidegrades), and the uncertainty of how they would interact with leveling up.

“I was really hoping that you’d have a size reduction entad in here somewhere,” I said. “That should be a common enough form of increasing carrying capacity.” What we really needed was one that would make things small but still touchable, and was usable in the middle of combat, which narrowed down the possibilities somewhat.

“It’s not,” said Grak.

“No?” I asked. “Well, maybe I can do it with ink magic. But I always hated trying to come up with some fresh new take on the portable hole.”

“Have you considered your desire for variants might be the reason that the one specific one we need is rare?” he asked.

“Makes sense,” I shrugged. We’d seen a fair few storage entads, and heard about more, but very few that met the requirement that I wanted. The closest was the storage entad that Masters had, which shrunk things down so they could be put into a box, but it was awkward to carry around and you just keep the minis out of it.

We spent some time going through the rest of them, testing whether I could get away with being a little less than perfectly reasonable. For the most part, I couldn’t, or if I could, the boundaries would only shift a tiny bit. The biggest boon by far was the Amulet of Five Spirits, which normally only allowed the acquisition of non-magical animals.

“Humans are animals,” I said. “Sorry, that’s just a matter of fact.”

“The mortal species possess an anima exa,” said Grak. “Animals do not.”

“Well,” I said. “Sure. But that’s not necessarily the definition, is it?”

“It is, yes,” said Amaryllis. “There’s a fairly clear dividing line.”

“But they still have souls,” I said. “I mean, maybe you can’t take their soul out of their body, but they still have a soul, because otherwise bone magic wouldn’t work.”

“Just test it then,” said Amaryllis, folding her arms. “Maybe it will work, but it doesn’t seem reasonable to me.”

“How many degrees would you say it should take?” I asked. “Remember that five is enough to redefine a two into a three. And remember that some alternate version of myself built this system.”

“I didn’t say that it wouldn’t work,” said Amaryllis. “Just that it didn’t seem reasonable to me. There’s no point in arguing when we can just test it.” I could tell she was a little annoyed though, mostly because she was making no effort to hide it. I understood it: the rules were different for me, not for her, and her clones couldn’t use entads at all, which meant that she was going to be living roughly 97% of her time with some fairly severe handicaps.

“Grak?” I asked.

He held out an arm for me, but paused. “Why me?”

“From the file, people turn into their own personal animal equivalents,” I said. “You acquire a cat, you turn into the same cat every time, but not the same cat you acquired, just cat-you. If you hand the amulet over to someone, they can turn into a cat, the same cat every time, but it’s a different cat from the cat you turn into. So if I acquired a human, meaning Amaryllis, I probably wouldn’t turn into Amaryllis, I would probably turn into a different human, if I changed at all, because human-me is just me. And if I turned into an Ell … well, I’m not sure whether or how Ell biology works if they don’t have their magic, or whether that would interfere, because it seems like it would add on an extra DOR, if not more. And I imagine that Ell-me would just be me, at least in appearance.”

There had probably been a hundred discussions of degrees of reasonableness among the Aerb group, and a part of me wished that I could have been a fly on the wall, or somehow gobbled up all of Aerb Juniper’s memories, if merging with him wouldn’t have watered down my own identity, or hurt him, if he still existed in some fashion. We’d talked about degrees of reasonableness with the Aerb version of Reimer, but fuck if I would fully trust him to give an unbiased interpretation of how it had actually functioned, because he’d always had his own understandings of the rules that often went counter to my own, and not just when he was trying to do a Candle of Invocation infinite wish loop.

The Amulet of Five Spirits was already stacked with the best non-magical animals that could be found on Aerb, as you might expect of an entad that had been in the family for a long time and thought on deeply by specialists. There were people whose entire graduate and post-graduate educations were focused on entad exploitation. The amulet had been filled with as wide a variety as possible, each of them S-tier at what they did, a screamingly fast predatory bird, an insect that could survive just about anything, the fastest fish that could survive in both freshwater and seawater, a fucking enormous big cat that could have killed a sabertooth with a single swipe of his paw, and a small, furry animal that could go into an extreme hibernation mode at a moment’s notice that allowed it to survive without oxygen, water, or food for up to six months. Each had their own purpose, and I had to ditch one of them in order to acquire Grak: I picked the bug to replace, as its particular brand of survivability had a bit too much overlap with what I already had.

And though it wasn’t very much of a surprise to me, I was still pleased that I was able to acquire a dwarf form from Grak. I changed to it almost as soon as the acquisition was finished, and felt myself shrink down and thicken very slightly, stretching my t-shirt a bit at the chest. I had the extremely disconcerting feeling of my penis shriveling up to nothing and some unpleasant changes to my butthole, which was now a cloaca.

“I think if I’m going to use this on a regular basis,” I said, my voice a touch lower, “I’m going to need entad clothes that change form with me.” My pants were too tight, except in the place that mattered.

“We’ll have to make a list of mortal species that are most worthwhile,” said Amaryllis. “And weigh that against the utility of animals. It would obviously be wonderful for the purposes of espionage.”

“Huh,” I said. I reverted to human form, thankful to have my penis back, and handed the amulet to Amaryllis. “There’s a chance that acquisition is the hard part, and once it’s acquired, anyone can use it. Worth a shot. We all know espionage isn’t my area of expertise.”

“It doesn’t work,” said Amaryllis, after a moment. “I can feel that it’s there, but it’s not letting me change. One moment, let me make sure that I can use the others.” She paused. “Stripping down.”

Raven and Grak were polite about it, turning away just a bit, and after a moment, I did the same, catching just a glimpse of her shirt coming up and revealing her stomach. I had been trying to figure out some argument for why it would have been appropriate for me to ogle her, but nothing had come to mind. We were married, sure, but it was a sham, and not one that required us to put up a show for Grak and Raven. I’d seen Amaryllis naked before, I liked seeing her naked, obviously, but we were in this uncomfortable place where the rules were unclear. Not unpleasantly uncomfortable, but a kind of tension, a frisson.

I did glance back at her, as she was in the middle of undressing, and caught her eye. She must have been watching me, because she was looking at me even before I was looking at her. All I got was a quick, impish grin from her, and then she turned into a great big bird with black feathers. My heart was hammering in my chest. She let out a loud caw, then flapped her wings and took off, making a circuit around the ballroom. The bird was some kind of terrifying fantasy falcon, and looked a bit like a stealth bomber, helped by the fact that it was jet black and incredibly fast.

I watched her with a kind of wonder, not just at the display of magic, but because I was starting to admit to myself that I really was in love with her.

Prurient Interest

“Alright,” said Amaryllis, smiling at me. “We have a huge amount of time blocked off together, impeccable defenses, and no distractions or other threats to our lives. It’s time to talk about what we’re telling the marriage inspector.”

“Yay,” I said. We were together at one of the estates that had once belonged to Amaryllis, which had been returned to her possession and cleared out. The room we were in had been a bedroom (the mansion had been riddled with them), but the actual furniture was much lower class. Amaryllis hadn’t quite remade the time chamber she’d spent eight months in, but quite a bit of the stuff had been reused, including the loveseat that we’d used movie nights on. The actual time chamber had been modular, with things pulled out of storage when needed and then shoved back in, but this room was bigger, so a few of the configurations had been spread out.

Light from outside was partially blocked by two towers full of plants, which had been disconnected from their light sources. Our well-used table was put up against one wall, with the chairs we’d spent hours each in, and a book shelf had been imported from somewhere, then filled with, from what I could tell, mostly books that Amaryllis had devoured inside the time chamber. In the actual time chamber, she had mostly used Sable for book storage, unless she was cross-referencing, in which case everything was spread out and annotated.

“You never really struck me as sentimental,” I said, looking things over.

“Well, that’s something that we can talk about,” said Amaryllis. “We have six hours today, then another six hours tomorrow, with some breaks built in for sanity. We’ll talk about how we view each other, what we imagine a counterfactual relationship would be like, then all the facts and stories that are a part of that counterfactual.”

“Or we could skip it,” I said. “The marriage inspector doesn’t have a huge amount of pull, does he?”

“No,” said Amaryllis. “But the office of marriage inspection leaks, and even if it didn’t, there’s a lot of benefit in producing our own leaks, which we would need some credible source for.”

“Okay,” I said with a shrug. “I’m going to warn you now that I don’t think I can give this my full attention for twelve hours.”

“Of course not,” nodded Amaryllis. “If I thought you could, I wouldn’t have scheduled so much time.”

“So,” I said. “You’re saying that you are sentimental?”

“I’m surprised you haven’t noticed,” said Amaryllis, looking around the room. “But sentimentality is just a matter of what feelings you feel. I don’t usually act sentimental, which is probably what stands out more in your mind. I take to favorites fairly quickly. I tend to think about the past in a rosy way, if I allow myself to. I hang onto things for as long as I can, even when they’re a little worn out, at least by inclination.”

I thought for a moment about that. I was reminded of the ‘Princess!’ shirt, which Amaryllis had worn enough that the pink had faded. “You always gave me the white mug,” I said.

“Because it wasn’t my favorite, blue was,” Amaryllis smiled. “But sure, I don’t indulge that sentimentality. If I feel torn up inside about some bit of nostalgia, that might get me killed, or someone else killed. So I do my best not to feel those feelings.”

“How are you doing with the Solace thing?” I asked.

Amaryllis frowned at me. “Well, Solace isn’t a part of the official story, because no one besides Uniquities seems to have connected the dots. It’s really unlikely that we’re going to be asked about it. The marriage inspection should be a formality, I just want us to have our stories straight for it, especially because those will be the stories going forward.”

“No,” I said, furrowing my brows. “Cut it out with that shit. Stop brushing it off and talk to me. I’ve seen the way you look at her sometimes. You were the one who told me that I was the only real person that you could speak with about it.”

Amaryllis watched me with her mismatched eyes. I found the new look enthralling. It was harder to look away from her. “You’re right,” she said. She set her notes to one side and folded her hands in her lap, staring at them. “I thought that I was going to have a daughter. Not a real daughter, but at least an adopted one. An unconventional offspring.” She sighed. “I had always wanted children. I still do.” She looked at me. “When I find a suitable mate, obviously, someone who’s comfortable with the fact that I’m already married.” The corners of her mouth turned up, not quite a full smile.

“Don’t try to get out of this by flirting,” I said.

“Flirting?” asked Amaryllis, eyebrows raised. “Me? Wait, did you think I was suggesting that you be the father of my children? Just because we’re married and you’re my best friend?” She scoffed. “Someone thinks very highly of himself.” There was nothing coy about the way she was smiling at me anymore.

“How did I end up married to such an unbelievable weasel?” I asked, because I could already feel myself being diverted by the energy she was injecting into the conversation. “I ask one serious question, and you’re like a slippery social ninja. Please speak to me. Think about it like this, if you turn me away, you’re training me to let things fester.”

“I just don’t want to talk about it,” said Amaryllis, not quite letting up with her charm offensive. “There’s nothing to say. I wanted a daughter, I thought she would be a daughter, and she wasn’t, she was just … Solace. Aside from the time we spent together before she got aged up, I went through eight months of pregnancy and then — I was going to say it was like giving your child up for adoption when you didn’t want to do that, but it was worse than that, because this child that I’d built up in my head wasn’t even real, the real child was a full grown woman who, at best, is suffering through some level of cognitive and hormonal impairment, and doesn’t view me as a mother at all. It sucks, but there’s nothing that anyone can do about it.”

“We could talk about it,” I said. “Like we’re doing now.”

“That’s true,” said Amaryllis. She sat in silence with me for a little bit. “I think it’s one of those places where there’s an ethical case for soul magic.”

“But … you haven’t?” I asked.

“No,” said Amaryllis. “No, I promised that I would get consent from the Council, but to do that would mean laying everything out, and I took what I view as the lesser of two evils.”

“You wouldn’t just … do it?” I asked.

“I made a promise,” said Amaryllis. “If I went back on my promise, you would know when I made a second promise that it would need to be taken with a grain of salt.”

“I went back on my promise,” I said. “With the Bethel thing. It was spirit, not soul, but —”

“I take your promises with a grain of salt,” said Amaryllis, wincing slightly. “I don’t mean that to be a slight, but between the Council, and especially between the two of us, I don’t ever want to be anything but honest. If you make a promise to me, I’ll quietly assign some slim probability that you only mean it in the moment, and when push comes to shove, you’ll back out. Sorry.”

“It’s okay,” I said. “It gives me incentive to change. So long as we’re in agreement that sometimes the universe sets you up to break your promises.”

“Absolutely,” said Amaryllis with a nod. “Thank you for pressing me about Solace.”

“I just want you to be happy,” I said. “Really, there are thirty of you now, so it’s about thirty times more important.”

“I’ll try to lean on you a little bit more,” said Amaryllis, leaning to the side and bumping her arm against mine for emphasis. “It’s mostly those little moments, being reminded that nothing was what I had hoped it would be like.” She sighed. “When she was just born, she would sleep all the time, her whole body laying across my chest. I loved that. Here was this little creature that I had made, sleeping away on top of me like she didn’t have a care in the world. I allowed myself to be sentimental about it. I would just … revel in it, watching her while my mind drifted.” Her eyes were slightly watery, and she bit the inside of her lip.

“Hey,” I said, putting my arm around her. “If that’s what you want, then someday it’s going to be real.”

“I want to wait,” said Amaryllis, leaning into me. “I wouldn’t want to bring a child into the world as it is now. It would be cruel. So, we’re going to have to win first.”

“Yeah,” I said. “And then I’ll help you find a suitable father.”

Amaryllis gave me a slap on the chest, but stayed there for a moment, nestled against me.

“You know,” she finally said. “They’re not really clones. They’re all just me. I haven’t used the other options yet, outside of testing, I just integrate every single time, so every clone out there has a more or less up-to-date compiled experience of what every other clone is doing, with a lag time of about a day. It’s like living my life at a rate of thirty days per day.”

“I can’t decide whether that sounds nice or horrible,” I said.

“It’s mostly nice,” said Amaryllis. “I’m sometimes social with myself, and learning very fast how to make things run even smoother, because when I integrate, I get both sides of any conversation. But I miss you, because I see so little of you.”

“Huh,” I said. It felt nice to hear her say that.

“Unfortunately, we can’t just cuddle up,” said Amaryllis, moving away from me. “Because you’re not getting out of prepping for the marriage inspector that easily.”

I groaned. “Alright, let’s do this then.”

Amaryllis cleared her throat, looking down at her notes. “I wanted to get the toughest thing out of the way first, which is what we do about Fenn.”

“Do about her?” I asked, giving her a questioning look.

“It’s a matter of how much backdating we’re doing,” said Amaryllis.

“Heh,” I said. She gave me a questioning look. “Backdating,” I said.

“Oh, that’s horrible,” said Amaryllis, wrinkling her nose. “That’s barely even a play on words.”

“Right, sorry,” I said. “But you were saying that we need some kind of explanation in terms of timeline? And … that Fenn presents a problem to that?”

“A bit of one,” Amaryllis nodded. “This is all a story, one that’s meant for both the marriage inspector and the general public. The timeline is at least partially known. The options for what we say about Fenn … it’s unpalatable, but the story and timeline would both work better if you’d never had a relationship with her.” She was watching me.

“She gets written out,” I said. “Ick.”

“It’s spitting on her memory,” Amaryllis replied. “It’s pretending that she was just the plucky comic relief and not something more. I don’t like it, but I wouldn’t suggest it if I didn’t think it was a better lie.”

“You know if she ever comes back to life, she’s going to be extremely pissed off?” I asked.

“If I could bring her back to life by manufacturing enough dramatic tension, I would,” said Amaryllis. “But she had made her peace with oblivion and what it meant not to exist. It was why she said that she wanted us to use her body in whatever way we saw fit. Once you’re gone, you’re gone. I don’t think that she’d be happy about it, no, but it would be pretty hypocritical of her.”

“Alright,” I said. “So we’re just … pretending that she didn’t exist.”

“To the outside world,” said Amaryllis. “And she would have existed, just not been romantically involved with you. Is that a lie you think you could tell? It’s a lie that we’re telling the outside world, not the one we’re telling ourselves.”

“Sure,” I said. I tapped my fingers on my leg. “That leaves open the possibility that things with us started … when, in the timeline?”

“Almost immediately,” said Amaryllis. “It’s a pretty classic trope of romance in a time of extreme threats.”

“Seems like we should stick to the truth as much as we can,” I said.

“Meaning?” asked Amaryllis.

“I mean …” I wasn’t sure how to phrase it. “The reality is that you didn’t like me very much, right off the bat.” The reality is that you then did your best to fall in love with me, because you thought that would work to your benefit, and then it worked a little too well, until you used soul magic to temporarily fix the problem, which seems like it might be unfixed now, if I’m not shit at reading signals, which I am.

“And you’re worried that it will be hard to keep our stories straight?” asked Amaryllis. “Most of what you say to the outside world will be filtered through me. We’ll probably do one or two interviews for the radio, but I’ll make sure those are pre-recorded, and screen what gets asked and what gets said.”

I was pretty sure she got what I was saying and was brushing off the question of her actual affections for me, past and present. “Well, I’m fine with it then,” I said. “There will be a parallel timeline to memorize, but the stakes are low, and we have lots of time at the moment.”

“Good,” said Amaryllis. “Now, I have a list of questions that the marriage inspector is likely to ask, and we should think through the answers to those questions, ideally together.”

“You don’t have answers prepared?” I asked.

“The answers are lies, but they should be true to who you are,” said Amaryllis. “I know you pretty well, but especially where it comes to romance, I’m doubtful of my ability to generate answers that are both plausible to outside observers and that resonate with you. And they’ll resonate more if you’re the one to think them up.” She looked down at her notes. “To start with, when would our first date have been?”

I thought a bit about that. “Fitting it into the timeline, it would make the most sense after the unicorn thing, if you mean ‘date’ in the sense of an explicit romantic evening.”

“Alright,” said Amaryllis. “First kiss?”

“Under the influence of the unicorn blood,” I said. “Then ‘for real’ after we had both recovered. Maybe with an awkward conversation in there.”

“What kind of awkward conversation?” asked Amaryllis, frowning. “I would apologize for kissing you, trying to keep some decorum and professionalism in our relationship, and then you would kiss me?”

“Something like that,” I said.

“It can’t just be ‘something like that’,” said Amaryllis. “It needs to be, if not an exact script, then an agreed upon narrative that can survive scrutiny. Would you mind acting it out?”

“You want to roleplay?” I asked.

Amaryllis nodded. “If that’s okay. Then, when you’re pressed on it, you can remember this conversation, and it will almost be like it actually happened.”

“Alright,” I said. “Sure.”

She set her notes down and stood up, facing away from me, then took a step away from the small couch and paused for a moment before turning around. She had completely changed her expression, and was looking at me with slightly downcast eyes and a quiet professionalism. When she spoke, her voice was smooth and calm.

“Grak told me that I kissed you while I was under the influence of the unicorn blood,” said Amaryllis. “I wanted to apologize for that. Obviously neither of us were in our right minds.”

I hesitated, then got to my feet. It felt weird to be the only one sitting. “No, it’s okay,” I said. “I didn’t get the wrong idea. We can continue on as we were. I know that the unicorn blood sometimes makes people say or do things that they don’t normally do.”

Amaryllis bowed her head a bit, looking at the floor, and tucked a strand of hair behind her ear. “Actually, just so you know, it’s not exactly that, it’s that it lowers inhibitions.”

I looked at her, then took a half step closer to her. Her body moved back slightly, almost involuntarily, but she didn’t move her feet, and after a moment, she returned to where she was, like I was a breeze that had momentarily blown her backward. She was watching me, her eyes moving quickly from one part of my face to the other. “Meaning what?” I asked. “That the only reason you haven’t kissed me before is your inhibitions?”

“It might be something like that,” she said, turning her head away from me to look at nothing in particular. She was breathing a little faster than normal, with her lips slightly parted. “Of course, I don’t think that inhibitions are necessarily a bad thing, sometimes they stop us from doing things that might not be advisable for one reason or another, and I would —”

I stepped forward, closing the distance between us, and when she turned to look at me again, I kissed her, which she met by melting into me, her hand slipping up to rest against my chest. We stayed like that for quite a while, kissing, and I tried to keep in mind what that other version of her had told me as her lips touched mine.

When she finally pulled away, she looked up at me with wide eyes. “I was going to say,” she said. “That there are lots of reasons that we shouldn’t be kissing each other.”

“Whatever they are, we can deal with them,” I said. “Together.”

Amaryllis nodded, then went back to the couch and picked up her notes, staring at them for a moment before looking up at me. “That was surprisingly smooth.”

I sat back down beside her. “It's not hard to be smooth when you know that there’s no failure condition,” I said. “Was it too smooth?”

“No,” said Amaryllis. “I think it plays well. Just —” she shook her head. “It wasn’t what I expected from you.”

“In a good way?” I asked.

She stared at her notes for a bit, then met my eyes. “Yes.”

“Good,” I said. “What’s next?”

Amaryllis looked at her notes for a bit, just staring at them without speaking, then cleared her throat. “What was our first date?” she asked.

“We never had time for them,” I said. “If you just mean romantic evenings with just the two of us instead of anything more complicated than that, then I guess it would have been in the bottle, following recovery.”

“For which we’ll have to fabricate some details,” said Amaryllis. She seemed to be finding her footing again. “Nothing special, just a meal shared together. Rabbit and roots? Better to be something that we both like and we both know.”

“Sure,” I said. “And after that, we settled together on a blanket to look up at the stars through the curve of the bottle to talk about —” I stopped, realizing that I was unintentionally plagiarizing from my relationship with Tiff.

“Children,” Amaryllis replied. “And the mistakes of our parents.”

“Works for me,” I said. “The mistakes of yours being … ?” She looked at me, waiting and not providing an answer. “You never knew your father, and that’s obviously not something that you want for your own children. Your mother loved you, but didn’t show it much, and that love took a back seat, because it had to.”

“That’s good,” said Amaryllis.

“Is it true?” I asked.

“True enough,” she replied. “I don’t know what unforced errors either of them made, and as to their values … I just wasn’t old enough. My father held off having children for as long as he could, which might be part of what deprived me of having a father. Even if he had lived, he wouldn’t have been likely to see me to adulthood. And they had a loveless, mercenary marriage, which I don’t want my own children to experience. I used to believe that people didn’t actually love each other.”

“So, it was a melancholy night under the stars?” I asked.

“A bit,” replied Amaryllis. “The conversation wandered, as they do. You don’t actually pick a topic and then stay with it.” She tapped her pencil against her notes. “Did you kiss me?” she asked.

“Yeah, just a few minutes ago,” I said.

She rolled her eyes, which was about what I deserved.

“Are you going to try to make a timetable for major milestones?” I asked. “Is that where we’re heading?”

“It’s the kind of thing that we’ll be asked about,” said Amaryllis. “Some amount of discrepancy is expected, because memories aren’t perfect, and beyond that, people want to paint themselves in the best light, but yes, we’ll want to stay consistent on sexual history.”

“So,” I said. “In this counterfactual history … what, are we just two horny teenagers?”

“Hrm,” said Amaryllis. “No. I’m reticent, not just because of conceptions about honor and the risk of pregnancy, but worry about what it would mean for the future and how it would reflect on me. There are some natural points of friction in our relationship as well, but not necessarily to the level that they would play into decisions about how things would progress between us.”

“Those concerns being … mostly about class?” I asked.

“And about you being the most powerful man in the world, or likely to become that man,” said Amaryllis. “I would have looked at the history of Zona with a raised eyebrow, and at my own position as one of your Knights, and thought that maybe the feelings I had for you were ill-advised.”

“Which would mean that you might pump the brakes,” I nodded.

“But it’s a romance, Juniper,” said Amaryllis. “The point is to introduce some tension into proceedings, and yes, that serves to slow it down, but it’s also to increase the level of desire from the participants.”

“Ah,” I said. “So we’re making out, but while we’re doing that, we’re talking about how we really shouldn’t?” I asked. When I thought about it, I supposed there was some of that with Fenn, though in the end … I won’t say that the relationship was a bad idea, but the obvious problems did come to a head in various ways.

“And you would have your own reasons for being reticent,” said Amaryllis. “Class would be one of them, obviously, my family another, the political reality a third, though you can obviously say whatever fits best for you.” She tapped her notes with her pencil again. “We need to have the uncomfortable talk about sex.”

“Will they really ask about that?” I asked. “Wait, I already know the answer, Anglecynn is shitty and backward, so yes.”

“We need dates and descriptions,” said Amaryllis. “If you’d like, I can go off in a corner and write up a script to give to you, and we can skip the conversation altogether.”

“I’m not that squeamish,” I said. It was a little bewildering that she thought I might be. “Are you?”

“No,” said Amaryllis, laughing a bit. “Of course not. It’s just sex. I’m inexperienced, to put it lightly, but I looked at enough pornography to desensitize myself.”

“But … why?” I asked. I was trying to picture it, and it seemed incongruous.

“I was trying to prepare for my wedding night,” said Amaryllis. “I didn’t want to be off-balance the first time I saw an erect penis. I wanted to understand the mechanical reality of it.” Amaryllis, studying, trying to get an A+ on the test.

“And … you would have been twelve,” I said. “Blegh.”

“Oh?” asked Amaryllis, giving me a prod with her finger. “And how old were you when you first saw porn?”

“That’s completely different and you know it,” I said. “Besides, we had the internet, it was hard not to see porn. You would be looking for something completely unrelated, and then bam, hardcore porn right there in your young, naive face. And when you go searching for it, my god, there you are, with every single perversion possible laid out right in front of you.”

“Nothing like Aerb though,” said Amaryllis. “I mean, you only had humans, and I know certain elements of your fantasies made it through to here. On top of that, I’m well-appraised of state-of-the-art computer graphics. So I know you didn’t have everything.”

“Well,” I replied. “Close enough. I can’t believe you’re getting competitive over this.”

Amaryllis paused. “But it’s a little bit endearing, right?” she asked.

“It is,” I said, giving her a smile.

She grinned. “We’re off track,” she said. “When would we have had sex?”

“After we were married,” I said. “You’re a good Christian woman, aren’t you?”

“Our story is that we spent months together, just the two of us, in a time chamber,” said Amaryllis. “In all that time, we would never have given in?”

“Can’t we just tell the marriage inspector that you’re not interested in sex?” I asked. “I mean, we can lie and say that we’ve had sex, but is it really necessary for us to fabricate this entire alternate life where we were not only dating, but where you’re missing this part of you?”

“I don’t consider it a part of me,” said Amaryllis. “It’s not core to my identity in any way. It’s not how I think of myself. And so if this plays better, which it does, I don’t see it as a betrayal of who I am, it’s just business. I care what the outside world thinks about my personal life only because it impacts me. In an ideal world, none of it would matter, no laws or alliances would hinge on it. But we deal with the world we have, so.” She shrugged, leaving that sentence truncated.

“Let’s say that it took some time then,” I said, looking her over. I felt a little wrong trying to imagine it, though she was asking me to, and we were married, and I was pretty sure that if I made even the slightest argument in favor of us having sex at right that very moment, she would go along with it, and then … well, then things would be different. I could feel my pulse start to quicken. I was thinking about it too much. “Would you stop me?”

“Stop you from doing what?” she asked.

I leaned over and kissed her, and she kissed me back. It wasn’t quite the same as before, because I was feeling a bit of that frantic energy. My hands went down to her waist, and slipped beneath her shirt to touch her skin, then to pull her shirt up, which momentarily broke our kiss. I was watching her face before we came back together, and there was a seriousness to her expression, but she met me to resume our kissing.

Eventually, once I had removed her bra, I began kissing her neck, then her collarbone, and I felt her fingers grasping at my shirt, lifting it up off me too.

“I’m not going to stop you,” said Amaryllis. “If that’s what you’re waiting for.” Her eyes went down to my crotch, then back up to my face.

“It’s a bad idea,” I said, but my hands had gone to the button of my fly. I had my pants halfway off before I stopped what I was doing and looked at her. She was removing her own pants, and she’d gone faster than I had, leaving her just in her panties. Her body was perfection, slender and muscled, her skin pale. “You said that you wouldn’t stop me,” I said.

“I won’t,” she said, and she came over to tug at my pants to get them off. I ended up on the couch, facing her, my back pressed against the arm of it. She was up on the seat, steadying herself with one arm, her legs touching mine, not quite straddling my thigh.

“Wait,” I said, and she froze where she was, giving me an expectant look. “You don’t want this,” I said.

“Did I do something wrong? Say something?” she asked. “Juniper — some part of you wants this, and I’m not going to take an erection for consent, but — it might be better for you to just follow your instincts and work out the feelings later.”

“I’m right that you don’t want it,” I said. “I just, for a moment, deluded myself into using you.”

“Using me — Juniper,” she shook her head. “I want you to be happy,” she said. “I want you to feel pleasure, I want you to feel satisfied, you’re — you’re my best friend, my partner, my husband, and literally whatever you want me to do with my body for you, I will do it. And after we’re done, I’ll hold you, comfort you, and explain that I’m perfectly fine, that you didn’t do anything wrong, that I still think of you the same way as I did before. This isn’t something that you need to torture yourself over.”

“I can’t,” I said, cringing. “Sex means something to me, maybe that’s just fucked up Midwestern programming, or maybe it’s —” I stopped myself. I didn’t want to say Maddie’s name, not when we were both nearly naked, not like this, but that was almost certainly where it was coming from. I’d felt gross afterward, like I’d used her, and all the excuses about sex being purely a physical thing had evaporated away. “I just can’t.”

Amaryllis sat back a little. “You’re thinking about Maddie.”

“I am,” I said. I didn’t know how she knew. Maybe it was obvious. “And even if I could put it out of my head in the moment, I’m scared that when it was over I would keep drawing the comparison.” This wasn’t the time or place to be having this conversation. I didn’t want to have it with anyone, ever. “Maddie and I talked about it, before we did it, and I asked her, I made sure that she was sure, but the whole time, she wasn’t saying anything, she wasn’t doing anything, she was just waiting for it to end. And I probably would have felt like shit about it anyway, but that made it worse, because it was just —” my words were failing me. It was the way Maddie had been after, too, the way she’d seemed disappointed in what it was.

“It was bad sex,” said Amaryllis. “I’ve heard that for women the first time can be awkward, weird, and maybe painful. And I know that you think that was the worst thing you ever did on Earth, but that’s all wrapped up in all this other stuff. I’m older than you, Juniper, by almost three years now. I don’t mean to slight her, but I’m more of an adult than most adults. I’m in full control of my own body, and you have very little power over me. If you think that you’ll regret it, then I don’t want to do it, and I’m not going to lie to you about what I imagine it will be like for me, but I think you’re letting a bad experience make too much of a mark on you.”

“I know,” I said. “I just … it’s a hang up.”

“So you’re turning me down?” asked Amaryllis.

“The whole time, you would just be waiting for it to be over,” I said.

“Or I would be enjoying pleasing you,” said Amaryllis. “If this is about how you feel, I’m fine with that, I accept that, but if you’re trying to make a logical argument, then I’m going to tear it down, because you don’t have a leg to stand on.”

“It’s just a feeling,” I said. “Sorry.”

“Don’t be sorry, it’s your choice,” said Amaryllis. She looked down at my underwear. I had, in this moment of panic and bad feelings, lost my erection. “I have a request.”

“Sure,” I replied. “We should probably get dressed though, if this is just a confusing and regrettable diversion.” My eyes kept going to her tits. She was beautiful, perfectly proportioned, and I wasn’t just saying that because she was also wonderful in so many other ways.

“I’d like to see your penis,” said Amaryllis. “We’re faking a sexual history together, and while I doubt that the marriage inspector will ask, it would be better for me to not have to guess. Ideally we would consummate this marriage, but failing that … I want to see it.”

I was watching Amaryllis. Her face was set and determined. She was still bare-chested.

“Sure,” I replied slowly.

Before I could do it myself, she reached forward and pulled my underwear down. Unsurprisingly, given that she was almost completely naked, the most beautiful woman in the world had just asked to see my penis, and she was touching my upper thighs, I had gotten hard again.

“I guess I don’t see what the fuss is about,” she said, staring at it. She was moving her head around to see it from different angles, as though one would suddenly appeal to her. “No offense.”

“None taken,” I said. “It’s very average.”

“Can I touch it?” she asked.

“Yeah,” I said.

“Are you sure?” she asked.

“Yeah,” I said again.

Her hand was warm and soft.

“Do you think you’ll regret this?” asked Amaryllis.

“No,” I said. “Kind of hard to concentrate though.”

“Hmm,” said Amaryllis. She was experimenting with me. “I don’t want to have sex with you, if you don’t want to have sex,” she said. “But part of the reason that we’re doing this is so that I can have some experience. Verisimilitude, right?” She was looking me straight in the eyes. “So I was wondering whether you would be alright with me getting the full sensory experience — if I could taste you.”

I stared at her. “Yes,” I said.

She moved her head forward, lowering it down, then looked at me. “It’s not like I like you or anything.”

“You tricked me,” I said, once she was finished. She was laying against me, still without clothes on, resting her head against my chest.

“Oh, certainly,” said Amaryllis. “That has got to be one of the top ten cons of all time. It took wits and wiles, truly, a heist where planning and preparation were my watchwords. Convincing you to accept a no-strings-attached blowjob is the kind of thing that will surely go in my memoirs. It’s a real feather in my cap.” She ran her fingers through the sparse hair on my chest. “How are you?”

“Good,” I said. My body was done tingling, and the moment of clarity was fading away. “Great, actually.”

“It wasn’t too much of an amateur effort?” asked Amaryllis.

“Not at all,” I said. I was turning the idea of what had just happened over in my head, and trying to see if there was some seam that I would eventually dig into, some way that my brain would decide this was a bad thing. There didn’t seem to be anything wrong with it. “And … how was that for you?”

She was silent for a bit, still touching my chest.

“Are you trying to find some way to tell the truth without causing offense?” I asked.

“I am,” she said. And then she was quiet for a bit longer, just touching me, which she seemed to enjoy. “I feel like your ideal version of me would be telling you something very different from what I’m about to tell you. It’s difficult, because I know just what she would say. There are levers that could be pulled, and they’re easy to see. It’s one of those situations where telling a lie would be so much easier, and I would just deal with my own, less enthusiastic feelings, because it’s a trade that I would happily make. It’s just … I’m not sure that it’s a trade you would make.”

My heart sank a little. “That bad?”

“No,” said Amaryllis. “Not at all. I knew what to expect. The sensory experience was new, and that was at least a bit interesting. But I could tell within the first twenty seconds that it wasn’t for me. I’m perfectly willing to do it again, I am, but if I’m being honest, it was just … manual labor for me, I guess. I liked making you happy. I liked taking care of you. I’d even like for this to be a permanent arrangement. But it wasn’t what you wanted it to be, for me.”

“Alright,” I said. “I guess I’ll accept that.” I let out a breath and touched her on the back. “Can I ask what the offense version was?”

“It was like licking someone’s elbow for a bit, then having them sneeze in your mouth,” she said. “Though that’s not quite it, because sneezing carries some negative connotations due to germs. I really don’t think there’s an equivalent. Normally you don’t inject bodily fluids into another person.”

“Well that’s brutal,” I said. “But … I don’t know. I’m glad we didn’t have sex, but I’m also glad that we did that.”

“And you would be fine with it being the new normal between us?” asked Amaryllis.

I thought about it, not just the appealing aspect, but everything else as well. “I have a condition,” I said.

“You have a condition you’re going to give me, so that I can keep giving you blowjobs?” asked Amaryllis.

“Well, it sounds ridiculous when you put it like that,” I replied. “But my condition is, if not some quid pro quo, because I wouldn’t want it to be transactional, then … I’d like to do something for you. Something that I’m not super into, maybe? Something that I wouldn’t do except to please you.”

“Oh,” said Amaryllis. “That’s actually thoughtful of you. But I can’t think of — wait, have you read the Bible?”

I froze where I was. Of all the things that I’d thought she might say, that wasn’t one of them. “I read it a bit,” I said.

“Did you actually read it, or did you just set out to read it, get bored a few books in, skim some more, look things up, and then say that you’d read it, which no one was going to be able to call you on?” asked Amaryllis.

“The latter,” I replied. “And if that’s what you want, then that’s what I’ll do. I’m a little bit weirded out by your being Christian.”

“I’m not,” said Amaryllis. “My god isn’t the Christian one. But the Bible has helped me to understand monotheism, and I go back to it from time to time.”

“I can’t promise that I’ll get the same things out of it,” I said.

“It would be nice if you did, but that won’t break my heart,” said Amaryllis. She leaned over and kissed me on my chest, with no pretense that this was for any other reason than because she wanted to.

We still had to do all of the marriage inspector stuff. It was pretense, but it wasn’t that much pretense that it could be completely blown off, and some of what we were writing down — especially the less salacious stuff — would become the basis for a planned PR offensive. There was a lot of hammering down dates, and on top of that, a fair bit of rehearsal and rote memorization. I was worried that I was starting to know the fake history better than the real one.

The meeting with the marriage inspector took quite a bit of time. I was interviewed first, then Amaryllis, and then the two of us together. The questions were just about as invasive as I had thought they would be, but Amaryllis and I had prepared for them. We lied a lot. My only note of actual concern was the entad he had on his desk the whole time, a metronome whose function was unclear and whose speed seemed to raise and lower. To his credit, he was unflappable and professional, right up until the very end, when I stopped my heart, bringing the entad metronome to a standstill. I had mostly done it on a whim, but when I explained that I had just been testing to see whether that was what the entad did, the marriage inspector seemed rattled.

We didn’t actually consummate the marriage. Amaryllis wasn’t pushing for it, probably because she was worried about a misstep, or reminding me too much of Bethel. And I wasn’t pushing it either, because it felt like a line that couldn’t be uncrossed. It gave some element of unsteadiness to our relationship, the whole thing did, but it was a good type of unsteadiness.

Feeling Blue

There was, as you might imagine, considerable argument about our next step.

There was one and only one quest which had a time limit, and that was the one that Perisev had set for us, which was to go murder Captain Blue-in-the-Bottle. We had other quests, some of them that I’d had for a very, very long time, relatively speaking. And then we had Fel Seed.

With our current party, Grak was the only one prepared for Fel Seed. He could put up a ward against Fel Seed’s magic, which suffused every biological thing that Fel Seed had ever touched, and be safe against a wide variety of monsters and threats there. He would need other wards as well, particularly one against acceleration in order to prevent Fel Seed from simply throwing a rock at our faces. And even with those measures in place, there were a lot of things that simply couldn’t be warded against, like attacks that pinned us in place and deprived us of the things we needed to live, like air. Some of those weaknesses could be shored up, but still, it was pinning a lot on Grak. Grak could extend the wards anchored to his skin out a considerable distance, six feet, which meant that he could protect us, but it would still be damned scary.

The second issue, aside from our safety, was that we didn’t actually give a fuck about Fel Seed. What we were after was an extradimensional tunnel to parts unknown, a tunnel that was, according to classified reports from a Second Empire dimensional survey, located almost smack dab in the middle of the City of a Thousand Brides. It wasn’t certain that we would need anything special to go through it, but getting to the heart of the exclusion with millions if not billions of flesh beasts standing in our way, only to find a locked door we couldn’t get through, seemed like it was really something we wanted to avoid. We didn’t know where the tunnel led to, what conditions would be like inside the tunnel or at its destination, or what kinds of things might come out of left field.

I wanted to go down that tunnel. I wanted to find Uther. I had felt, for a long time, that Uther was at the end of it all, because if I were this world’s Dungeon Master, then that relationship would be at the heart of the story I was trying to tell. Uther hadn’t just made his mark on the world, he had put the world into a mold of his own design. And that world? It was my world, my ideas, my concepts, my style. Even my companions were marked by Uther, at least a little: Amaryllis, his descendant and the spitting image of his daughter; Raven, his one-time companion; and Bethel … well. I could conceive of some world where Uther wasn’t the end of the story, but if it had been my campaign, then after everything had wrapped up with Uther, that’s where I would have asked my players whether they were interested in running more things in that world, or whether they just wanted an epilogue session or e-mail laying out what the future looked like.

And that, really, was what I wanted. I wanted to be done with things.

We were all in agreement with that, the question was one of approach.

“It’s suicide by another name,” said Raven. “Every well-planned, intelligent attempt at Fel Seed has revealed a new trick up his sleeve. He’s been smart, he’s collected mages and entads over the last few hundred years. There are Fel Seed cultists to contend with, beyond just his flesh beasts. Aside from that, it seems likely that you’ll need star magic in order to get into the tunnel, which you don’t currently have.”

“So I’ll get it,” I said, keeping my voice level. “But I really doubt, from a design perspective, that we would be gated out because there was a skill that I didn’t have. You don’t require a single ability like that.”

“Fel Seed was poorly designed,” said Grak.

“Not poorly designed,” I said. “Antagonistically designed. There’s a difference. But yes, I concede the point.”

“We can’t keep doing what we’ve been doing,” said Amaryllis. “We’ve had our first exclusion, and I think we’re right to be terrified of more. Exclusions in Uther’s day were gentler, the world wasn’t so cross-pollinated, and there were more magics in general. If we lose bone magic, there will be at least a million dead over the span of a year. If we lose rune magic, that means an end to bottling and millions in the hells. If we lose warding, that doesn’t just mean that thousands or hundreds of thousands instantly die, it means that warfare tips hard in the direction of offense. And that’s just talking about exclusions. The stakes are increasing as Juniper gets stronger, and that means that people are going to get hurt, even if we play perfectly from here on out.”

“Anglecynn was in no wise an escalation from Mome Rath,” said Raven, crossing her arms.

“Uther himself explains, in Degenerate Cycles, that escalation is inevitable,” said Amaryllis. “He knew narrative better than anyone else. On this matter, I think we should trust him.”

“We’re not strong enough,” said Grak.

“Then it’s a matter of becoming stronger,” I said. “Unlocking more magic is a no-brainer, as is entad acquisition. But for every quest we tackle, there are sure to be complications, and … I have to assume that there’s some amount of rubber-banding, since that was always how I played it, and I’ve found myself up against the ropes so hard without getting ground to a fine paste that I have to assume that it’s not just the anthropic principle. Right?”

“Anthropic?” asked Raven.

“Meaning … let’s say you flip a coin, and if it comes up tails, you shoot yourself in the head,” I said. “You flip three times, it’s heads every time, so you say, ‘wow, how lucky’, but in any world where you had flipped tails, you would have been dead and not able to make that observation.” I shrugged. “So maybe there are other worlds where I’m dead.”

“I don’t think the world works like that,” said Amaryllis.

“Wouldn’t you pick heads?” asked Grak. “Heads for a shot in the head?”

“We don’t know for certain how or if it works,” said Raven. “Escaping from danger twice doesn’t mean that you’ll escape the third.”

“This is you saying that?” I asked. “You, who were there while Uther escaped from danger hundreds of times?”

“He never acted like he was invincible,” said Raven.

“Sure,” I replied. “Walking into danger like you think the Dungeon Master wouldn’t dare hurt you, that’s a good way to set yourself up for a rude awakening. I’m just saying, so long as we have a workable plan, which we’re halfway to, we have to consider that there’s some level of balance in play. And like Amaryllis said, the longer we wait, the greater the costs are likely to be.”

“It’s a question of how much we do before we go,” said Amaryllis. “Are we at least agreed on that?”

She got a round of nods from everyone except Solace, who simply sat there. She had been silent for much of this discussion.

“No?” asked Amaryllis.

“If the locus wills it,” said Solace. She didn’t say how she would determine that. We sat in silence for a bit, chewing on that. The question was whether we would go ahead without Solace, and the answer, I was pretty sure, was yes.

“We need Bethel,” said Grak.

“Valencia too,” said Amaryllis. “To keep Bethel in check, if nothing else.”

I nodded. “Then we’ll add that to the list. We’ll get a report from Valencia about how she’s coming along.”

“It hasn’t been long enough,” said Raven. “If it’s possible to reform the house, I sincerely believe it will take more time than we’ve given it. And to go into this venture with bad blood between us would be disastrous.”

“Maybe,” said Amaryllis. She tapped her fingers against the table, and I could just tell that she was thinking about narrative. Hypothetically, if we were having intraparty squabbles and tension, that might take some narrative weight from whatever was happening with Fel Seed. It wasn’t a recipe for success, but I could see the angle.

“So let’s make a list,” I said. “We put down some checkboxes, then figure out the fastest and least dangerous way to check all of them off. Call them sub quests. We’ve got two already, one is grabbing Bethel, the other is acquiring star magic. What else?”

“Entad support,” said Amaryllis. “Anti-biologicals, methods for quick escape, clairvoyance, which will be tough, and probably a few others. I’ll set a clone to the Caledwich auction house next time I have ten minutes to spare, and put out some feelers. Grak, we can form a sub-committee.” I could see Grak found this slightly ridiculous. He did nod though.

“What else?” I asked. “Is that it?”

“Souls,” said Raven. “If we’re going to do this, then we’ll want to use the same method that you used against Onion. It risks exclusion, but soul magic has always had smaller exclusions. We’ll need souls from all kinds of mages, and in fairly large quantities, which will take some doing.”

“I’ll get in contact with Finch and the athenaeums,” said Amaryllis with a nod. “And I think that should be it. That’s equipment, personnel, and training. More knowledge would be nice, so I suppose we could make sure that everyone has read the relevant literature, and it’s possible that we could make our own surveys of the FSEZ … I’ll put another clone on it.”

“Good,” I nodded. “We’re not committing to it yet, I want to make that clear, but I want to put us in a position where we could enter the zone at a moment’s notice if we have to, instead of flying by the seat of our pants.”

“And in the meantime?” asked Raven. “We’re taking on Captain Blue-in-the-Bottle?”

“Yes,” I said. “We’ll do our best to meet Perisev’s timeline. The faster, the better.” I resisted the urge to say ‘how hard could it be?’.

Captain Blue-in-the-Bottle had a dumb name, and if my experience with Onion was any indicator, that meant that he was ungodly powerful. He was the god-king of his exclusion zone, and commanded a rather large labor force of undead, their souls still trapped inside their bodies, having mouths but unable to use them for screaming, and if you were reading a book on the captain, that was what it would lead with.

Well, a sensible book, anyway. I read three different biographies of the man, and only two of them began by talking about the exclusion zone and the horrors that went on there. The third biography was a bit different, not taking things out of order, and instead presenting Captain Blue-in-the-Bottle as a child, then as a young man, and continuing on like that with no sense of foreshadowing. It was a more interesting read for it, but not really the most convenient or straightforward way to present the information.

He hadn’t been born Captain Blue-in-the-Bottle, obviously, since most babies didn’t have a rank. Instead, he had a perfectly innocuous name, Elisha Blue, and so far as anyone knew, a perfectly normal childhood, though perhaps one with more money than had been good for him. His family had owned a recreational schooner, and he’d taken to it enough that he pursued a career as a sailor, one funded by his parents, who were necromancers.

(Technically speaking, ‘necromancy’ meant ‘death divination’, and more properly, you would have called the practice his parents engaged in ‘necrolurgy’ or something like that, but Aerb didn’t seem to care about being proper with its Greek or Latin, because it didn’t actually have those languages. The local Latin equivalent was originally the work of a small group of canine Animalia, which spread into academic and later popular usage long before Uther’s time.)

There were a lot of things you could do with necromancy, and Aerb had a few different traditions that involved animating the dead. As this particular field was practiced in Elisha Blue’s day, it involved taking a full skeleton and pumping energy into it, then having it animate in order to do crude but useful work. It was considered ghastly but not evil, and after the invention of the infernoscope (long before Elisha’s time), it had been confirmed that the dead didn’t mind it: they were being tortured for all eternity, or, if bottled, had presumably gone to oblivion. Contrary to how D&D usually framed necromancers, this variety of necromancy was almost exclusively used for utility, saving labor rather than with skeletons running rampant or being used in undead armies. If they were in armies at all, it was as pack mules or latrine diggers, their crude movements meaning that they required direct necromantic supervision.

Elisha Blue had become a sailor, but one that followed in his family’s trade, with a crew of skeletons to provide motive power across the seas of Aerb, their oars supplementing tall sails. Sailing was fucking ludicrously dangerous, given how little chance there was your soul would be recovered, and that meant that prices for shipping those things that needed to be shipped were relatively high. A better necromancer could get more from his thralls, and by all accounts, Elisha Blue had been a good necromancer, even going so far as to make some innovations in his particular field of magic. It was nothing that revolutionized shipping, but it lowered his costs and bought him a bit of respect. His ship was outfitted with entads that allowed it to carry more, as well as load and unload faster, and he became a force unto himself.

The biographies were at odds with one another in regards to that part of his life. It might have been that he was relatively unexceptional, a man making what progress he could, even if it was fairly similar to the other advancements of the Second Empire. Or it might have been that if you’d been watching him closely, you would have seen the seeds of malfeasance then, the ways that he treated his customers and employees. Maybe he was a cheat and a swindler, maybe he was just like any other shipper, headstrong and arrogant enough to think that he wouldn’t die and be sent to the hells. What he definitely became, the biographies agreed, was a fairly brilliant innovator, as far as necromancy went.

In the naive case, necromancy required the whole skeleton, and if you could preserve the body using mummification, brining, salting, or some other method, all the better, because that allowed for slightly more fine-grained control and considerably more power. So far as I could tell (nothing I’d read was technical), this brand of necromancy involved the soul inside the body, what Fallatehr would have called the anima ipsa, that part of your being that stayed behind on Aerb when you died, and could be accessed through bone magic in order to pull attributes from you, even when you were definitively in the hells.

While he was still a proper captain, Elisha Blue had made some minor contributions to the art of necromancy, particularly in the realm of miniaturization. The thing about corpses and skeletons was, if you needed them to do useful labor for you, there were some parts of them that really didn’t need to be functional, like their skull. The (rather minor) advancements that Elisha made mostly had to do with compacting skeletons and corpses, rearranging them or altering them so that only the parts you actually cared about were taking up space. This was especially important in his chosen profession of shipping, where less weight was a decided asset. Beyond his actual skill in necromancy, he had also made some advancements in engineering which allowed more undead to take up less space by virtue of the mechanisms they were powering being more efficient, rows of oars being replaced with cranks that fed into a drive train. He was powerful, but none of his work was terribly revolutionary. If you’d been a necromancer in those days, you’d have heard of Captain Blue. If you only knew one necromancer, there was a good chance it was him, though that was partly due to his penchant for advertising.

His real work, and real brilliance, began once he retired from shipping and inherited his parents’ fortune. He had a country estate, which had once belonged to a duke before a series of reforms in the Second Empire. There, he built a research laboratory, one that was intended to be world class. The intent, so far as it could be inferred, was not just to advance the state of the art, but to create novel methods of necromancy that could be monopolized and sold. It was hinted, though not in so many words, that Captain Blue intended to found his own athenaeum, perhaps with the backing of the Second Empire, one that focused not just on necromancy, but a few other death-related fields. With this concerted and well-funded effort in place, the field expanded by leaps and bounds, with Captain Blue at the forefront, always the most powerful. The work on miniaturization continued, and after five years, they had gone in new directions, allowing a necromancer to control his undead at a distance of miles, and see through their eyes, if they had eyes. Beyond that, the full-body requirement had been circumvented, allowing undead that were nothing more than a pair of legs, or an upper body with no head.

Twelve years in, this brand of necromancy failed everywhere on Aerb, save for that estate and an area roughly a hundred miles around it. Captain Blue was the only person able to practice it. He couldn’t leave the zone.

In the parlance of the Empire of Common Cause, this was an enpersoned exclusion, but more than that, it was a free exclusion, one that posed no particular harm to anyone living there, and which could be exploited freely. Elisha wasn’t some monster, he was just a normal man, an upstanding necromancer who had, at worst, pushed things too far, and who became an object lesson in the kinds of boundary pushing that could sometimes lead to exclusions happening. It wasn’t even entirely clear why necromancy had been excluded, because nothing extreme had happened, at least so far as people could ascertain. Captain Blue himself had no answers.

The planned athenaeum never happened, of course, but the research laboratory continued on, now working entirely to the whims of one man. Some fraction of the world’s necromancers moved to the estate, now only capable of working on theory or helping Captain Blue in some capacity or another, forever assistants.

Two years after the exclusion, the first of Elisha’s manufactories opened up. Unlike the necromantic manufactories that had come before it, it wasn’t simply a matter of undead driving cranks while complicated and expensive machinery did the real work, no, these new undead, christened ‘zombies’ were something else, barely even dead at all, perfectly preserved with only a slight pinkening of the skin, capable of complex (if rote) actions and some adjustments to correct for errors, techniques never before seen. There were a few limitations, like the fact that the candidate dead needed to die within the exclusion zone and ideally where Elisha could work on them, but the Second Empire was backing Elisha’s venture, which seemed to be a way to turn a waste product into a thing of value. If you knew you were going to die, and especially if you were a laborer of some kind, Elisha would pay to have you transported. If the Second Empire was going to execute someone, they would often send them to Elisha’s exclusion.

Elisha seemed to take some joy in branding and public relations, and it was during the time of the Second Empire that he took on the moniker of Captain Blue-in-the-Bottle. His products were stamped ‘zombie made’, sometimes with a little drawing of a loveable, dim-witted undead, and he had his own logo and persona, a captain of a ship in a bottle, reference to his history as a world traveler, and his present as someone stuck inside an exclusion zone. There was some deliberate effort to make himself appear like a harmless eccentric, with the zombies as his mascots.

The Second Empire fell, but Captain Blue, in the metaphorical bottle, continued on. His zombies were slow to wear down, but they did need to be replaced eventually, and so he still paid dividends to people who were willing to come to his exclusion zone and join his undead workforce. Not too many people were fooled into thinking that becoming a walking corpse wasn’t macabre and ghastly, but if it paid … well, people would do a lot of things, if there was money attached, especially if they were dying.

Captain Blue-in-the-Bottle himself didn’t die when he should have. He was human, but breezed past normal human lifespan without so much as a word of explanation about how he’d done it. Necromancy was, obviously, the easiest thing to imagine having helped him.

It wasn’t too long before the founding of the Empire of Common Cause that Captain Blue-in-the-Bottle was found out. His zombies weren’t undead in the way people had thought, they weren’t bodies being remotely piloted by the skilled and talented Captain, they were partway living, capable of feeling pain, pain which they experienced an immense amount of, owing to the ways in which their bodies broke down. A zombie set to knitting would wear away at their joints until bone rubbed against bone, until the outer layers of skin had been removed by abrasion and the nerves were rubbing directly against the needles. Their souls were still in there, and only when the body had been worked until it could work no more would Captain Blue-in-the-Bottle sunder soul from body, bottling it not out of compassion, but because he was worried that information would leak to the infernals.

Nowadays, shunned by the international community, Captain Blue-in-the-Bottle had become a much darker figure, an abusive dictator who ruled over those who still lived in his lands with an iron fist, backed by an army of his undead, some number of the laborers converted to use in warfare.

A few attempts had been made on his life, but it was a difficult thing, because he was holding all his zombies hostage. According to him, if he were killed, all his zombies would ‘die’ with him, and that meant between one hundred thousand and half a million souls would get unceremoniously dumped into the hells, where they would be eternally tortured as they had been on Aerb, but without any possible hope of rescue. Following his exposure, or possibly before, depending on who you asked, Captain Blue-in-the-Bottle had stopped retiring his zombies altogether, and instead buried them in mass graves that were then covered over, the zombies ‘living’ there in hidden caches so that if Captain Blue-in-the-Bottle died, it would come with a cost.

The funny thing about the exclusion zone was that aside from all the torture of the dead and the out of control dictator, it really wasn’t that bad. People still lived there, some of them brainwashed into thinking that this was all somehow okay, others staying before they were prohibited from leaving. There was nothing wrong with the zone, no inherent threats, and if you went past the imperial border guards and snuck inside, you might think that it was just like the rest of Aerb, if maybe a little parochial. It had been classified by the Empire as a minor exclusion, meaning that you could live there with a little adjustment, but that was at least partly a political designation.

It took us six days to get there, flying in our ship, almost perpendicular to the path we’d taken to get to Anglecynn. Without a dragon overhead, Captain Bonny was in high spirits, and because of Amaryllis’ clone merges, we could be kept abreast of everything that was happening in both Anglecynn and Poran. So far as Amaryllis told me, Poran was a bit of a slow grind, and would be for the foreseeable future, while in Anglecynn, she was barrelling through virtually unopposed. We’d tried to figure out some way to disguise the clones, but eventually had just settled on letting it be known what they were, their weaknesses obviously not broadcast. Amaryllis held seats on virtually every council or sub-council of importance, as the standard limits of ‘no more councils than you can handle’ were much higher for her.

If the locus had its domain extended, it wasn’t actually using that power. Over the six days in the airship, I saw neither hide nor hair of it. Solace wasn’t with us.

The ship landed in a field far outside the city-state of Necrolaborem, and then took off again once we had disembarked, moving back to a position where it could swoop in and rescue us on short notice, if for some reason the teleportation key didn’t work out, and if we had ten minutes for Amaryllis to update her clone that was staying back on the ship.

There were a few things that we didn’t have a plan for.

First and foremost, we didn’t have a plan for how to save all the souls inside the zombies from going to the hells. That wasn’t strictly necessary though: those people were being tortured, and it was entirely possible that if they got an upper hell, they would get something easier to handle than a combination of locked-in syndrome and a decaying body. I didn’t really know the calculus there, but it seemed like keeping Captain Blue-in-the-Bottle alive because of the threat of other people going to the hells wasn’t that good of a reason, given the circumstances. Beyond that, it seemed likely to me that we were going to deal with the hells, whether that was after I’d somehow achieved godhood, or at some point before that.

Second, we didn’t have a plan for killing the Captain, because we didn’t know what that would take. I figured that if he could be put down with a bullet to the head, someone would have done that, but there were surprisingly few attempts. We had information from two sources that should have known a lot, Finch and Raven, but neither had any real notes.

“He’s bad, obviously bad, but he’s not the literal end of the world,” Raven had explained. “So far as I know, the Library hasn’t put any effort into getting rid of him, and certainly wouldn’t have done so under my direction. If he was killed in some other timeline, I never heard about it. Pinno would have more information, but that would mean going back to the Library, which … is probably ill-advised, for a number of reasons.”

“The initial hope was to starve him out,” Finch had explained, in a separate conversation. “Legally, there’s a total embargo, nothing in, nothing out. All he’d have to do is stand down, release the undead from his grip and promise that no more would be created. Economic power didn’t work on him. There are a few concessions, minor deals, but nothing major.” He’d shrugged. “Technically speaking, there’s nothing to stop anyone from killing him, except that you’re not allowed in, and whatever surprises he’s got for you. People have tried. They don’t come back. Thankfully, if you try, then it’s a mess I don’t need to get involved with, so long as you don’t do anything too impossible.”

“And you’ll give us backup?” I asked. “Bring down some goons in shimmerplate, at least once he’s dead?”

“Exclusions aren’t really my department,” he replied with another shrug. “But there are already hundreds of people at the border.”

And that was basically where we were. We had Grak, myself, and Raven, plus Amaryllis as well, though she was feeling a bit inadequate as a fighter. Solace had said that she would be able to show up in our time of need, which she didn’t elaborate on, and probably had something to do with the moving bit of domain that I was radiating out from me.

Necrolaborem was an ugly city. Like a few industrialists back on Earth, Captain Blue-in-the-Bottle had formed a company town, a planned community that was devoted, heart and soul, to the enterprise that revolved around his necromancy. In its heyday, it hadn’t been a bad-looking place, though it was micromanaged and excessively curated, maybe because the Captain was concerned with presenting a front to the rest of the world, a happy, campy face on something that made people squeamish. Now, it was a mixture of two types of buildings: the first were old structures, like the grand train station, now missing pieces of its edifice and in desperate need of a paint job, and the second were tall, unadorned, magestone buildings, put up by a steel mage who had been building with only function in mind.

We were approached by guards when we got to the edge of the city, as we’d expected we might be. Two were human, but the other two were undead, their skin off-colored, more pink than it should have been. It was from carbon monoxide poisoning, I knew, the preferred method of death for the Captain. If I hadn’t known anything about the Captain, I would probably have missed the fact that these were zombies. Looking at them with my other senses, I could see that they were well and truly dead, not breathing, hearts not beating, still and silent when they stopped moving. They wore clothes like normal people though, uniforms with thick red bands around their arms, and looked straight ahead, slightly unfocused.

This was the endgame of necromancy, the dead made almost into people again, and inside them, people who had no control, experiencing only pain. They were better than people, in a lot of ways, they didn’t need sleep, they were strong, they had skills that went beyond what they had in life, making them ferocious soldiers.

“Announce yourselves,” said one of the guards. His rifle was raised and pointed at us.

“Juniper Smith, Amaryllis Smith, Raven Masters, and Grakhuil Leadbraids,” I said, gesturing at each of us in turn. “We’re here for a meeting with the Captain. We sent a letter ahead.”

The guard hesitated for a moment, then nodded and lowered his weapon. “Follow me. Don’t deviate.”

It was kind of funny. The easiest way to get up close and personal with a man who had been cut off from the outside world was just to send him a letter asking if we could visit.

The country estate had been (magically) bombed and rebuilt, then (non-magically) set on fire and rebuilt, and the current iteration was absolutely hideous, though clearly better maintained than the surrounding city of Necrolaborem. There were zombies everywhere I looked, with most of them doing complicated work that I wouldn’t have thought of zombies as being able to do, keeping the grounds, trimming hedges, raking up leaves, and generally engaging in semi-skilled and self-directed labor. Many of them were guards, standing there in partial armor, equipped with both a sword at their hip and a void rifle on their backs. One of the benefits of being a despot who was hated by the international community was that you didn’t really have to give a fuck about international bans or anything like that. Void was actually one of the minor concessions he had with the Empire: he had vowed to only use void for the purposes of defense, halfway cooperating with the imperial ban.

The guard led us into the main hall of the estate, which had an incredibly tall ceiling, with arches that made it feel like an inverted ship’s hull, though it was far too big for that. It served double duty as something like a museum. On display, largely behind glass cases, were a wide variety of necromantic contraptions and inventions, charting Captain Blue-in-the-Bottle’s rise to greatness. There were probably twenty corpses all told, some of them moving to show whatever detail was explained on their plaque, and mixed in among them were some other, less directly necromantic things, like news articles explaining some grand triumph, name plates from a few ships and a full figurehead, and further down, all kinds of artifacts from his product lines, boxes with their stamps on them, a logo that showed a ship in a bottle, and various things that he must have saved from hundreds of years ago.

“At this time, Captain Blue-in-the-Bottle would like you to examine his collection while you wait for him to finish up with important work,” said a well-dressed man in spectacles who the guard handed us off to. “My name is Terrence, and I would be happy to answer any questions that you have about the displays.”

“Do you have an estimate for how long it will be?” I asked.

“Not at the moment,” Terrence said with a short bow. “I apologize, but the Captain can be quite busy at this time of year.”

That was fucking absurd, and I hoped we all knew it, but I wasn’t sure that Terrence hadn’t bought in on what the Captain was selling. It took a certain kind of man to create a monument to his own existence, and I was fairly certain that if it were at all possible, Elisha Blue would have brainwashed his ‘citizens’ into believing that he was a genius who had been unfairly maligned by the international community. Terrence seemed young.

“How long have you worked for the Captain?” asked Amaryllis.

“Since the age of fifteen,” replied Terrence. “Though in some sense, everyone within the EZ works for him from the moment they’re born until the moment their corpse gives out.” He attached no particular emotion to the term ‘corpse’, which was impressive, but maybe meant that he didn’t know the corpses still felt pain. It was hard to tell. “But please, enough about me, I would be remiss if I didn’t show you at least a few highlights of the collection.”

“Lead away,” I said.

It was almost certainly a power play, but I didn’t particularly mind, because at least it was a little bit interesting, and it would help to sell us as interested business partners, rather than a fireteam here to kill him. I could tell from the conversations we’d had that I had the least distaste for necromancy of the lot of us, though seeing corpses up close, including the mutilated ones that had been part of the Captain’s miniaturization efforts, still did make me a bit squeamish.

Eventually, as we were on the fifth display, this one just a leg that was in constant motion, pushing a pedal, a zombie came trotting down the steps and pulled Terrence to the side, delivering him a message on paper. Terrence read it, then folded it and put it in his pocket before returning to us. I was surprised at the sophistication the zombie had displayed, which was beyond what I had read about in my books. It was clear that Captain Blue-in-the-Bottle hadn’t simply been at rest, he’d been working, making advancements in necromancy over the decades. Our intel was out of date.

“The Captain would like to know whether you intend to kill him,” said Terrence, keeping his chin high and his diction precise. I had, naturally, read the paper through Terrence’s eyes, so the question was no surprise.

“Our weapons are precautions,” said Amaryllis, the most accomplished liar among us. “It’s not unheard of for those who have been backed into a corner to resort to tactics like ransom, and the four of us would fetch a hefty price. Better to have thorns, and better to show them.”

“Very well,” said Terrence, nodding and letting out a breath. “But I must inquire as to the exact nature of this visit, beyond that which was covered in the inquiry you sent to the Captain.”

“Did he share it with you?” asked Amaryllis.

“Not at all,” Terrence responded. “But he said, in general terms, that you had a business proposition of an undefined nature, the sort that would be best communicated in person, given the delicate nature of our alliances with the outside.”

The wording there, ‘our alliances’ was either a slip or just part of the lies that the Captain told his people. Amaryllis and I had argued for a bit about whether or not the Empire of Common Cause had really stopped Captain Blue-in-the-Bottle from plying his trade. To hear her tell it, obviously he was right, people didn’t give a shit where and how their stuff was made, so long as they could claim the moral high ground, and maybe not even then. Obviously the zombie-made goods were being bulk teleported to a buyer (or shell company) on the outside and then sold as though made by mortal labor. She had no proof though, and I felt like it was needlessly cynical, since there were plenty of examples of people banding together in other circumstances so that they could stamp out, or at least shun, what they saw as evil.

“We represent the Republic of Miunun,” said Amaryllis. “We’re undergoing rapid expansion at the moment, fueled by a number of technological developments, and we have a bottleneck in terms of labor. What we need from the Captain is some kind of arrangement that will satisfy our needs at an agreeable cost, whether that means converting one or more of his manufactories, or dealing with a shortfall in labor here. The price per unit labor of his workforce is currently unclear, and he should know, upfront, that at this stage, we are engaged in fact-finding only.” At least some of that was true. We were going to need factories, and in an ideal world, all the labor would be done by, if not the undead, then at least people we could pay a pittance, which would allow us to reserve the tuung for things that actually mattered, like engineering, logistics, sales, and that kind of thing.

“I see,” Terrence said again, giving us a short bow. “I’ll go inform the Captain at once, and I apologize for any paranoia that he has displayed in making his request, as understandable as that paranoia might be.”

He left, and we were alone, save for the guards, who might as well have been wooden statues for all they were capable of hurting us. No, if we were going to get hurt, it would be with some novel weapon, or maybe with some novel truth. If it looked like we could steamroll him, which it did, then there was probably a catch.

“I’m muting us, if we need to talk,” I said.

“Nothing from me,” said Amaryllis. “It’s what I expected.”

“The state of the art is better than I thought,” said Raven.

“He’s faking half of it,” replied Grak.

“Faking?” asked Amaryllis.

“He stationed undead so we could see them,” replied Grak. “They were engaged in repetitive actions that looked like work. They were not performing labor.”

Amaryllis frowned. “Good catch,” she said. “Anything else unexpected?”

“I see nothing suspicious with my sight,” said Grak. “The wards are weak. The necromantic magic seems naively unconnected to him.” That was a good sign, since it meant that his zombies would probably continue on without him, giving more time for soul rescue operations.

“Be on your toes,” said Amaryllis. “Be prepared for sob stories and sweetheart deals.”

“That’s not the impression that I got of him from his biographies,” said Raven.

“The biographies are information that we were given before coming in,” said Amaryllis. “They’re propaganda by the Empire, and set dressing by the Dungeon Master. Don’t trust it.”

I agreed with her, but sometimes the catch was that there was no catch. Sometimes the unhinged multi-millionaire necromancer dictator really was just that, nothing more.

Our private discussion complete, I had time to look at one more exhibit before Terrence came back, and it was one that I was honestly a little surprised to see in his collection: placed between two panes of glass was a broadsheet containing Captain Blue-in-the-Bottle’s response to allegations about the pain and suffering of the zombies.

I’d read his rant in one of the biographies, skimming it the second time it showed up in the second biography, but I stood there and tried my best to focus on it, to place it into its proper context and read it as it would have been read by contemporary readers.

He admitted everything outright. Yes, his zombies had the capacity to feel pain, and yes, the slow decay of their bodies in the course of their work caused them considerable pain, on top of the suffering that they experienced by virtue of not being in control of their own bodies. All of this was made very clear in the first paragraph, laid out in simple terms. The remaining five paragraphs were devoted to explaining, in an increasingly sneering tone, that this simply did not matter in the scheme of things, and that this would do nothing to stop sales of his products except to those who wished to prove to their neighbors that they were fine, upstanding folk, and even then, no boycott would last. The primary argument, as I read it, was that labor was suffering, something people had always accepted, but this took a backseat to the insulting tone.

Even trying to place it in context, it didn’t make any damned sense. For a man who had done a lot of fairly innovative stuff with branding and public relations, it was a colossal misstep, and if he’d really believed that business would continue on as usual, what he should have done was to keep his mouth shut, or to issue a blanket denial, or at least give a mealy-mouthed explanation of why it wasn’t as bad as it appeared. Instead, he’d gone for explaining that it was exactly as bad as it appeared, maybe worse, and that he’d had full knowledge of it, and beyond that, his customers were complicit and such shitbags that they wouldn’t change anything. It was like if some Earth company’s history of abusive practices and wage theft was exposed, and the CEO’s response had been, ‘how’d you think we kept prices low, maybe you’re the ones that are the real monsters for buying our products’.

And if he’d done the smart, polished, PR thing, sent out the equivalent of a press release that said ‘we’re looking into these allegations and taking them very seriously’, maybe the exclusion zone would be considered a free exclusion, and the accusations would be treated as unpleasant rumors, or even just a blemish on his record.

He never did walk it back, even when it became clear that he was wrong, and as it turned out, people did care enough to boycott and embargo him. He was wrong about people, which cost him a lot, but he just kept doubling down on being horrible, which had led to the current state of affairs.

Terrence led us up a grand staircase, through some hallways and rooms that I was convinced were only there to impress us with their size and grandeur, and finally, to the study of Elisha Blue.

There were books on all the walls, wrapping the study in their covers, and I had to imagine that some of them were just for show, because even with the ladder on rollers, it would have been a pain and a half to get at some of them. Beneath the towering walls of books was a slab that was clearly sized for a corpse, and a desk that held a number of papers, behind which was sitting the man himself, Captain Blue-in-the-Bottle. He looked younger than I’d thought he would, in his early fifties at the latest, and he didn’t look in the least bit dead, which was another surprise. He was, however, wearing a black captain’s hat and a buttoned up navy-blue coat that looked entirely like a costume. His face was thin and his forehead had the bulk of his wrinkles, but he didn’t look bad, for someone dressed as a mascot.

“Ah,” he said, looking up from his papers. “It’s not often that I have visitors.” He gestured at four chairs that had been carefully set out in front of his desk. “Please, have a seat, I was just going over some numbers in preparation.”

“Thank you,” said Amaryllis, taking the seat that was offered. It was kind of ridiculous to have a meeting like this with all of us in our armor, but he was wearing a captain’s outfit in a land-locked city, so I supposed we were just going to roll with it.

“Do you know, I don’t get the papers?” he asked. “They want me not just starved of creature comforts, but blinded to what’s happening in the world as well. For myself, it doesn’t matter terribly much, but for my citizens, it’s a terrible blow.”

“You aren’t allowed to give them news?” asked Amaryllis, furrowing her brow. “Why?”

“It’s by imperial decree,” said the Captain, giving us a shrug. “I assume that they didn’t think things through very well when they made that decision, which wouldn’t be uncharacteristic.” He gave us an avuncular smile. “This is by way of explaining that I don’t have any particular information on who you are or what’s going on in the wider world at the moment.” He paused and looked at Raven. “Obviously Raven is known to me, if you’re one and the same.”

“I am,” she replied with a nod.

“And how can Necrolaborem be of service to you, if you’re truly here in pursuit of mutual benefit by trading our comparative advantages?” asked the Captain.

“The four of us make up the Council of Arches on the Isle of Poran, which currently belongs to the Republic of Miunun, consisting almost entirely of a species called tuung,” said Amaryllis. “We’re currently embarking on a rapid industrialization plan, but at least some of the work will be unskilled, which was where we were hoping you could offer your services. We would need to know the costs involved in retrofitting one of your factories, what kind of production you can maintain, what timeframes we would need to be dealing with, and obviously there would be some logistical issues, because we would naturally want for this to be done without it being common knowledge. Miunun isn’t a member of the Empire, but it plans to be, at some point.”

The Captain nodded. “And I assume that you brought with you some plans and schematics? Or some engineering expertise?”

“I’ll be lead engineer,” nodded Amaryllis. She held her gloved hand out and a leather tube appeared in it, courtesy of Sable. “The preliminary diagrams and notes are there, but part of the reason a meeting is required is that I don’t know the specifications of your operations here.”

The Captain hesitated, then reached across the desk to take the tube from Amaryllis. He opened it cautiously, then took the papers out and unfurled them across his desk. He took a minute to look through the pages, frowning at them, before finally looking up at us.

“You’re not here to kill me,” he said.

“We were fairly clear on that,” said Amaryllis, giving him a little smile.

“And what about being found out?” asked the Captain. “If you intend to join the Empire, you’re likely thinking in terms of public perception. When that happens, will the contract be ended? And how do you intend to enforce this contract?”

“If the contract is beneficial to both parties, then it doesn’t matter that there’s no mechanism of enforcement,” said Amaryllis. “We’ll have our own factories on our end, producing precursors, and send parts to you for final assembly and packaging, then you’ll send them back to us so that they can be distributed for sales. Once sales are complete, we can send you whatever you need via bulk teleport, assuming that currency does little for you.” She frowned at him. “Surely that must be the arrangement you have with your other business partners.”

The Captain gave her a bewildered look. “What other business partners?” he asked.

Amaryllis rolled her eyes, just a bit. “Surely you don’t expect us to believe that no one has approached you before. There are strong incentives to break the embargo, and with bulk teleport, it would be relatively easy to hide. Entad communication is generally difficult if not impossible to intercept. I’m not asking you to name names, but we can’t possibly be the first people in decades that have elected to do business with you in defiance of imperial law.”

“Is that what you believe my life has been here?” he asked, sitting back slightly in his chair. “Do you think that I’ve been living a life of luxury, that the embargo hasn’t been a source of constant pain and suffering?”

“No,” said Amaryllis, “I just —”

“The exclusion robbed me of my athenaeum,” he said, leaning forward, hat slightly askew. “The embargo robbed me of my business. All I have is this land, which is only mine by the threat of damnation for hundreds of thousands, and you dare to suggest that I’ve been living a life without hardship?” His eyes were slightly wild.

“I meant no offense,” said Amaryllis. “I assumed wrong.” She looked to Grak, who gave her a slight nod, then to me. “Juniper?”

“I’d like to talk for a bit about ethics, if we could,” I said, looking at the Captain.

“Ethics?” he asked, frowning at me.

“I’ve read three biographies of you,” I said. “I read your initial response to the public in regard to the allegations. If we’re found out, I want to have had a discussion about the problem of pain, something that I can offer in my defense.”

Captain Blue-in-the-Bottle sighed. “How trite,” he said. “Very well, I will bring up the idea that pain and suffering are part and parcel of ordinary labor, and you will bring up the idea of consent, and I will respond that I have a number of manufactories where every zombie did, in fact, give meaningful consent to the procedure, knowing full well what it entails. You then will insist that people cannot give meaningful consent to what amounts to torture, or that consent is not eternal in that way, and an agreement made involving autonomy is effectively identical to selling oneself into a permanent slavery, which is similarly not allowed by the current regime. Can we skip past all that then? Or was that the extent of the conversation you wished to have?”

“I assume the problem of pain is intractable?” I asked. “It’s not something that you could fix by, say, causing antemortem nerve damage?”

“The problem,” he replied, “Is that your politicians want someone they can publically castigate, someone they can stand against, as a way of telling others that they are virtuous. Necrolaborem has a great quantity of skilled labor, but not so much that they can’t slight us. Labor abuses are rampant elsewhere in the Empire, but they are cloaked, and the result of poverty, exploitation, and carelessness. I, however, am a single man, a target of opportunity. I have tried to negotiate with the Empire in good faith, but the politicians benefit only from tightening the noose they have on me.”

He hadn’t answered the question, and I assumed that the answer was ‘no’, he wasn’t able to eliminate pain, not if he wanted to keep his current level of power and control over the zombies.

“You feel maligned,” I said. “You feel like the rules are different for you, or maybe that they’re only different because you’re openly saying what other people believe, but fervently deny.”

He nodded. “But from the way you say that, you don’t agree. And yet, you come here for my services, to use my manufactories, to benefit from the labor that I’ll be forced to sell you at low rates because there are no other buyers.”

“I’d hoped for more nuance,” I said. “I’d hoped that you had some better answers. Maybe you would tell some lies that would make you look better, but no, there’s just blame for others and an unwarranted cynicism about what the world is like, mixed with a base selfishness and unwillingness to change. It’s disappointing.”

I stood from my chair and began walking over to Captain Blue-in-the-Bottle, who reached into his desk drawer and began to pull a void pistol, which I sliced through without breaking my stride. He got up and knocked over his chair, but I was far, far faster than him, and had him by the wrist before he could get away, not that it would have been possible for him to do that given I had Amaryllis and Raven right there, and that Grak had been building up wards the whole time we were talking.

“Are we good on wards?” I asked Grak.

Grak nodded to me. “Necromancy is difficult. It’s all or nothing at this point.” We could sever his connection to his undead, but it wasn’t clear what would happen then. Maybe they would all go still, ready to become animate once they had his orders, maybe they would continue on with whatever they had been tasked with, and maybe they would all ‘die’, which would give us thirty minutes or so to get souls out from hundreds of thousands of bodies, most of which were hidden. That last scenario was the one we were trying our hardest to avoid. Grak had been surreptitiously experimenting with warding against necromancy from the moment we’d touched down in the EZ, as had been the plan, but from the way he’d phrased it, I was pretty sure that he didn’t have a workable solution, or any idea what the end result would be.

I turned back to Captain Blue-in-the-Bottle, who I had been stilling. “Alright,” I said. “Tell us what your contingencies are.”

“Beset by enemies,” he said, letting out a little moan. “On all sides.”

“We want the locations of all your zombies,” I said. “We want to know where the mass graves are. We’re going to spend the next month in this exclusion zone if we have to, removing souls and ensuring that everyone escapes damnation.”

While I was talking, I was trying to use the skin contact to probe for his soul, which wasn’t working well. He had a pulse, but the magic that should have been flowing through his blood wasn’t just weak, it didn’t seem to be present. I was hoping to avoid soulfucking him if I could, but if it meant keeping a half million people from being eternally tortured … well, I would do it, and then kill him afterward. The problem was, whatever necromantic magic had kept him alive long past his natural lifespan, it had fucked with my path into his soul.

“Never,” he said. “You would kill me.”

“We wouldn’t,” said Amaryllis. “We have no interest in your death, only in salvation.” On Aerb, that was a poetic term for oblivion of a soul.

“And what?” he asked. “You would keep me in a prison for the rest of my eternal life?” He spat at me, and I effortlessly dodged, still not letting go of his wrist.

“Let’s talk,” I said. “Let’s come to an arrangement.”

“An arrangement,” he squawked. “This — this violence against me, and you want an arrangement? For every minute you hold me, I’ll send a dozen souls to the hells.”

“Here’s the thing,” I said. “That’s a bullet that I’m willing to bite. I came in here intending to kill you, knowing that it would probably damn half a million people to the hells, and being content with that, because what you’re doing to them now is torture. When I say that we should make a deal, what I mean is that you can walk away from this with your life. You can start with a conversation.”

He spasmed once, kept from moving too much by how I held him, and I braced for the worst, but then he simply went limp and dropped to the ground, lifeless, with my grip on him released.

“That wasn’t him,” said Grak. “Enabling a full ward against necromancy dropped him.”

“Fair enough,” I said with a sigh. “Then we’re just going to have to find the real Captain.”

“That’s going to be difficult,” said Amaryllis with a frown. “He has six hundred square miles to hide in.”

“And he’ll know that we’re here, and that we’re coming for him,” said Raven. “There’s nothing to prevent him from amassing forces and retaliating against us.”

“I could make detection wards,” said Grak. “One attached to the hull of The Underline might serve.”

“It depends on what his next step is,” said Amaryllis. She clenched her fist. “So much for this being an easy in and out mission.”

“We have time before our deadline is up,” I said. “And there’s one obvious solution to finding him.”

“I don’t like it,” said Amaryllis.

“She’s a quest too,” I replied. “One that we’re going to have to do sooner or later.”

“I don’t like it either,” said Raven. “Quest update?”

“None,” I replied.

I was listening with vibration magic, because of course I was, so I heard the footsteps long before the servant, Terrence, got close enough that I could see through his eyes, and far before he opened the door. He looked in on us, and his face fell.

“The Captain would like me to inform you that he is no fool, and has contingencies in place,” he said, voice trembling slightly.

“Of course he does,” I replied. A lich couldn’t be killed just like that, if you destroyed his physical form, he would just emerge from his phylactery in 1d10 days, which meant that finding his phylactery was going to be our number one priority.  “Do you happen to know where he is?”

Terrence shook his head, and I had half a mind to soulfuck him so that he would say everything that he knew. He really did seem to be just a part of the help though, and to do that to an innocent, especially when there were other options, wasn’t something that I was going to do, whether that was petty morality or not.

“Then we’re off,” I said to the others. “Terrence, thank you for showing us around. If you can, let the Captain know that we’ll be back, and we’d be perfectly willing to discuss the terms of his surrender. He can’t hide from us, and he can’t outlast us.”

Terrence nodded once.

“Now get the fuck out of here,” I said.

Five minutes and a poke through the wards later, we were back on the Isle of Poran, preparing to go to a different exclusion zone entirely: the one filled to the brim with Doris Finches.

Star Pupil

We were given our own room while the Dorises secured us a star mage to teach me. It was bare bones but functional, and Grak had us warded almost as soon as the door was closed.

“So,” Amaryllis said to Raven. “Tell us what we’re walking into.”

Raven shrugged. “Based on what they said, nothing too serious, but they’re obviously missing some crucial piece of the picture. The elemental planes are full of some rather grotesque creatures, and a small handful of them are able to survive on Aerb, if anyone is stupid enough to bring them over. The Dorises are almost certainly lying, unless they’re incredibly coordinated, because it’s very difficult for a star mage to make a portal that allows anything to survive the transition.” She tapped her fingers on her leg, then used her bracer to call up a book, which she opened and leafed through before showing us a picture. It was a segmented worm with horrible little lamprey fangs, along with some spines along the sides. “This is a bloodworm. It’s very fast with very sharp teeth, and can drain the blood of a human in approximately eight seconds. It feeds on soul energy, not on blood itself, but with blood as the medium. Current belief is that on the elemental plane of blood, they seek out occasional infusions of soul energy from various sources, going into a feeding frenzy and then curling up to become dormant.”

“How easy to kill?” asked Amaryllis, frowning at it.

“A regular nation with a halfway competent military would be able to do it,” said Raven. “Grak might be able to make an annihilation ward that kills them outright, and if it really is contained to a single building, that would be enough. In theory, it will be easy. But as I said, it’s possible and likely that the Finches are lying, not just because the bloodworms are so unlikely to have come over on accident, but because if it were just bloodworms, they should have been able to take care of it themselves. There’s some other problem on top of the worms too, which I’m less confident about.”

“You said other failure states,” I said. “What are the consequences of a blood mage having possession of a thousand times their normal blood volume?”

“There’s a feedback loop,” said Raven. “A blood mage with an excess of blood can draw on the power of that blood in order to boost herself, and that boost can make it easier to squeeze more power from the blood. At a certain tipping point, which is more like a hundred times normal blood volume, they can get taken over by something else, unless they’re sufficiently skilled at handling it.” Bloodlust, I was guessing. “Usually it’s not a threat to the world though, just to a city, and never for more than a few days until they run out of victims. With Doris … if she can duplicate the blood when she duplicates herself, it might be different.”

She paused and used her bracer to pluck out another book, which she rapidly leafed through. “The second failure state, which is of a greater scale, involves pushing the limits of internal blood volume. Blood mages have magical hypertension, and a grandmaster can weaponize that, allowing their blood to shoot out at high speeds. With sufficient pressure and a sudden rupture, it can vaporize a small country.” She kept leafing through the book, frowning, until eventually she stopped. “Sorry, I thought there was a picture, but it would suffice to say that this is at the upper echelons of personal power, attainable only by either a grandmaster or someone drawing on positively enormous quantities of blood. I think the figure, which I can’t find at the moment, was that it would take more than a million gallons of blood.”

“You’re saying that there are blood mages powerful enough that if you cut them with an infinitely sharp sword, they would explode with blood so hard that they would be the equivalent to a nuclear weapon?” I asked.

“In theory,” said Raven. “In practice, it’s happened in one or two timelines, under extreme circumstances.”

“Where the fuck are we on this chain of quests?” I asked. “We need to go fix a Doris fuck up in order to have them track Blue-in-the-Bottle, so that we can kill him, so that Perisev will, what, not make an attempt on our lives? This is ridiculous. We could just leave and kill Perisev, which would shortcut the quest.”

“Do you want to?” asked Amaryllis. “Because I would, again, be fine with allowing the Dorises to kill themselves.”

“It doesn’t seem like a good plan from a narrative perspective,” said Raven, frowning at Amaryllis.

“Doris Finch is a pressure point for Amaryllis,” I said to Raven.

“Enough of a pressure point that you’re going to make suboptimal plays?” Raven asked Amaryllis.

“No,” said Amaryllis, crossing her arms. “I’m just stating a preference.”

“We need the Dorises for just a little bit longer,” I said. “After that, fuck ‘em.”

“Fuck ‘em to death,” said Amaryllis.

“I don’t particularly like this dynamic,” frowned Raven.

“It has its charm,” said Grak. He looked oddly happy. He’d told me once that he liked Amaryllis when she was angry.

“Imagine being so shitty of a person that you would ambush and kill thirty of your clones so that you could gain four slaves, who are also your clones,” said Amaryllis. “And even that term, ‘slave’, is doing her favors, because this is one of the most brutal, oppressive versions of slavery that has ever existed on the face of Aerb. I will make every effort to not let my opinion of her cloud my judgment, but if we find a way to wipe her out, I’m strongly in favor of doing it.”

“On the plus side, the person she’s hurting most is herself,” I said. “So the primary victim here kind of deserves it.” I didn’t personally hate Doris Finch, but I could get why Amaryllis would.

“I can ward against her, incidentally,” said Grak. “Redundant, given she is flesh and blood.”

“Still useful,” I said. “How quickly could you ward against a hypersonic blood bomb? If that’s on the table?”

“It would have to be a velocity ward,” said Grak. “The blood would cease to be blood at those speeds. Too much debris would be caught up in it.” He frowned, not because he was thinking about the problem, but because he was unhappy with his solution. “It would have to be small and ideally covering extradimensional space. A ward over Sable would give us the best chance. Even then I would need a few minutes to make it rigorous, and it would take all my concordance.”

“Good enough for me,” I said. I had no idea how impossible what I was asking for was, but ‘able to withstand a nuclear blast’ seemed like it had to be on the very upper end of what was possible with warding.”We’re going to hope that it’s not that, but Raven was the one who foreshadowed it, so blame her if it comes to pass.”

Raven rolled her eyes, but didn’t give any of the obvious counterpoints, and I didn’t know her well enough to know what that meant. Maybe she really did believe she’d be responsible for it, if it happened.

The Doris star mage was let into the room after a knock on the door sometime later, and, for the first time since Fallatehr, I was introduced to a new magic with an audience present, not just my companions, but a second Doris besides the star mage, this one guarding her.

“Fuck the stars,” said Doris. She looked more or less like the others, but her hair was on the longer side, her clothes were a bit unkempt, and she had a brand on her forearm that looked to have been either a really elaborate design, or several brandings over a long period of time. It wasn’t clear to me whether she had done it to herself or — well, if she’d done it to herself in a different way. “Most of the time you won’t be looking at them. Every month or so, maybe every week for precision work, you’ll look up at the stars and figure out which ones are important and where they are, using a bit of math to figure out what they mean to you based on where you are, and then forget about them until your constructions drift off-course and you need to look at the sky again. You’re good with math?”

“Uh,” I said. “I was told that there wouldn’t be calculus. Other than that, yeah.” I had the Mathematics skill, but it was kind of pointless at the lower levels, since it didn’t give me any skills that I didn’t already have from a decent high school education and an aptitude for systems.

“What the fuck is calculus?” she asked. “Look, it doesn’t matter, can you do basic geometry?”

“Sure,” I said. “Sohcahtoa.”

“Right,” she said, apparently understanding what I’d said. “And you know what a function is?”

“Uh,” I said. “Sure.”

“If you don’t know what a function is, tell me now and we’ll start there,” said Doris. “You’ve got four fucking hours and if you don’t get what you wanted out of this, I get shot in the head.”

“I’m just not sure that I’ll be able to define it,” I said. “A function is putting in some value x and getting out some value y.”

“Okay,” she said, relaxing slightly. “Sure. Star magic is just a matter of constructing functions, finding out which variables you’re putting into them, usually in consultation with a star map, then drawing or fabricating the output.”

“Uh, okay, so, to give an example?” I asked.

Doris sighed and pulled some papers out of her pocket, then spread them across the floor. “This is a map of the stars, made three days ago, by me,” she said. As I looked at the paper, I realized that it wasn’t paper at all, it was parchment, some that had been scraped and reused enough times that it was starting to show. The Dorises didn’t have wood, and couldn’t import it, which meant that they made do with what they had. What they had a lot of was Dorises, and I was about ninety percent certain that her parchment had been made from human skin. “Our position, using the planar hexline system with offsets, is -0.57891, 0.17663, 0.40288.”

“You use three axes?” I asked. “Not two?”

“If you want to do the math to transform the two axis system into the three axis system, knock yourself out,” she replied. “It’ll only add an extra twenty or thirty minutes onto every single calculation you do.”

“Just asking,” I said.

“Base prismatic expansion is given by taking a multiplication of XYZ coords with a polygon constellation given by magnitude ordering of stars, starting with brightest red, not violating the concave angles rule, and shifting hue down.” She had been tracing out a pattern on her map with her finger, and when she was finished, she looked at me.

“Okay,” I nodded, looking down at her chart. “So we start with the brightest red star, then — magnitude ordering means that we move to the second brightest star, but hue shifting would mean that we, what, move to orange? Which takes precedence?”

“Depends on what you want, usually magnitude,” she replied. “Typically hue needs to be a half-step down. Playing with hue is not what I would start with, if I were you. There are specific strands of the function, elements that you vary to produce different effects. We’re talking base prismatic expansion, the simplest ‘spell’ you can do.”

“And a half-step is … what?” I asked, looking at her map with its notations. “Based on this, you register hue as a single number, and if this is in normal visible range, that’s, uh, kind of complicated.”

“I’m trying to teach you what I can in a few hours,” said Doris. “Do you want to blow past this and figure it out later, or do you want me to belabor the details?”

“You didn’t study at an athenaeum,” I said. “You learned this yourself.”

“I had books,” said Doris. “Part of a deal with the outside at some point, I never got much more information than that. But knowing that isn’t going to help you learn.”

“Sorry,” I said. “The hue thing — the stars are all kinds of colors to human eyes, but human eyesight is narrow and lopsided, and not all eyes are the same. I’m having trouble with just the base concept here.”

“The way I understand it, normal star mages use fak and lep, two types of glass that do hue shifting based on thickness,” said Doris. “I don’t have that, so I go based on what I see. It doesn’t matter all that much, because you can do the same pattern in different ways and it still works.”

“So a half step, in your system, is just … split the colors up into seven, then half a step?” I asked, looking at her notation. She nodded. “So we go for the brightest that’s within half a step, then the next brightest that’s in the next half a step, ignoring any lines that we’d have to draw through, and ignoring lines that would make concave angles — looping to the start of the colors if we have to?”

“No,” said Doris. “When you get to deep indigo, you draw a line back to the start, and if that’s not a legal shape, then you have to do it a different way.”

I nodded, starting to maybe understand a little bit. “And the multiplication by coords, that’s, uh.”

She pulled out a pen and hesitated above parchment. “Do you have paper?” she asked. “It will be easier.”

Amaryllis stepped forward, from where she’d been leaning against a wall, and dropped a ream of paper along with a number of pens and pencils from Sable. Doris stared at them, then took a pen and paper. She began to quickly sketch out some math, copying from the map and marking down all of the relevant stars to make the shape.

“You have three coords, and N points,” said Doris. “How you apply those coords depends on whether they’re negative or positive, and what numbers you can divide N by. Here, we’ve got six sides, which means alternating, which means —” she did the calculations without speaking for a bit, and came up with a new shape, this one not actually a polygon, because some of the lines were crossing each other. “And that’s it, as basic as basic gets. So long as the stars stay in their current configuration, if you write that shape anywhere near here, it’ll make an extradimensional divot on the surface over the course of about two hours or so. And there, now you know star magic.”

Skill Unlocked: Star Magic!

Achievement Unlocked: Starry-Eyed

Spell discovered: Base Prismatic Expansion!

“Yup,” I said, nodding. “Now I know star magic.”

“There are obviously a hundred things you’re going to have to learn, if you really want to be a star mage,” said Doris. “I can’t tell you them, because I don’t know most of them. Some of the shitty star mages out there just go look things up in books all the time, then plug in the numbers, and that’s enough that they can skate by. Me, I do what I can with what I’ve learned, mostly through experimentation, or under instruction from another star mage. It’s a fuckton of labor, but you can split it up. For us, that means that you get told to do the calculation right or get ended, solutions are usually easier to check than to generate. I’ll give you whatever hard-won knowledge I have. In the EZ, we generally don’t give a shit about restricting learning. It’s not like you couldn’t just buy one of us as a tutor if you were willing to spend enough time in the zone, fuck, that’s basically what you’ve done. Tell me what else you want so that you’ll tell my captors that I did a good job.”

“This is a naive case,” I said, pointing down at the diagram she’d drawn. “I’m going to need to know how to do more, and I’m going to have to understand fundamentals. As in, I could probably look at the stars and figure out how to do this one specific thing that you showed me —”

“You should probably set the bar lower than that,” said Doris.

“What I couldn’t do would be to make a portal to another plane, or even just make a larger or non-standard extradimensional space.” I was watching her. “I wouldn’t be able to step into the ethereal,” which required holding a shape or shapes in your head, so far as I knew, “I wouldn’t be able to make this permanent, there are lots of things. It’s like you showed me how to solve one specific math problem without actually telling me how to do math.”

“Alright,” said Doris. “I’ll run you through the very basics. I have to warn you that it’s maddening.”

“It’s okay,” I said. “I’m already a little insane.”

We spent four hours on it. It was productive, in part because we just didn’t wander off track at all. Sometimes when I was studying, I would get distracted or bored and want to switch to something else, and while I was relatively okay at reigning in that impulse, I probably lost a lot of time when I would start daydreaming, only to realize that I had been in the middle of reading a biography on one of these horrible people I was supposed to kill. It had been worse on Earth, where the internet and videogames were siren songs.

Doris … actually wasn’t so bad? She was a little rough around the edges, a bit acerbic, but she seemed intelligent, and she wasn’t a dick about things. One of the things that people said about Doris a lot was that she was actually a lot smarter than you would expect, and I was finding that true, not just in terms of star magic expertise, but just in the way that she seemed to think about things. If it had just been this one interaction, and I’d known nothing else about her, I wouldn’t have pegged her for a slaver or a cannibal.

She knew a fair amount about star magic, though it was also pretty clear that I was being given non-standard terminology, and there were definite limits to what she could tell me. She had learned star magic in the EZ, with nothing but books to go off of, and some of her techniques wouldn’t generalize; the EZ was small enough that the star mage Dorises had just baked in a lot of math that they’d never have to change.

Star magic was leveling up slowly.

“Untethering is the second hardest part,” said Doris. She had just finished explaining about the other planes, the eleven dimensions (which seemed like overkill) and how fucking hard it was to even get a return on a ping at them, let alone forging a connection with them. “It’s in high demand, but we can only barely do it, when the stars are right, and it’s better if you have a team, which we don’t do well with.”

“All you’d have to do is be the kind of person who works well in a team,” said Amaryllis. She had been in and out of bouts of concentration to integrate with her clones, which took ten minutes per. Not all of them were integrated every day, because she’d have basically a full work day of integration, and the clones were in cells anyhow, able to communicate facts, strategies, and ideas back to a central clone. It was still fairly time intensive.

“I know myself,” said Doris. “I know myself better than any person in the history of Aerb has known themselves.” She pulled up short. “I don’t have the fucking time for this. You understand they’ll shoot me if I don’t do my best?”

“And deprive themselves of a star mage?” I asked.

“No,” she replied. “I split before I came in here. If I fail, then they kill me and keep her. If I succeed, they keep me and kill her. Either way, they keep their star mage, this is just incentive for me to actually do the work. If they didn’t have a guard, they would torture me for information first.”

“I put up a barrier,” said Grak. “They could not listen.” It was a blunt dwarf way of saying it, but underneath that, he was a little cocky. I was happy about that. It was very possible that he was the best warder on the plane, and better in a lot of ways than any normal warder ever could be. It was about time he stuck out his chest a bit.

“Well, great,” said Doris, glancing at the guard, who hadn’t moved. “Now, we need to get through as much as we can,” said Doris. “You should know that we’ve been experimenting with planar portals, because as you might have noticed, we’re light on resources in the EZ. I was a research assistant in the city before I got reassigned here. I can tell you what I know, but it’s not much, because I’m from a divergent branch, never senior. Portals take so long that it requires untethering, which means an immense amount of work on the backend. Not only that, you have to make some predictions of where the stars will be, sometimes up to three months in advance, which is no mean feat. The planes themselves move, if slowly, so if you want something that lasts, you need to figure that out and compensate for it. And the problem gets worse for further planes.” She looked to Amaryllis. “How much time do we have left?”

“Thirty minutes,” said Amaryllis. “But you’re coming with us.”

Doris stared at her. “Coming with you?” she asked.

“We’re going into the city,” said Amaryllis. “You’re going to accompany us. Something happened at the facility you were working at. If you were there, you have information that could help us.”

Doris stopped for a moment, then looked bewildered. “What happened?” she asked. “Was there a problem?”

“They successfully connected to the elemental plane of blood,” said Raven. “Beyond that, we’re unsure.” She turned to Amaryllis. “Do you think bringing one with us under duress is a good idea?”

“The combat specialized ones are a different branch,” I said.

“I can ward her so she cannot split,” said Grak.

“No, you can’t,” said Doris. “A ward will either kill us or not work at all, full stop. We’re copies, all of us, we’re suffused with that magic.”

“Try splitting now,” said Grak.

Doris hesitated. “There would be one too many of me,” she said. “One of us would have to die, and we would both be working to make sure that it wasn’t us.”

Amaryllis held Sable out in front of her and popped out a gun. The guard didn’t move. “Just fucking do it.”

Doris didn’t hesitate this time, maybe because she was used to threats of violence, but of course, nothing happened.

“Good,” said Amaryllis. “There’s that tested, not that I had any doubt.”

“She’s renowned for her backstabbing,” said Raven. “She’s psychopathic.”

“I’m not,” said Doris.

“It’s going to be a problem,” said Raven, folding her arms.

“It’s kismet,” said Amaryllis, staring Raven down.

“Grak?” I asked. “Where do you stand on this?”

“There’s not much cost,” he replied. He switched to Groglir, nodding at me. “I can kill her with a thought.” He turned back to Raven. “Better to have a guide, better to have an expert.”

“I’m no expert,” said Doris. “We fork. I have fewer years than others, there’s a reason that I was an assistant instead of part of the research group. And I don’t want to go.”

“I don’t think we really give a shit,” I told her. “Sorry.”

“I hope you realize that this makes us slaveholders,” said Raven.

“Not really,” I said. “I mean, temporary slaveholders, but — what, it becomes worse to take an unwilling technical and area expert with you when they’re a slave? It’s unwilling either way, the ‘slave’ part is semantics.” I felt like I had never said the word ‘slave’ so many times in my life. “Kidnappers, maybe. I don’t feel great about it, obviously, but you know that we can’t save the Dorises from each other, not in the long-term. So unless there’s a practical reason that we can’t take her with us, then we’ll take her with us unless the Blues can provide some kind of substitute.”

Star Doris didn’t seem happy about that, not in the slightest, but she didn’t have much of a choice in the matter.

“So,” I said as we walked down the ‘road’ to the city of Dorisopolis. If you hadn’t been paying attention, it might surprise you to know that city planning in the EZ was, not to put too fine a point on it, essentially non-existent. “You were saying about how you know yourself better than anyone?”

“That’s right,” said Star Doris. She was taking this with relative aplomb, but I had to imagine that she’d been through worse than being taken by strangers. I did wonder about how many times she’d forked, and how different she was from the others. If you were omniscient, you could probably make a map of the different camps or do some color data visualization, but there would be no way to get the information, and the population of the EZ was incredibly unstable. Tattoo and scar tracking might work, I supposed.

“So tell us,” said Amaryllis. “Tell us why it’s impossible to get along with yourself.”

“We’ve never found a way to make equipment permanent,” said Star Doris. “If we make a copy, that copy has twenty-four hours with all the same things, except you only rarely know if you’re the copy or not.” She was talking like she was trying to keep from clenching her teeth. “The very first time we split, we found out the hard way that one of us had our clothes, money, books, and everything else, and the other was naked. She had everything, we had nothing, and she wouldn’t share.”

“Meaning that in the same position, you wouldn’t have shared,” said Amaryllis.

“We didn’t have the best life growing up,” said Star Doris. “We know what the outside world thinks of us, more or less, we know that some of us get captured and interrogated every now and then, or that we just talk in exchange for whatever scraps they’ll throw our way. You probably read something about me before you came in. I was used to not having much. When that’s your life, your instinct isn’t to share, to lift someone else up at your own expense. But you have to understand that it didn’t start like this, it built up over years. Back at the beginning, we didn’t think of the copies as people. And we didn’t know we were excluded until well into it.”

“The only reason that she betrays you is that you betray her,” said Amaryllis. “You’re the same person right now. Just agree on outcomes.”

“I don’t,” said Star Doris. “I can’t. I’m a survivor. I survived because I was willing to kill. The number of dead Dorises has to number in the billions by this point. I’ve stabbed her in the back so many fucking times that I would never believe she wouldn’t do the same to me. And we use that. We make copies and pit them against each other, because we know they can’t cooperate, and wouldn’t be able to even if we were dumb enough to let them.”

“It’s survival of the fittest,” I said. “If you extend a helping hand, you get shanked, and the shankers rule the world.”

“Against them, maybe I could understand it,” said Amaryllis. “But we’re not talking about them, we’re talking about you. If you decided right now that you would cooperate with your copy, you could. There’s nothing preventing it.”

“A lifetime of knowing and seeing otherwise,” said Raven. “A theory of self that encourages this. Scarcity of resources and the knowledge that their way of life can’t continue unless they’re willing to exploit and enslave.”

“I hardly think this society requires slavery, torture, and way, way too many brutal murders,” I said. I was positive that someone had laid out an ideal Doris society, and vaguely remembered reading about one. Maybe it had been Amaryllis, in one of those occasional moods she got into where she wanted to talk at me rather than to me.

“We would run out of food,” said Doris. “The only thing keeping us all fed is that we can get something from nothing. If you’re rich or lucky, you can eat the things that feed on our bodies instead, but we have very little in the way of crops, and those only go to the Dorises that sit at the top of the heap. We’ve asked for aid from the Empire, but they don’t have the resources, and they don’t trust us to agree to their terms.”

“Are you actually trying to convince us?” I asked. “I mean, I know things in the EZ are bad, but I wouldn’t have thought that you would defend them.”

“She was literally just talking about how she would stab someone in the back if they offered a helping hand,” said Amaryllis. “She has every incentive to get us to reach out to her with that helping hand.”

“Did you learn nothing from Anglecynn?” asked Raven.

Amaryllis went silent for a moment. “You think that this is undue cynicism?” Raven shrugged, not providing more of a challenge. Amaryllis was keeping her eyes on Raven, and seemed to be chewing that over, her anger and distrust of the Dorises momentarily forgotten. “Shit.”

“Shit?” I asked.

“I was talking to you about paths,” she said. “Paths that we might have gone down? Points of no return?”

I finally caught up to what Amaryllis must have been thinking, which was that if there had ever been a social solution in Anglecynn, we had mostly missed it, and if the Doris EZ was similar, then the thing that would guarantee we went down the combat path would be treating the Dorises how you’d assume they should be treated, just based on what you heard about them.

“I think these are different situations,” I said. “And I don’t think that one was meant to inform the other.”

“You’ve lost me,” said Star Doris.

“Good,” I replied. I turned to her. “What do you think it would take to turn this EZ into a functional nation?” I asked.

She seemed to give that some thought. “Absolute enforcement,” said Star Doris. “Strict control from the top, strict hierarchy of function, mechanisms for compliance, rule of law. We have none of those right now.”

“Dorises won’t cooperate unless they’re forced to,” said Amaryllis.

“But we will cooperate,” said Star Doris.

“You would need panopticon surveillance,” said Amaryllis. “You would need someone willing to cut off your fingers the moment you so much as gestured toward stepping out of line.”

That added some instant tension to the conversation. I couldn’t think about someone cutting off fingers without thinking of Bethel, and no one else in the group could either. That, and the phrase ‘panopticon surveillance’, was enough for Amaryllis’ suggestion to be clear. I couldn’t tell whether or not she meant it, or if it was just her way of spitting on the idea. From an implementation standpoint … well, there were hurdles, the biggest being Bethel herself (pun not intended).

“It would be evil,” said Raven.

“It would work,” replied Star Doris. “I wouldn’t sign up for it, but it would work. We’d still have to kill our copies for food and water, and they’d still be a resource, but we would be functional. And if there were a Doris who was unambiguously our leader, we would be able to deal with the outside world.”

“You would backstab the outside world,” said Amaryllis.

“Everyone says that, but it’s exaggerated. Turnover is high in the Republic,” said Star Doris. “Uncertainty is high. Backstabbing is a short-term play, but if you don’t play in the short term, you get crushed by those who do. It’s not our fault. The system is set up against us.” She snorted at Amaryllis. “You think we’re dumb, Everyone does. You’d think talking to me for half an hour would disabuse you of that notion. I have my deficiencies, I won’t argue that, but I’m not dumb.”

Just self-sabotaging, short-sighted, and distrustful. “People say that about you a lot,” I said. “They’re surprised that you’re smart. So you’ve got that going for you, which is nice.”

“If your intelligence can’t solve problems, then it’s not intelligence,” said Amaryllis, but she had cooled off a bit, and there wasn’t venom. “You’re stupid in a very specific way. But to put the EZ under an authoritarian regime … I can’t see that being the answer.”

I nodded. Amaryllis was talking narrative now, and while that narrative was definitely something I could have seen a party doing over the course of a D&D campaign, it wasn’t the kind of solution you would intentionally write to be the good one. It was more a ‘whoops, I guess facsism is good when we do it’ kind of thing. “So we just teach a Doris to work together with herself, or work in the long-term, and once that starts working, the rest join her. It’s a society reorganization quest, but you only have to fix one person.”

“People have tried,” said Star Doris. “Not that I care if you fail, but people have tried. It’s usually not hard to capture a Doris at the border, if you have magic and entad support. Soul magic doesn’t work on us, but they’ve done everything short of that.”

I’d known that we couldn’t soulfuck her: Uniquities had let us in on that one, though they didn’t know that we were planning to go into the zone. But as Doris had pointed out, soulfucking wasn’t the only way to change what was in someone’s soul, it was just the fastest and easiest, so long as you had a competent soul mage. I almost wanted to ask Grak whether, since they were completely suffused with clonal magic, he would be able to make some ward that was capable of changing her, but I figured if that was at all within his abilities, he would probably be working on the problem.

“I don’t understand why you’re here,” said Star Doris. “I don’t understand what you want. I can work with you better if I know your goals.”

“You’re confused about all the idle talk about fixing the EZ?” I asked. She gave me a curt nod. Her lips were twisted into a puckered frown. “Consider us — is ‘Good Samaritan’ a thing?” I asked.

“It’s now considered offensive,” said Raven.

“Uh,” I said, trying to work that out. In the original, the good Samaritan was notable because he was expected to be evil, or at least an enemy. Maybe on Aerb the phrase held the implication that people from Samaria were evil. “Is there a non-offensive replacement?” I asked.

“Helpmate would do fine,” said Amaryllis. She looked over at Star Doris. “We’re helpmates.” She gave a glance at me, and lifted her hand, signing quickly in Gimb. “Samaritan was a type of orc.”

I thought about that for a bit, and still didn’t really get it, maybe because I didn’t remember the parable right, but we were getting close to the city, and I wanted to be focusing more on what was going on around us, just in case there was an ambush waiting.

Our time in the city of Dorisopolis was approaching.

Where the Streets Run Red

“So what’s the murders per capita in this shithole?” asked Arthur, giving me a goofy grin.

“Uh, pretty low,” I said. “If you’re comparing it to real life, it would be staggeringly low.”

He frowned at me. “The way it was described to us, it was supposed to be a place where the gutters ran red with blood,” he said. “Drow blood, but still.”

“This is some worldbuilding thing, isn’t it?” asked Reimer. He set down his pencil. “Go on, do your rant.”

“Can I use my phone while you go through this?” asked Craig. His hand was already on it.

“Uh, may you,” I replied. “And no. I’m not going to give some boring TED talk about it, it’s just a function of what’s in the books.”

“I want to hear,” said Maddie.

“Veto,” said Craig.

“If you don’t want to explain it, don’t explain it,” said Reimer. “But that’s bait, it’s obvious bait, so if you don’t want to explain it, don’t say things like ‘it’s just a function of what’s in the books’, like you’re fucking Sherlock Holmes about to explain his masterstroke. Emphasis on stroke.”

“There’s a limit on how high a death rate can be while still sustaining a functional economy,” I said. “And even if you’re not thinking about the economy, then you at least have to be thinking about replacement rates. If you look at historic cities with really high death rates, I’m about ninety percent sure that you’d be looking at a few different types of scenarios, stuff like war or disease, or brief periods of brutal regimes. Some of those examples you’d be looking at would be with replacement population flooding in from somewhere else, growth from immigrants offsetting murders. But those don’t apply to a drow city, because where would more drow be coming from? Nowhere, the city is self-contained.”

Craig raised his hand. “Is this going to be on the test?”

“I’m taking this as scene setting,” said Arthur, frowning a bit.

“The question was how high the murders per capita were,” I said. “I’m just explaining things that your characters are seeing, or figuring out, or learning with an Investigation check.”

“There are other explanations,” said Tiff. She was slouched in her chair a bit, and had been doodling in her notebook. The no phones rule helped a lot with people being distracted, but you still eventually got stuff like dice stacking, doodling, and browsing rulebooks when people weren’t into the session. For whatever reason, Tiff wasn’t into it, but we had enough people that it wasn’t a huge deal.

“Go ahead,” I said, after waiting a second for her.

She sat up a bit. “Your question is death rate against growth rate,” she said. “First thing you could do is just make all of the drow die from murder, instead of … heart disease, or whatever the current top killer is. Second thing you could do is make growth really, really high. Drow matrons pump out a lot of kids, then most of them die before reproducing.”

“The first works, but it’s not high enough,” I said. “I ran the numbers. Second is really not like the drow.”

“And when have you ever hewed to the books?” asked Tiff.

“Should be hewn,” said Arthur.

“If I wanted a species that didn’t feel like drow, then I would just make a new species,” I said. “But if you take drow and make them ultrafast breeders just to try to justify how many deaths they have … it doesn’t work. The truth is, there’s no way for a city to be at the appropriate level of violence and murder without special circumstances or a continual influx of population that’s somehow happening in spite of a ludicrously high murder rate.”

It was one of those awkward arguments, the kind that I didn’t like when I looked back on it, but which had passed easily enough. No one had really been mad at each other, but it had been uncomfortable, and even running it over in my head afterward, I didn’t know quite how I could have fixed it.

Dorisopolis didn’t have a formal name, but that was what everyone called it. The Republic of Doris Finch was in some respects a failed state, but in other respects was just a bunch of customs and understandings without a formal government at all. A better analogy might have been a collection of gangs, though that wasn’t quite right either, because the unique nature of her power meant that a new gang could spring up within a matter of minutes. In a lot of ways, it was unlike any other place on Aerb, and definitely unlike any place on Earth.

There were elements of Aerb that I would have argued were grimdark, but we’d had a long D&D session back on Earth arguing the definition of that term, and a lot of it was about the tone of the writing and where it put focus, rather than any particular facts about the setting. If I was looking at Aerb in general, I might be tempted to call it grimdark, because their motorcycles ran on souls, nine thousand hells, and the looming threat of the exclusionary principle coming to crush cities and strip out industries. But in terms of my actual adventure, I wasn’t so sure.

If that book the Dungeon Master had shown me, Worth the Candle by Juniper Smith, was written in my authentic voice, I had to believe I wouldn’t have just glossed over all the mundane stuff. The book of my adventures on Aerb would have had some grim and dark stuff, but it wouldn’t have been only that, not unless you were willing to cut out playing Ranks with Grak, or Amaryllis introducing me to rock climbing, or the long conversation that Fenn and I had about why anyone would voluntarily use the awesome power of the internet to watch some stranger play a videogame (and yeah, it would have taken twenty pages and then abruptly ended with a sex scene, but I would have included it all the same). My actual experience of Aerb had its moments of grimdarkness, but on the whole? When I went into any major metropolitan area, I never got the sense that people were trudging along, burdened by the knowledge that this was a world in decline. They seemed like people. Maybe some of them were just coping, and to be fair, my exposure to ‘normal people’ was low, but it seemed like most of the problems were far away, easy to forget about if you wanted to.

But this is all by way of saying that the DFEZ was way past grimdark, and Dorisopolis was the worst of it. It was more mortal suffering than had existed in any actual city on Earth, made possible only because these bodies came cheap, and were one of the only reliable resources in the place. Doris Finch had her personal problems, and that meant every single citizen of the city had those same personal problems, like you took the least trustworthy, most cutthroat person in New York City and then multiplied them to blanket Manhattan. It was insanity, and we were walking through it.

The buildings were all magestone, built tall, but without any kind of plan in place, and a few of them had tipped or been collapsed, leaving them leaning sideways. Steel magic made ugly buildings, unless you were trying hard or willing to put in work to make a facade, and neither of those were the case in Dorisopolis. I was a little bit leery of even going into the city, not just because of the proliferation of void weapons and how many spots there would be to take pot shots at us, but because there was a very real possibility that one of those buildings would collapse. You could do that kind of work with star magic, given enough time and paint.

There didn’t seem to be much in the way of basic sanitation, and there were so many corpses all around that in a few places they formed impromptu gardens, with all the specialized fauna that had taken hold in the EZ to feast on the bounty. Where people needed to walk, the place wasn’t quite clear of bodies: instead, it was flattened muck, muck which must have been corpses at some point, if I had my guess. I saw vermin as well, featherless birds and rats with shells, or close enough that I wasn’t going to quibble on taxonomy.

“It’s better further in,” said Star Doris. “Downtown, there’s enough entad support to keep things clean.” It almost sounded like an apology. I’d issued a few apologies like that, when people came over and saw how messy my room was. This was obviously different, and on an entirely different magnitude, but it was still surprising to me, because it was an admission that this was, in some way, her fault.

To be honest, I was a bit worried about the possibilities of disease. The Dorises were a monoculture, which made them ripe for it, and with the combination of poor sanitation and rampant cannibalism, it was a breeding ground for pathogens. The two big things keeping that in check were isolation and pustule magic. Barely any people came into the zone, and obviously no one left it, but it was my understanding that even something like a mild cold could rip through the Dorises. Pustule magic was the other big check, and had supposedly been learned under extreme crunch by a Doris when someone had unleashed a plague on them. Normal pustule mages weren’t much good at dealing with diseases or maladies on other people, but the normal rules got a little fuzzy when you were talking about clones, and a Pustule Doris could strip out (or add in) illnesses from one of the others, which was one of the ways that the Dorises attempted to maintain control over each other.

There were very few diseases that would have been more than a mild inconvenience for me, given all the resources at our disposal, so a lot of my worry was just my regular human brain not having updated to the sheer breadth and depth of resources that I had available to me, with a tiny sliver left over for how worried I actually should have been about rare or magical viruses that the population of Dorises was harboring.

We saw a lot of them, coming in, and with the Crown of Eyes, I was fully aware of the closer ones that I might not have noticed with my normal senses or vibration magic. Many of them were watching us, but more were simply going about their business, which largely seemed to consist of manual labor of one kind or the other. There was a lot that the Dorises didn’t have, in part because the EZ had been wrecked a long time ago. The only things left in it were those that they had no use for, or which could survive in their direct possession. They made up for this, in part, by harvesting themselves, and quite a bit of their work was simply in turning a human body into something that would be useful. This included skinning and tanning, making tools from bone, rendering fats for oils, and using hair for textiles. A lot of those things, a human body wasn’t really good for, but you work with what you have, I guess. I kept expecting to see the Dorises engaged in some kind of art, either its production or consumption, but I only saw a single painting in any of the homes, and that had clearly been done in the shades of what could be extracted from a human.

The smell, as you might imagine, was atrocious. The Dorises didn’t have plumbing, which meant that they were at the mercy of the rain in order to gather water in steel mage cisterns. Even if a thunderstorm had come, I was sure that it wouldn’t be enough to wash everything away, not when there was a distinct lack of gutters, and obviously no functional stormwater system set up. I had read that the Empire of Common Cause had briefly engaged in a campaign of water deprivation, accomplished by a relatively small handful of water mages, but all it had done was to make the Dorises spawn and kill clones in order to extract water from their own bodies, and the campaign was stopped, having done little in the way of bringing the Dorises to heel.

“How much further?” asked Amaryllis.

“A half mile,” said Star Doris. “At that point we’ll be all the way downtown. That’s where the research building you want is.” We’d gotten direction from the Blues, but they were kind of crap, and Dorisopolis wasn’t very well laid out. “And from there … I’d like to request permission to split off a copy.”

“A copy?” I asked. “Why?”

“One to stay with you, one to leave,” said Star Doris. “If it’s dangerous, then I might die, and I don’t want to die. You only need one of me.”

“From your perspective, it gives you a fifty percent chance,” said Amaryllis. “A better person would ask to split off a clone in order to have their essential self perpetuate. But if we let you make a clone, they won’t be going willingly, they’ll want to be the one who goes free. And at some point, we’re going to have to say no to this idiotic idea that we should let you make more of yourself in order to avoid your fate.”

“The question is when it’s proper to stop her,” said Raven.

“We can give her one copy,” I said. “She doesn’t believe in the value of a unique individual continuing on, but I do.” I looked at Star Doris. “Your last clone was when you split before coming in to teach me star magic?” I asked. That clone was now dead: we’d done nothing to stop the Dorises from their barbarism, though we had debated it.

Star Doris nodded.

“And before that?” I asked.

“Copies that have lived?” she asked. “Two, for slave trades, within the last month. I don’t split often. The less star mages, the better.”

“Then you have a month of divergence,” I said, frowning a bit. “I guess I place some value on that, enough to deal with the inconvenience and problems it might bring.”

“We don’t all subscribe to your ideas,” said Grak. I looked over at him, and saw he was frowning. “You pay no attention to the thread of consciousness.”

That threw me for a bit of a loop. “Uh,” I said. “You think that snipping that thread is … wrong?”

He nodded. “It doesn’t matter what I think, I know. But I thought I should let you know, as you are speaking for me.”

“Okay,” I said. That gave me pause. It wasn’t a conversation that I’d ever had with Grak. I immediately wanted to launch into a debate with him, but now was not the time and place. Did he think that going to sleep was evil, because it severed the thread of consciousness? Probably not. I would ask later. “Thank you for the correction, I just …” I trailed off. I hadn’t known. How did he contextualize things like Amaryllis’ clones, or unicorn timelines, or the Lost Year of the revision mages? “Do you suggest something else?”

“No,” he said. “We will protect her. And to honor her request would show charity, even if she is making the request for a stupid reason.”

The streets became clean, not little by little, but all at once. There was some kind of entad at work, because it was unnaturally clean, the filth and grime of human bodies completely eliminated as we walked between one set of buildings and the other. The smells cleared up in an instant, and the Doris residue, where it had clung to our feet or touched our armor, was instantly wiped away. But this, too, was a mark of the insanity of this place, because the Dorises could freely copy entads, so long as they worked around the twenty-four hour refresh. Given that they maintained a stock of void rifles from what must have been only one or two that had made their way across the border, it didn’t seem like anything would have prevented them from spreading the effect across the whole EZ, except that if you had something, and deprived others of it, that was often to your advantage.

My opinion of the Dorises lowered a bit. It felt so good to be in a place that was supernaturally clean, especially after everything that we’d just been through.

“You could shit in your armor here,” said Star Doris. “The effect would wipe it away.”

“It feels good,” said Raven, breathing a little deeper. I waited for someone to make the obvious joke and ask if she’d just shit in her armor, but to my immense disappointment, no one did. I missed Fenn.

“What is it?” asked Amaryllis. “Entad, naturally, but what is it?”

“Like I have any fucking idea?” asked Star Doris. “The higher Blues control them. Some day, one of those bitches is going to make a copy at the wrong time and this whole scheme is going to come tumbling down.”

“They’re relatively stable though?” asked Amaryllis. “They’re the dominant tribe because they were capable of working together?”

“They’re well-fed,” said Star Doris. “Easier to think when you’re not going on a few years straight of eating your own warm flesh. Easier to win an exchange if you’re not so worried about losing absolutely everything you have, which is more or less just the stuff on your back. But the ruling class isn’t stable, no, there’s turnover all the time. It takes too many people to run their schemes, too many slaves, too many managers, and their systems of control only work so well. Besides that, they’re too greedy, always pushing things so that those at the bottom are kept just on the knife edge of rebellion. It doesn’t take much when any one of us can become an army in a minute or less. Once that happens, it’s copies on copies. I’ve been in one of those, and I don’t want to be in another.”

“It’s probably one of the reasons that they starve you as much as they can,” I said. “The more you have to live off your own flesh, the less you eat, which means the weaker you are, which means the easier you are to overpower.”

“That’s probably what they’re thinking, yes,” replied Star Doris. She looked at us. “Are we going through the market or diverting around?”

The ‘roads’ in Dorisopolis weren’t very wide, but the one ahead of us was an exception, and it was filled with stalls. Dorises were walking in among those stalls, bartering with Dorises, because Dorisopolis couldn’t sustain a currency with how simple it was to counterfeit, and because Dorises didn’t trust enough to trade IOUs or other one-time-use tickets. On the airship ride over, Amaryllis had tried to figure out a monetary scheme that would work when everyone could counterfeit things at will, and she came up with a few, but nothing that was elegant. It would all have been enormously complicated by the fact that it was easy for Dorises to impersonate each other, and that a single Doris could split in two, which you’d have to figure out some way of accounting for in your system of debits and credits.

Instead, it was just trade, items for items. It was pretty much a guarantee that Dorises were only trading away ‘fake’ goods, those that would melt away to nothing after the twenty-four hour period was up, but that didn’t matter all that much, because the actual process of duplication was laborious (create a Doris, kill her, take her stuff, repeat), and barter was a way of getting the things you needed without having to go through the trouble. It made sense that the bodies were piling up as much as they were. I occasionally saw Dorises going off together; there was trade of services as well, as some of the Dorises were specialized.

“We’re going through the market,” said Amaryllis. “They should be able to see that if we get mobbed, we’ll kill them.”

“Suit yourself,” said Star Doris, and she began moving forward.

The Dorises were stopping what they were doing and staring at us. They moved to the sides to let us pass with a healthy distance between us, but I could see through their eyes, and there were a hell of a lot of eyes in a fifty foot radius around us. For all the cleanliness of this section of Dorisopolis, and the way the Dorises had clean faces and unstained clothes, there was still something wild about them, maybe the way they were all so clearly wearing clothes that were at least partially made from their own bodies, or the hollow look that most of them had. Some of them were slaves, I knew.

Aside from all our armor and the way we bristled with weapons, we were juicy targets. It was imperial policy that no one go into the EZ with unbound entads, specifically because the Dorises could copy them, but looking at us and how many we had, the Dorises might think that we were violating that rule (which we were). Even if we weren’t, they might have been thinking that we would make for hostages they could ransom off, either to other Dorises or to the outside world. If we were here, then maybe we had skills that they could use for the low cost of making us into slaves. Rumor was that they didn’t often take non-Doris slaves, a response to how hard the hammer had been brought down on them in times past, but that was suspect.

I was on edge, as I’d been since we’d stepped foot into the EZ. The Dorises weren’t suicidal, and they had horrible morale, breaking as soon as they thought the tide had shifted, but in theory, they could multiply so fast that they could smother you in bodies.

I knew something was about to go wrong when I was suddenly able to see with a lot more eyes. Somewhere in the buildings above us, there was a Doris multiplying at a very rapid rate, and I could see through her eyes that she had a void rifle.

“Void rifles, above us, seek cover,” I said quickly.

I hadn’t expected it to happen as fast as it did. Almost from the moment it became clear to the Dorises around us that someone was going to attack, it was open season. Dorises started multiplying, and they began to crowd in around us. I had my sword drawn in an instant, but the Dorises were pressing up against me, doubling to close the gap rather than really moving. They couldn’t multiply within Grak’s ward, but so many of them were multiplying that it was a press of bodies either way. I felt hands on me, grabbing at me, not trying to hurt me, just trying to take my things from me. The Crown of Eyes was yanked from my head, and the chaotic sensory experience of seeing through the eyes of everyone in a packed crowd ended in an instant.

It was around that time we started being fired on from above. The sound of the void weapons was almost inaudible over the sound of the screaming around us, but I knew where they were, and the distinctive sound of discharge was something I’d been tuning my hearing for. I was very cognizant of the fact that a single lucky shot would be enough to end my life. Not having many other options, I began pushing myself up, trying to get on top of the Dorises around me, away from their grasping hands. With a pang of regret, I switched my armor over to its acid elemental mode. There were screams not long after that, as it began burning away whatever Dorises I was touching. I was tempted to change into an animal to get away, but that would have left my gear behind.

The problem wasn’t the Dorises next to me, it was the others, who were creating ever more clones that were adding to the mass of humanity. They were literally trying to drown us in bodies, or at least hoping to weaken us, and the Dorises that were next to us were now trying to escape, but couldn’t because of how much force the crowd was exerting.

All the while, there was still the sound of void rifles firing from above us, and now, mixed in with it, the much louder sound of regular ballistics.

Almost at once, the Dorises that I’d been climbing on disappeared beneath my feet, and I landed back down on the ground, next to the Crown of Eyes, which I snatched up while I turned around to see what the fuck was going on. Before I could figure it out, we were moving, me, Amaryllis, Grak, and Raven, with a lone Doris following us, dragged along, as the others stayed well back. I almost cut her down before realizing that it was Star Doris.

We made it into the mouth of one of the big buildings, leaving the market behind us. The sound of void rifles and gunfire stopped, but there was still screaming from the Dorises, howls of pain and cries of anguish. The press of Dorises had disappeared around us, but at the boundary were those who had been cleanly sliced through, removing hands, arms, legs, and faces. As I listened, the screams were slowly cut off, one by one, and I knew that the healthy Dorises were putting the injured ones out of their misery (not out of empathy, but just to shut them up).

“Good work,” I said to Grak.

“It could have been faster,” said Grak. His hair was mussed, but otherwise he looked fine. “I was trying to figure out how to save this one.”

“Is everyone okay?” asked Amaryllis. “I got scratched, but nothing serious.” Wherever it had been, it was now healed.

“Fine,” said Raven. “Someone was burning bones.” I had forgotten until she said it that she got a bonus from that.

“What was that?” asked Star Doris, looking at Grak.

“A ward,” said Grak.

“Who are you people?” asked Star Doris.

“The Chosen People of the One True God,” said Amaryllis. She watched Star Doris’s face. “That’s not a joke.”

“There,” said Grak. “I’ve put up a shell, six feet from me. If a Doris passes it, they will die. That includes you. Stay with me.”

“That’s impossible,” said Star Doris.

“You can test it, if you’d like,” said Amaryllis. “Tip of your pinky is the traditional method. We have healing on hand.”

“I believe you,” said Star Doris. “But it’s impossible.”

“Just very hard,” said Grak, but he didn’t quite put his heart into it, because some things he could do might literally be impossible for anyone else, same as for me.

“We should get moving,” I said. “There are lots of Dorises around, and we should make a beeline for the star magic facility. It’s not far.”

“I want the copy made now,” said Star Doris, swallowing hard. “If you’re still thinking that you’ll let me.”

“Sure,” I said. “Grak?”

He twitched his mouth. “Now, just one. Don’t leave my radius.”

Star Doris blurred slightly, and another of her appeared. They looked at each other with hostility, but didn’t attack, which I’d worried they might. “Which one?” they asked in unison.

“That one goes,” I said, nodding at the one on my left. “That one stays.”

I really, honestly hadn’t thought that she would do it, but the one I had said would stay pulled a knife and made to attack the other, who obviously knew that this was coming. I was faster than her, though, and I laid my hands on both of them, stopping them in place with still magic.

“So what was the plan?” I asked. “You wanted to kill her so that we would let you make a new clone? And I thought you were a slave, where did you get the knife?”

“She picked it up just after the melee,” said Amaryllis. “It might have been the only real knife on the block.”

I turned to her. “You saw that?”

“I did,” she said. “What was she going to do, stab us?”

I cringed. If I really bought into narrative theory, which I didn’t, I would have thought that it was a one hundred percent guarantee that Amaryllis would get stabbed by Doris Finch. “Look,” I said, turning to the Dorises. “This was a fucking dumb plan. It was one that you hatched knowing that you would have to face down your other self. And if that’s the case, then that means you were willing to risk this fuckery because you know something about what we’re walking into.”

“Or she’s just terrible,” said Amaryllis.

“Could be,” I said. I looked at the two Star Dorises, who I was allowing just enough movement so they could breathe. It was pretty much at the limits of my ability to keep both of them from moving, and they were only ordinary women. “What do you know about what we’re going to find, if you ever do take us to the facility?”

“Death,” said one Star Doris, the one that had pulled the knife and was destined to come with us. “It’s been brewing there for months. They opened a portal to the elemental plane of blood, and found that we could go through it, breaking the exclusion.”

“She would say anything not to go,” said the other Star Doris. “We’ve never been there. We don’t know anything.”

“You’re claiming that you can break exclusion through sufficiently powerful star magic?” asked Raven. “If that were possible, we would know.”

“It’s possible,” said the first Doris. “But that’s not the problem, the problem is that we sent out hemonauts, lots of them. We had a colony there —”

“All lies,” said the other Doris.

“Shut the fuck up,” said the first Doris. “That’s not going to work.”

“You know that it’s not a ploy,” said the other Doris.

“Alright,” I said. “You, no talking.” I amped up the still magic and deprived the denier of her voice. “You were talking about a colony of hemonauts.”

“I don’t know how many, I wasn’t important, and we keep information from ourselves as much as we can. The portal was only big enough for one Doris at a time, with lots of equipment in place, bloodlocks and quarantines. And then a Doris came back different, and the bloodlocks and quarantine were mostly destroyed, leaving the portal open.” She took a breath. I wasn’t letting her move much, but her eyes turned to me, pleading. “It killed hundreds, thousands of us, and the Blues kept trying to push more people against it, but that was just making it worse.”

“Is it a threat to the EZ?” asked Amaryllis.

Doris hesitated, then nodded. “Maybe not today, or next week, but eventually what’s in there will venture out.”

“Okay,” I said. “Other one then.” I silenced the first Doris and let the other one talk. “How much of that was lies?”

“We worked there,” she said. “I can draw you a clear map, we’re not far. Other than that, we knew nothing, we were doing low level work, if any of what she said were possible, we wouldn’t have known it.”

“You’re lying,” said Amaryllis.

“How can you tell?” I asked.

“She’s just not that good of a liar,” said Amaryllis. “She was hiding something back at the camp, this is it. I’ll admit telling is easier when you can compare truth and lies side by side. We’ll keep her, let the other go. Give a reward for good behavior, and a punishment for bad.”

“That’s not how she’ll see it,” said Raven. She was sick of the Dorises already, I was pretty sure, not just how they were, but how we were dealing with them.

“Eh, just do it,” I said. “Either way, whichever one we keep, we’ll be doing her a disservice. Neither want to go with us, not that anyone sane would want to.”

“Before we let her go, we should get a location from her,” said Amaryllis. “Thoughts on ways to compel truth before she goes?”

“A single remotely revocable ward should do,” said Grak. It wasn’t something used often, and it was a bit difficult, but a warder could collapse their ward from a distance. We could trap the Doris and then keep her trapped, until we got to the facility. If she lied, she wouldn’t be let out.

I nodded. “Alright,” I said. “Then Star Doris A comes with us, and Star Doris B stays here,” I said. I was still using my hands to hold them in place, but I nodded at them. “If Star Doris B tells the truth, then Grak drops the ward when we get there. If she doesn’t,” I hesitated and turned to Grak. “Set duration for … twenty-four hours?”

“It’s a bit cruel,” he said. “It only needs to be enough to make her obey.”

“If the intent is to make her obey, then make it as harsh as possible,” said Amaryllis. “That way she won’t betray us, and we don’t have to worry. It’s not cruel if it doesn’t come to pass. Why make it into a choice for her, if we’re doing coercion?”

“Some might say that using coercion is the problem,” said Raven.

“Grak?” I asked. “What do you feel is appropriate?”

“Twelve,” he said. “If we’re ambushed and killed before we get there, she would suffer punishment for cooperation.”

“Sure,” I said with a nod. “And she’s really got very little reason to lie in the first place.”

With that, I let go of Star Doris A, and we put her in position to have a full-body ward. She protested, because she was at risk from the other Dorises, but moving to a secondary location just because she hadn’t been able to stop herself from double-crossing us… Well, there were limits to our charity. She told us in detail everything that we wanted to know, the threat of confinement apparently enough.

We set off with Star Doris B, ready to set ourselves against whatever terrible thing had escaped from the elemental plane of blood.

Open Veins

As it turned out, Star Doris had been telling the truth, and we weren’t far from where the blood mages had been doing their thing. Any normal member polity of the Empire of Common Cause would have mandated that high-level research and engineering take place far from a center of population, and this wasn’t just a matter of common sense, it was enshrined in law as the Riddle Acts, just in case someone was dumb enough to think that surely an exclusion couldn’t happen to them, or that the risk of an exclusion was worth it. There was maybe some way to justify it, and it was pretty common for people to conflate ‘calamity that was concurrent with exclusion’ and ‘the actual action of exclusion’, but it was still sensible. For the Dorises, the math was a bit different: their zone wasn’t terribly big, all things considered, and if there were some calamity, it was fairly likely to get them all. Beyond that, they needed colocation because that was the only realistic way to keep everything secure and contained, to the extent that was even possible. Obviously no one went into a big research or engineering project thinking that it was going to result in some degenerate feedback loop or an insane person with a godlike power … but still, it spoke to a lack of caution that most people in the Empire would find startling, until they heard that it was Doris Finch doing it, at which point calls would go up for something to be done.

It was a big building, made of magestone as almost everything in the zone was, but it was obvious that more care and attention had gone into it than almost any other building around us. The walls were smooth, and while it certainly wasn’t artful, it was clear that this building was built to last, by someone who either took pride in their work, or more likely, had been working like their life depended on it. It was squat and ugly, but it almost looked like deliberate ugliness, and after some of what we’d seen in the EZ, my standards were a lot lower.

There were no guards. Instead, there was a general notice, written directly onto the doors, which proclaimed the facility fully locked, stripped of valuables, and with death awaiting anyone who entered. It was written on the doors because if it had been written on parchment, that parchment would have been stolen. As I read the sign, I was a bit disheartened by how much of it was lies. I knew that the Dorises didn’t trust each other, but I hadn’t considered how much signage would be watered down when everyone would think that it was just a ploy.

“I released the other,” said Grak.

“Good,” nodded Amaryllis. She turned to look at Star Doris. “How do we get in?” she asked.

“Like I have any idea?” she asked. “Through those doors.” The doors were big and thick, made of metal, which the Dorises didn’t normally have in abundant supply. The hinges were huge, thick things as well, set into the door so that you’d have a hell of a time removing them.

“All entrances are sealed off?” asked Amaryllis. “This is the least defensible?”

“Like I said,” replied Star Doris. “I don’t fucking know. I used to work here, but I wasn’t casing the place. I came in through that door every day, did my work, usually away from anything important, and then I went back to my home. One day I came to work, and that message was there. No one had done me the courtesy of letting me know about what happened, I had to find out from the other Dorises later on.”

“So what you told us might have been lies,” I said. “Good to know.”

“Anything that I was there for, that’s true,” said Star Doris. “Anything that I got secondhand, maybe it would be lies, but I’m not a total bitch. I don’t usually lie for fun. This was from a Doris that I’d worked alongside, a close clone of mine. We don’t have bonds, but if it costs nothing, we’ll talk, and if there’s a cost, we’ll make a trade.”

“Alright,” I said with a sigh. I very nearly turned to Grak and asked him to make a steel ward that would let us drill through, but on second thought, I walked over to the door, grabbed the large handle, and hefted it open. It swung freely. “Fucking Dorises,” I said, shaking my head.

The interior was poorly lit by some slit windows high up on the outside. The Dorises didn’t have souls per se, which meant no soul power, and even if they did have souls, I wasn’t sure they had the technological power necessary to make lights. Lamps were at least somewhat common, their fuel presumably Doris oils or fats, but this place had been abandoned for quite some time. I was fairly certain that among the few entads that had made it into the zone was something that produced light, given how often that was a byproduct of what entads did, but we were well past the duplication period.

On our side, we had Amaryllis’ new dagger, which blazed like a miniature sun until she turned down the brightness to something that was more tolerable, and the more mundane solution, flashlights. The interior space we found ourselves in was a fairly tall and wide hallway, the same bland magestone as before, with something like a vault door at the other end of it. It had been cracked open, and blood had seeped and pooled out of it. It wasn’t coagulated or dried, not that I could tell, which meant that it was either recent, or some kind of magic had been done there. I switched over to Grak’s eyes, and saw that it was glowing, but not in the shade I had expected: it was two-toned, normal blood mixed with Doris’s magic, so clear I didn’t need it explained to me.

I felt a nervous tingle as I looked at the open door. Part of the purpose of building this facility had been containment, to make sure that if anything went sideways, they would be able to shut it down and keep it from spilling out into the EZ. That clearly hadn’t worked.

“Alright,” I said, drawing my sword. I’d had some practice with it, enough that I could do the triple axis wound reflection relatively fast. “We go in, find the portal, and … close it. Which should be as easy as breaking up the markings that allow the star magic to work.”

“The bloodworms aren’t terrible to deal with unless they get you,” said Raven. “Whatever else is there, that’s likely to be more of an issue.”

I nodded, then glanced at Grak. In theory, the wards that surrounded him would make him nearly invulnerable to everything outside of completely non-magical materials, void effects, memetics, or something like that, but there was no way that I was going to ask him to go first. I was, frankly, worried that he was going to die soon. He had gotten so much stronger, and most of his issues were … well, not necessarily in the past, but I thought he was probably over the hump. I thought about Gemma, and how she had unceremoniously died, leaving me wondering whether that was because her role in the narrative was redundant, or because I hadn’t expressed much interest in hearing her life story. Grak was a friend, and we spent a fair amount of free time together, sometimes Earth stuff, sometimes dwarf stuff, but it felt like there was no story left anymore, just gentle support when he needed it. I was worried that he was expendable, from one very important point of view. Fenn had died for less.

(There was a potential romance with Grak that I wasn’t interested in, and not just because Amaryllis was sucking up all of my romantic attention. I didn’t feel any attraction, any heat. If I’d been told point blank that I needed to start dating him, or have sex with him, in order to make him immune to being killed off by the plot, I would have done it without much of a second thought. But to propose or actually do any of that just as a precaution seemed degrading to both of us and damaging to our actual friendship, and it was complete guesswork what the Dungeon Master’s criteria might actually be for deciding whether someone died, if there even were any criteria.)

I went first, sword held in front of me, ready to strike down the first thing that moved, but aside from the blood touching my boots, there was nothing, just an interior room that led off into different hallways. Amaryllis was behind me, holding her dagger high enough that it could cast light in front of me, but from her position, not everything was bathed in light until the moment she stepped through the door herself. That was when I could finally see the ceiling, which was writhing with hundreds of worms.

As if on cue, they attacked, some of the further ones dropping down, and a few of the closer ones launching themselves at me. My sword was in motion almost at once, bones being burnt to give me the speed that I would need to cut through them. I switched the elemental plate over to lava, which immediately began sizzling the blood at my feet, and made my way through the bloodworms, slicing and dicing them. They were fast, but at least when I was burning bones, I was faster, and the biggest problem wasn’t even their speed, it was the fact that they moved so low to the ground that they were awkward to strike. A handful actually made it to me, but my still magic was stronger than the force they could produce with their jaws, and the only risk was getting overwhelmed.

“Clear,” I said, after about thirty seconds. There were lots of corpses, and I was worried that they were playing dead, or that we would attract the attention of something worse, but nothing was moving much.

The others followed me in, Star Doris staying close to Grak. Blood was moving away from him as he walked, keeping the floor clean beneath his feet, but the effect didn’t extend far from his skin, and I thought it was probably just part of his suite of wards that he always had up since becoming Warded.

“Which way?” I asked Star Doris.

“To what?” she asked.

“To the portal,” I said, gritting my teeth slightly. The bloodworms, I was pretty sure, had been an aperitif. “The big fucking portal to the elemental plane of blood, the one that something horrible came back from?”

“You understand that I didn’t do any work on that, right?” asked Star Doris. “I wasn’t told anything, I was just given work that the primary star mages didn’t want to do.”

“Then if you don’t know where in this facility it is, tell us where it isn’t,” I said, gesturing at the hallways that split off around us. “Look, we can split off a clone and then do a deathmatch thing if you really need us to. If that’s what it takes to compel your cooperation —”

“It’s through there,” said Star Doris, pointing to a door somewhat further down. “I think it is, anyway. I knew some of the women in materials processing, that was the direction they would go.”

“But you know the mechanism too,” I said.

“I never saw it myself,” she said. “I only saw bits and pieces. You should have taken someone who knew more.”

“A lot of them are probably dead,” said Amaryllis. “Let’s keep moving.”

Aside from the inch-deep layer of blood on the floor, which hissed as I walked across it in my lava armor, nothing looked too badly disturbed. One odd thing, more a matter of how the place had been built than anything to do with the blood portal, was that there were very, very few doors. We’d gone through the big one at the entrance, which would keep people out, and then the vault door, which would keep unnamed things in, but elsewhere it was just open doorways. That had been a recurring theme in Dorisopolis, in part because making doors was difficult work, especially with their lack of materials. It was still kind of unnerving.

We cleared slowly and cautiously, checking rooms as we went so that we wouldn’t be ambushed by something behind us. We were in no particular rush, aside from the possibility that we were about to run into something that was slowly growing in power. I wasn’t sure that I bought bloodworms being what was keeping the Dorises out, though they had famously low morale as a group, extremely poor entad support, and only relatively minor combat specializations. There were bladebound Dorises and blood mage Dorises, but from what I had heard, they generally weren’t any better than you’d get after a handful of years at an athenaeum. The Dorises had allegedly trained themselves, after all, and while they got a lot of combat experience, they only ever trained and fought against themselves, and it wasn’t like they were fighting for fun, nor grinding up skills if they didn’t have to. There were a lot of the bloodworms, but subsequent fights with them were barely worthy of mention.

Eventually we reached what appeared to be an antechamber, a large place in the signature flat magestone, set up a bit like a locker room, with various stalls filled with equipment. Toward the front of the room, on either side of another vault door, were two heavy suits in cages, and two cages beyond that which were empty. They were like something that an old timey diver would have worn, thick and heavy, with bulbous metal helmets that had thick glass faceplates. They were sized for a Doris.

“Shit,” said Amaryllis, looking at the suits. “Someone on the outside funded this.”

“Not necessarily,” replied Raven. “It could be that they made a trade with someone foolish enough to hire their services.” Both of them were looking at the make of the suits.

“Opening up a portal is hard work,” said Amaryllis. “If you wanted to force an exclusion and deal a blow to — whoever, or if you just wanted to engage in forbidden research where you weren’t hamstrung by red tape, it would make sense to go somewhere like this. The EZ leaks, but not reliably so, and if you kept them in the dark — I shouldn’t jump to conclusions.” She turned to Star Doris. “Do you know?”

“No,” replied Star Doris. “I’ve never even been here. If this was part of some deal, it would have been kept from me. Obviously.”

“I don’t think it matters for right now,” I said. “Either way, something went wrong here, for them.”

It did help to answer the question of ‘why blood’ though. The elemental planes were different ‘distances’ from Aerb, I’d known that much just from reading. Generally speaking, the more worthwhile planes were harder to get to, but even if you had to pick from among the crappy ones, accessing the elemental plane of blood seemed like one of the worst to me. There was no air, just blood, and I wasn’t sure what good those faceplates would do, because blood wasn’t particularly easy to see through. I had thought that maybe it had something to do with the overabundance of basically-real blood that the Dorises could produce, blood which was real enough to count for the purposes of blood magic. That was still a decent theory. Part of the reason that Amaryllis had jumped to outsiders working with the Dorises in secret was that this was the kind of scheme she would have cooked up if she didn’t hate Doris.

The second vault door was, in fact, locked, though the seal wasn’t tight enough, and it was clear that this was where all the blood had been leaking from. I didn’t know whether it was under pressure, or if it would be barely a trickle, but it was clear that whatever the real horror we were going to face down was, this was where it was going to be.

It didn’t take much to pry open the door. There was no rush of blood, no re-enactment of The Shining, just a short time when it gushed over the lip, then barely a trickle. There was still no coagulation.

I was paying a lot of attention to the Crown of Eyes, hoping that it would spoil the surprise if there were a person in the next room. My mind kept going back to the image of a Doris with billions more gallons of blood inside her than she should have had, and what would happen if all the magic keeping it contained stopped at once. Hopefully we would have some time. In the worst case, Grak would put up a ward and we would pray for the best. Actually, in the worst case, we would use the teleportation key and be on the (figurative) other side of the hex, but that would junk the mission.

This room was large, warehouse large, and based on what it had looked like from the outside, probably the largest room in the whole facility by a wide margin, though with the star mage expertise they had, it was entirely possible that the facility was bigger on the inside than the outside. In the center of it was an elaborate construction of a type I’d never seen before, with lots of struts, many of them curved, connecting in odd places. It was only when the light bathed them that I finally saw the lines marked on them. The whole assembly, which looked like a particularly erratic playground set, twenty feet tall and much bigger around, must have been three-dimensional star magic. I knew the equivalent of ‘hello world’ in star magic, but this … I could see how this would have taken a whole team of star mages a lot of time to do, since each of those lines would have required its own calculations, nevermind the work of actually putting them in place with a high degree of accuracy, and I was pretty sure that they were etched there rather than drawn on, mostly because parts of it were covered with dried blood.

“This is the portal,” said Star Doris. “Eight years of my life were spent on this.” Spent by whom, she didn’t say.

“What do we need to do for disassembly?” I asked. “You would have built in redundancies, maybe even booby traps.”

“Just knock the thing down,” said Star Doris, staring at it.

It was very still and quiet in that big room. We were more than fifty feet from it.

“That closes the portal,” I said. “In theory.” Portals closed easily and safely by default, even if you weren’t trying, at least from what I knew, with none of the calamity that an extradimensional space might have. “But if there’s something down there, what happens? You said that there were hemonauts that came back wrong.”

“I said that was what I’d heard,” replied Star Doris. “Look, do you need me for this? Because I was only supposed to bring you here, and I only worked on parts of this construction. All you’re doing by having me here with you is making sure that if you die, I die with you.”

“You can go,” I said.

“I’ll need light,” she said.

“Amaryllis?” I asked.

Amaryllis hesitated, then popped a flashlight out of Sable. It was big and bulky, standard for what you’d find on Aerb, and I wondered how much calculation she’d put into that. A single Doris with a flashlight meant that all of the Dorises could have their own, given not even that much time. It meant giving over flashlight components to the Dorises as well. Amaryllis didn’t raise the obvious objections though, and when Doris had confirmed that the flashlight worked, she left without another word.

“We should have killed her,” said Amaryllis as she watched Star Doris go.

“What’s her incentive to betray us?” I asked.

“I don’t know,” said Amaryllis. “Just a gut feeling.”

“It was the right thing to do,” said Raven. She was staring at the structure, and the equipment that was half-concealed at the center of it. “I would say that we should prepare for a fight, but we’re not remotely equipped for interdimensional warfare. There are some very, very big things in the elemental plane of blood, and some of the smaller ones are even worse. And if the Dorises really can break the exclusion, then … I don’t know what might have happened. Something taking control of her is a worst case scenario for that entire plane.”

“People can’t survive on the elemental plane,” I said. “I mean, it’s no worse than being underwater in the short term, aside from the lack of visibility, but … I guess that whatever took her over could change that, if something did take her over.”

“Fuck,” said Amaryllis, taking a breath. “I don’t like this.”

“Yeah, the air tastes too much like iron,” I said. I didn’t have the bandwidth for using air magic and vibration magic at the same time, not if I wanted to be able to talk and think. Filtering particulates was particularly tough.

“This could be anything,” said Amaryllis. “It’s too much of a wide open space. It’s here for us, and we don’t have a clue.”

“I only ever went to the elemental plane of blood for a brief thirty minutes,” said Raven. “We didn’t explore the elemental planes much, not unless they were intruding onto Aerb in some way.”

“It’s not a good time for second thoughts,” I said.

“No better time,” said Grak.

“What are we proposing?” I asked, biting back my assumptions about what kind of a hold we might be putting on things.

“A surfeit of caution,” said Raven. “I used to go into these kinds of situations knowing everything that I could get from primary sources. We came in with as detailed of knowledge on the DFEZ as we could, but this is different. There’s nothing stopping us from leaving and seeking out materials on the elemental plane of blood. We don’t have to rely on only what I can remember. It’s fairly clear that four hours shouldn’t make the difference.”

“If you give me ten minutes, I can get things moving in Caledwich,” said Amaryllis. “I have a clone on standby in the library there.”

“She just waits there all day?” I asked.

“No, of course not,” Amaryllis replied. “She does general reading and research. Hold on, I’ll start now, don’t discuss too much without me.” She closed her eyes and began concentrating.

“We’re probably overthinking it,” I said. “This portal has been leaking blood, despite the best efforts of the Dorises. There’s a bloodworm infestation, which we’re not charged with dealing with, and it’s probably … I don’t know, feeding on the excess blood.”

“They don’t do that,” said Raven. “They don’t feed on blood at all, they feed on souls.”

“Right,” I said. “I know, but this blood,” I paused, looking at it. “Only has Doris’s soul.”

“Then I don’t know,” replied Raven, frowning. “But we agree that the bloodworms aren’t actually the problem?”

“They might have been, for the Dorises,” I said. I was still looking at the big structure, which was waiting there for us. I’d run into things like this when DMing, or at least, situations that were superficially similar. The party would get to a part of the quest where they were supposed to just do a simple thing, then they would end up talking themselves in circles for real-life hours and going down conversational rabbit holes without actually making any decision about the matter at hand, which wasn’t supposed to be a decision at all.

“We should start thinking about this on a higher narrative level,” said Raven. “The Dungeon Master has his machinations, but if we assume that he set this all up for us, then he would set us up with something that would be appropriate to our skills and abilities.”

I let out a groan. “And how would he do that?” I asked. I fidgeted with my magics, doing a quick check of all of them just to help slow myself down to the group’s speed. “I mean, the guy has godlike powers, sure, but according to the Dorises, this has been a slow-motion trainwreck. How does the Dungeon Master adjust the difficulty on the fly? He just, what, has several possibilities at each site, which he then kicks off when it looks like we’re getting close?”

“That would be one way of doing it, yes,” said Grak.

“It’s my understanding that the Infinite Library existed, in part, to keep these things from boiling over,” said Raven. “If there are many mechanisms for preventing calamities, all he would need to do is remove the brakes at the appropriate moment.”

“But that would mean this quest went into a period of criticality only when we got here,” I said. “Or maybe he knew that we would probably need help finding the phylactery, but that gives him only a few days.”

“You assume he doesn’t cheat,” said Grak.

“No, I don’t,” I said. “I mean, I assume that he doesn’t just reach down into the world and retroactively make stuff up, but … well, I have to believe that, because if I don’t, then it’s hard to make any actual decisions.”

“Except for here,” said Raven. “Here, where you’re making your decisions on the basis of whether or how much the Dungeon Master cheats.”

“Okay,” said Amaryllis, opening her eyes. “I caught some of that. Mostly meta discussion?”

“Yes,” nodded Raven.

“Not too important, I don’t think,” I said. “No offense.”

“None taken,” said Grak. Raven did look a little annoyed, but said nothing.

“How is Anglecynn? How is library Amaryllis doing?” I asked.

“It’s all me,” said Amaryllis. “So ‘she’ is a handful of seconds divergent from me, which means that she’s mildly unhappy with not having control of the situation here, but well-adjusted enough to put her nose to the grindstone and be subordinate. As for what I know and feel from that integration, it’s mostly personal reflection and some plans to satisfy social desires. The actual knowledge gained was in areas that aren’t relevant here, primarily sources on materials fabrication. We’ll sync back up in two hours, unless I have cause to do it sooner.”

I sighed. “I really do think we should just —”

I was suddenly looking through five sets of eyes, not four. I got no innate sense of where those eyes were in relation to me, but I recognized the hallway that we’d gone through, which meant that they were close to the antechamber. It was only by focusing intensely on that direction with vibration magic that I heard the footsteps.

“Company,” I said, voice low, and I moved closer to the door, weapon drawn, focusing on the eyes that were looking over the suits. This interloper was on their own, armed with a flashlight but nothing else. I could see from their hand that they were humanoid, but almost certainly not human, because their veins were sticking up too much from the surface of their hands. I knew all the mortal species of Aerb, but didn’t have a good enough practical grasp to tell which one this might be just on the basis of a hand, even if the skin was purple, which narrowed it down considerably. I couldn’t see a weapon, but that didn’t mean much.

We turned off our flashlights, and Amaryllis sheathed her brilliantly shining dagger, leaving us momentarily in the dark, waiting in complete silence.

He was moving slowly, with the same caution that we showed, spending time looking at the suits in the antechamber, paying attention to the blood he was moving through, trying not to splash. The sound was much clearer once he was around the corners, though I still wasn’t sure that I would have been able to hear him without vibration magic, even in the silence.

I had my sword to his throat as soon as he was through the door, and he gave a yelp of surprise before dropping his flashlight into the blood. Our lights came back on, and I realized that I recognized him: he had immaculate eels for a beard. It was possible that I was confusing him for another of the zildin, who I hadn’t seen that many of, but I was almost certain that it was Pinno, the Infinite Library’s expert on exclusion zones.

“Pinno,” I said, nodding to him and sheathing my sword. (The sword was really more of a physical indication that I was ready and willing to do violence, and sheathing it was at least partly symbolic.)

“J-Juniper?” he asked, looking me over.

“What goes wrong here?” Raven asked him.

He looked between the two of us, trembling slightly. “Why are you here?”

“The Dorises screwed up something with their portal into the elemental plane of blood,” I said. “We were going to try to fix it. But if you’re here, then I guess that means something went wrong?”

“You killed people on your way out,” said Pinno, looking at Raven. “And you,” he said, turning to me. “You went mad.”

“If they’re catatonic, we have a way to fix it,” said Raven. “Juniper is no longer afflicted, which I was quite clear about when I tried to leave peacefully with him. He’s capable of reversing the effect of that particular meme. I take it you’re not here for us?”

“No,” he said. “No, I was here for the calamity.”

“World-ending then?” asked Raven, raising an eyebrow.

“No,” he replied. “No, the Library has been acting up since you’ve been gone, and the current leadership hasn’t quite been following in your footsteps. This is an attempt at early intervention.”

“Do the books record us being here?” asked Raven, frowning at him.

“That’s a delicate question,” replied Pinno, raising a hand to stroke his eels. “I suppose I can say that they don’t.”

“Then what does happen?” I asked. “Look,” I continued, when it didn’t seem like he was going to give an answer. “We’re trying to ensure a good outcome here, same as you.”

“There’s an entity on the other end of that portal, and partly here even now, establishing itself, reorienting to the prime material,” said Pinno. “From what gets written about it twelve to thirteen years from now, we think that it’s able to take on some significant scraps of those people whose blood it consumes. The Dorises were a unique circumstance, so much of the same blood that this entity was able to take on a semblance of intelligence. Not a clone of Doris, but something similar. Three weeks from now, it breaks this low quality confinement and begins to expand, which the Dorises are unable to stop, and which the Empire doesn’t learn about until the prospect of stopping it would require … well, resources that they don’t know exist.”

“Our friend Thargox,” I said. I still knew nothing about what kind of entity it was, only that it was good at linking warders together, and Solace was apparently on friendly terms.

“So what are you here to do?” asked Raven. “You’re not a warder, nor a star mage.”

“I’m here to talk with it,” said Pinno. “After it grew big enough that it covered the EZ, it ran into some problems. The Doris blood that it had been using couldn’t pass the border of the EZ, which meant that it was reliant on other blood to create something of a blood homunculus. That could leave the zone and speak for it, but couldn’t be manufactured en masse. But it could be talked to, and dealt with, and after five long, disastrous years, eventually the Empire was able to make it see reason.”

“Make it?” asked Amaryllis.

“Not like that,” said Pinno, shaking his head. “Not with force, just with long conversations about the benefits of … well, of not being like the person whose blood it was primarily composed of. We think at least part of the change might have been simply from cycling out the Doris, but not all of it.”

“Then why come here?” asked Raven. “It’s not the end of the world. We wouldn’t be doing anything about it, except that the Dorises refused our help unless we did. Knowing that it turns out for the best … Why take the risk of accelerating the timeline? Unless this is a contingency?”

“Different leadership, Raven,” said Pinno, his voice gentle. “And different circumstances. The business of keeping the world on track has seen a change in strategies. We’re leveraging easy benefits where we can.”

I was listening to him with a frown on my face. So far, our plan to break down the star magic structure seemed like it would probably work, and then this sub-sub-sub-quest would be done, putting us back on track. But what Pinno was offering was an ally of considerable power, as well as a potential solution to the Doris Problem, even if it seemed like it would be a grisly end for her. A creature of blood, granted its power through eating just enough Dorises that it could think … well, it wasn’t the kind of ally your average hero would have, but for me, it seemed about right.

“Okay,” I said. “So we put up wards, then we talk to it and convince it that we can engage in mutual cooperation with it. Maybe we even give it a lift outside the EZ, if you think that’s prudent. This was essentially your plan?” I asked Pinno.

“I was going to do it without wards,” said Pinno. “I am, as Raven mentioned, not a warder. And to put it into a cage during its first steps on Aerb seems as though it might not be the best strategy.”

I wondered what his plan to deal with the bloodworms was, if he’d had one at all, if he’d even known about them. He must have seen their bodies on the way in. Looking at him closer, I realized that he wasn’t obviously armed, he just had a walking stick that was slung across his back. Through Grak’s eyes, I could see that there were no entads. And I wasn’t entirely sure that he could be trusted, as much as he’d seemed like a total alt-history nerd when I’d been studying with him in Infinite Library.

“We’re not opening anything without a ward in place,” said Amaryllis.

“I don’t believe I have a say in the matter,” said Pinno, looking us over. I’d shifted my armor from magma to smoke, the better to hide in the dark, but I’d have wagered it was still pretty impressive, the equivalent of a snake with brightly colored banding that said ‘don’t fuck with me’.

“Alright,” I said. “Then if we’re going to talk, let’s talk.”

The star magic structure surrounded a big, bulky tube with another heavy door at the top. I wasn’t sure that I would be able to fit through it if I had to, as the size was just about right for a Doris in a heavy suit to fit through uncomfortably, at least as a guess. To one side was equipment, including tubing and a set of hand-cranked pumps. The more I thought about it, the more I thought that you couldn’t have paid me to go in there, not even using one of the Earth-modern scuba suits that Amaryllis had fitted and ready for me inside Sable. Leave aside, for a moment, the fact that it was blood, if you went through the portal you would be in a boundless, lightless, sea of blood, with no visibility, no gravity, and all kinds of horrifying shit that made that place their home. In the late Carboniferous Era, insects had grown huge because of plentiful oxygen: the elemental plane of blood was wall-to-wall nutrients, created by processes inherent to the plane.

“We’re putting up the ward,” I said. “If we have to kill that thing, then fuck it, that’s what we do.” I looked at Pinno. “I don’t buy you coming here at the same time as us by coincidence, just so you know.”

He hesitated. “I didn’t know it was you,” he finally said. “Word reached me that someone had gone in ahead of me, before I considered myself properly ready.”

“You know they practice slavery here, right?” I asked. Soul sight wasn’t showing any entads on him either, not even the walking stick. I really did wonder what his plan had been.

He glanced at Raven, who gave him a nod. “I have my own unique abilities,” he said.

I kept staring at him, then looked at Raven.

“He’s a pacifist,” she explained.

“D&D 3.5, Book of Exalted Deeds?” I asked. “Something like that?”

“Much more difficult to attain,” she said. “I would have brought it up if it were relevant.”

“Right,” I said, nodding. It would have been implemented in Aerb as some kind of pseudomagic. I wondered whether Reimer had known about it and just not said, or if this was some hidden feature meant just for me, maybe even just to show the path not taken. I had a ton of questions about how this actually worked, in practice. In the D&D splat book, you got a bunch of benefits for taking various vows, which would then give you powers that (sometimes) (kind of) replaced the normal functions. “Okay, well I’m not going to worry about it right now.” I paused briefly, squishing down the urge to ask a question, and looked at the big metal container that held the portal to the elemental plane of blood. “Time to open this can of worms.”

It was a ‘place our figs’ moment, and we settled on clumping up, mostly so that if it came to it, Grak could ward us and Amaryllis could let us teleport out.

Grak put the ward up, and I climbed up the steps beside the hatch and began to crank it open, ready to bolt at a moment’s notice. Once it was unsealed, I pulled the hatch back all the way, and just for a moment, looked down at the surface of the blood inside. I had expected vertigo from looking down into the nearly infinite expanse of blood, but there was nothing like that, because it was simply too opaque. It might as well have been a few inches of blood, for all that I could see into it.

I stepped back when it started bubbling up, and Grak closed the last hole in the ward.

“It won’t hold against a detonation,” he said, looking over his work. “I’m saving concordance for that.”

“Okay,” I replied. “It’s presumably just some kind of —”

But I didn’t get to finish that thought, because an enormous blob of blood came out shooting out of the tube like some loogie hocked up by a seriously ill giant. It bounced off the ward that Grak had put up and slapped onto the hard ground beside the tube, splattering to the side and revealing a human form. She was covered in one of the bulky diving suits, with the helmet still intact, and after a few long moments, she slowly rose to her feet.

“Steady,” said Pinno. My sword was raised, and I was in a fighting stance, but if this was our worst case scenario, a Doris with a fucking insane internal blood pressure, then the last thing I would want to do was cut her.

She removed the helmet, which came off with a rush of blood, because it must have been filled with the stuff. Her hair was cropped short and matted with blood, and it was all over her, leaving the question of how the hells she’d been breathing in there. The question only deepened when she began disgorging more blood, first letting it flow from her mouth like vomit, then with quite a bit of hard coughing, until finally she straightened up and looked at us with bloody and bloodshot eyes.

“Hey,” she said, then pounded on her chest a few times and coughed up another mouthful of blood.

“You’re a hemonaut,” I said. “How in the fuck did you survive in there?”

“Where are the others?” she asked, spitting to the side and trying to blink the blood away.

“They’re gone,” I said. “Again, how the fuck did you survive in there?”

She looked at the five of us. “Blood mages can breathe blood,” she said. “I don’t know if they teach that at the athenaeum. Probably doesn’t come up much.” She looked around us and blinked a few times. “Are you going to kill me?”

I looked through Grak’s eyes to give me the warder's sight, and saw nothing too unusual about her. The blood around us and on her was magic, some of it in a double hue that I’d have guessed would indicate that it was Doris blood and latent magic, but I was no expert, and Grak hadn’t seen fit to say anything.

“We weren’t planning on it,” I said, slightly relaxing my stance and my grip on my sword. “Tell us what happened here.”

She looked at me, then rather than answering, shook her hand, spraying droplets of blood that briefly showed the ward around her before falling to the ground. She didn’t seem terribly surprised by that. “Well,” she said. “You’ll let me out if I talk? Meaning I walk free? I’ll need a promise.”

“Would you trust a promise?” asked Amaryllis.

“It’s better than nothing,” Doris shrugged.

“Then sure,” I said. “You tell us what you know, and we’ll let you go.”

“Ask away,” she said. “Or I can give my own explanations, since I don’t know what you know.”

I nodded.

“We opened up a portal to the elemental plane of blood,” said Doris, gesturing with a bulky glove to the tank she’d come out of. “It’s small, barely fits a person, but once you’re through, you’re out in the clear. It breaks exclusion, which you’re probably wondering about, but that’s because exclusion zones have their own interactions with the other planes. Our star mages figured that out forty years ago, but it was another twenty before we could actually put it into practice. We’re excluded on the elemental plane of blood too, but we’ve got our own exclusion zone there. It was just a matter of finding it.”

“How do you know this?” asked Amaryllis. “You’re a blood mage, not a star mage.”

“Why did they tell me?” asked Doris. “I had a need to know. I was supposed to be in charge of the outpost there. We figured that we could make polders, eventually reclaim the whole of the blood EZ, start figuring out a way to harness all that blood for something useful. Build some pumps or something, because there’s no natural flow of blood. Find a way to defend against the creatures there, then start hunting them. We already have as much blood as we want, and entad support to remove the extra bodies, it’s just a question of how much time and infrastructure it takes. The idea was we would make some kind of pump and have a pipeline of blood flowing from the colony back to the original EZ.”

“That’s smart,” said Amaryllis. “It would take lots of processing. Lots of coordination.”

Doris shrugged. “It probably wouldn’t have worked, but that was the mission from high command, with non-compliance punishable by death. I think part of it was that they wanted to see if some blood magic strain could figure out something new and interesting to do with all that blood, or if one of us would adapt to the environment. That was me, more or less. You let me know if I’m going on about the wrong things. My priority here is to tell you what you want to know so that you’ll put your swords away and let me go, which is what you promised.”

“How was the portal built?” asked Amaryllis. I could assume that this wasn’t idle curiosity, more a way of probing what she knew and whether her hypothesis about outside actors was correct.

“Carefully,” said Doris. “Probably not the way they would build it on the outside, but we make do. And the outside world doesn’t have the ability to throw tens of thousands of star mages at a problem, because they don’t produce enough of them, and slavery is frowned upon, not to mention that it doesn’t work well for intellectual pursuits. I’m not a star mage myself though.”

There was the obvious problem that nine women couldn’t make a baby in a month unless they had a time chamber, but I didn’t press her on it, because she was at least partly right: you could divide up work and structure your projects so that they were massively parallel, even if that was wasteful. An overwhelming amount of skilled labor was one of the EZ’s comparative advantages.

“Do you have water?” she asked. “Food would be good too. I’ve had nothing but blood for a long time.”

“What happened?” I asked. “Something terrible.”

“The colony went well,” said Doris. “There was nowhere to run away to, and everything came through the portal. Being totally dependent? It was good for us. Teamwork, or else. After long enough, it was almost a matter of habit. We were constrained on air, food, water, so if you made copies, you had to do it carefully, or better, not at all. That helped too.” She looked at us. “Then one of us learned how to survive on blood alone, and that was just about it for the whole thing. They had half as much to threaten us with, and those of us who couldn’t breathe blood were ripe for slavery. It was a whole new world then, because we didn’t have any restrictions, we didn’t need air systems, we didn’t need food, and soon there were colonies that had declared their independence from the Blues. The Blues tried their best to reel us in, but they didn’t have blood mages on our level.” She looked at us. “Was that a no to food and water?”

Grak took some time to pull a meal bar from his vest, then a canteen, passing both of them over with careful respect of the wards. (His vest was on over his temporal plate, a bit of entad gear that had been given to him from the haul, extradimensional, but with a slow response time. It could change form factors of mundane equipment as well, again, slowly, and with serious limits. It was fairly boring, but he’d seemed pleased with it.)

Doris ate like she was starving, wolfing the meal bar down, then drank like we’d come across her baking in the hot sun of a desert.

“Fuck that’s good,” she said, tossing the canteen back across the ward to Grak. As it passed through the ward, the blood simply slid off it, leaving it clean. “We traded with the Blues, as much as we could, but we knew that they weren’t happy about it. And eventually, there were too many colonies in the blood exclusion, too many factions that were stripping the place bare, even with the heavy losses we were taking from the natives. There’s some scary shit out there, when you can only see through your sense of blood, probably even scary if it were crystal clear water, but it’s damned near impossible to kill every last one of us, and we can wear down nearly anything, or clog their maws with bodies until they’re choking to death on pieces of us.” She looked proud of that fact. “It didn’t take us long to be the dominant lifeform of our exclusion. And it didn’t take long for there to be an arms race among the colonies.”

“Which is what brought you to calamity?” I asked. “Or,” I said slowly. “You decided to wage war on the Blues and take back the exclusion?”

“We were tough to kill,” said Doris. “But once you’re a good enough blood mage, one that’s surrounded by blood, one whose blood is the same blood as everyone else around you, it gets really deadly, fast. You can wipe out a colony, if you do it in a single lightning-fast strike. We couldn’t develop defenses against the attacks we were inventing. And eventually, there were precious few survivors, and no one that wanted to build anything up, because we knew that it could be torn down. So yeah, we made an assault on the Blues.”

I looked at Pinno, who had a bewildered look through this whole story. What Doris was telling us had virtually no relation to what he had told us was written as happening in the alternate timeline. He hadn’t cottoned on to what was happening.

“You’re a master blood mage,” I said. “You reached apotheosis. And you’re the only survivor of the clone wars in the elemental plane of blood.”

She sighed, then nodded. “Look,” she said. “You told me that you would let me out if I told you the truth. You promised.”

“You’re something different,” I said. “What have you been doing here, just waiting? I don’t believe for a second that you couldn’t open that hatch on your own. And this blood, that’s your work. The blood worms, also probably your work.”

“Are you letting me out, yes or no?” asked Doris, stepping toward the ward and pressing her hand against it.

“No,” said Amaryllis.

“Wait,” I said. I glanced at Amaryllis. “I think the correct answer is yes.”

“Juniper,” she started, half pleading.

But I was looking at the blood around us again, using Grak’s warder’s sight to do it. It was blood, Doris blood, and while I had no idea what you could do with sufficiently high blood magic, I could see one fact pretty clearly: there was no question of letting her out, because she was already out.

Parallel Lines

The Underline sailed along, well under the three hundred foot limit, taking us not to the Isle of Poran, but back to the Necrolaborem EZ, this time with remote assistance from the Dorises to actually find the fucker. Based on the readings that they’d been able to give us in the DFEZ, he was in the city itself, but deep underground, which wasn’t entirely unexpected, but was annoying. It meant that we were either going to have to find the entrance or drill down. We were working on it though, and in the meantime, we were cruising along in the nice, gentle air. We could have teleported, since we’d been to Necrolaborem, but none of the sites we’d ‘acquired’ by making whorls on our worldlines were ones that we could be confident would be safe.

Amaryllis and I shared a cabin, as we’d done during all our recent flying, and while we spent a fair bit of time out and about on the flying schooner, or with the others, our cabin was a place that we went to retreat. The bed was wide enough for two, if they were willing to get close, which we were. She liked to lay beside me, resting her head on my chest. We were both clothed, something that needed to be stipulated in these odd times, dressed in t-shirts and shorts, because it was a little bit warm in the region we were passing through. It made me think about Reimer’s insistence on having his characters constantly wearing full plate unless there was some mechanical penalty for it, which had always irked me (there had been a time when I used the term ‘ludonarrative dissonance’ every chance I got). In reality, constantly wearing as much physical protection as possible got old fast.

“How are things in clone land?” I asked.

“No change from the locus,” said Amaryllis. “Solace is brooding, and it’s difficult to comfort her, because she views it as a vindication of the Second Empire’s research, at least if I’m reading her right. That’s been leading to her having some hard feelings toward both of us, which is frustrating. Again, reading between the lines. She’s not talking all that much.”

“I wish it weren’t that way,” I said. “I wish Grak’s thing had been the end of it.” That the locus getting out of the bottle hadn’t done much was disappointing but not surprising.

“In Anglecynn,” Amaryllis continued, “There was an effort to bring forward a vote that would have restricted the number of council seats that any individual can hold, which I squashed. The pushback has started, though it’s not as fierce as I thought it would be, because so many people dying in such short order has left an enormous power vacuum that I’m filling almost entirely on my own.” She paused. “I’ve started being a little more flamboyant in how I dress myself, because people keep getting the versions of me mixed up, even though I have very clear roles assigned. It’s starting to get to the level of costume.”

“Sexy costumes?” I asked.

She gave me a dirty look. “I know you’re joking, but that’s been a problem in Anglecynn. One of the things that I underestimated about going public with the clones is just how many sex jokes I would have to endure. The clones dress very conservatively, covering skin and hiding my figure, but people still seem to think that when we’re not working, we’re having giant lesbian orgies. And if the jokes aren’t about that, it’s about you being a very lucky guy. But people will say that to my face, like it’s any of their fucking business, or at all appropriate to speak of to another person. These inconsiderate assholes get a boner thinking about it and don’t have the common courtesy to keep their idiotic fantasies to themselves. The papers are worse about it, but that I at least understand, because there’s a profit motive — I’m working on reforms there, incidentally. But no, these people who’ve been pissing me off are in conversation with me over the future of their businesses and our country. And they’re saying these things.” She was tensed up, and took a moment to relax. “Obviously you are a very lucky guy though.”

“I am,” I nodded. I still felt a bit guilty about the new sexual aspect of our relationship, but that guilt was fading as it became the new normal.

“I liked having the four of us together,” said Amaryllis, as though she could feel my guilt and felt the need to assuage it. She had two clones on the ship with us. “This isn’t about you and me, it’s just a really pointless and unwelcome complication for my work.”

“Okay,” I said, rubbing her back. “You let me know if there’s anything I can do.”

“I’ll think about it,” said Amaryllis with a sigh, allowing herself a moment to just enjoy the feeling. There were, as it turned out, a lot of physical sensations that she enjoyed, and I had been slowly learning them. “Anyway. That’s another thing that’s going on in Anglecynn, if you wanted to know.” She tapped her fingers on my chest. “I’ve been commiserating with Blood God Doris about how annoying the lewd jokes are.” I was pleased as punch that my name had stuck.

“They don’t, uh,” I started, not knowing how to finish that. “I assumed that there was freaky sex stuff going on in the DFEZ.” I had no idea how to phrase that so that I wasn’t doing the exact thing that she was just complaining about. After our brief time in the EZ, I didn’t think that I would ever fantasize about Doris, not having seen the poverty, slavery, cannibalism, and everything else. But I had assumed that the Dorises were using each other for sexual gratification.

“It’s very limited,” said Amaryllis. “Most of the Dorises are in brutal poverty, and of the ones that aren’t, they hate each other and don’t trust themselves. That makes intimacy difficult. So there’s a trade in dildos, and plenty of masturbation, but very little of what people like to imagine goes on there.” I badly wanted to know how that conversation had gone, and wished that I could have been a fly on the wall. It seemed like a bizarre thing to bond over. “Blood God Doris hates what people imagine, viscerally hates it, probably because conditions have been so bad for so long, and there are people on the outside making up this fantasy that might as well not have her in it at all.”

“Huh,” I said. “And … you’re getting along?”

“I’m starting to understand her,” said Amaryllis. “It would be better if I could count on her to listen to me, but I can’t. She wants someone to advise her, but she doesn’t want to be a puppet, and it’s exasperating, because I could have the whole EZ turned around in virtually no time if I had either of her powers.”

“And Poran?” I prompted.

“Oh, that’s completely fine, but it’s work,” said Amaryllis, shrugging. She held up a hand and began counting things off. “Principle engineering and design for the first televisions is finally done, which means we’re looking for labor; the televisions will be useless without television stations, which we’re securing content, rental space, and radio allocation for; tuung are really gung ho about a second generation, which they’d like to start sooner than later, with or without Bethel; and finally, we’re getting some imperial attention, probably because of the locus in our backyard, which means that we might reach the status of member polity earlier than expected.”

“Sounds great,” I said. “That would be a quest completed without me lifting a finger.”

“It’s a long way out,” said Amaryllis. “The Empire moves at a snail’s pace, when it deigns to move at all.”

“And you personally?” I asked. “All those Amarylli out there are doing well?”

“It’s just me,” she said. “I keep telling you that.”

“You didn’t answer the question,” I said.

“The prospect of more time with Blood God Doris makes me uneasy,” said Amaryllis. “Some of it is just being with her, some of it is the worry that she’ll snap and kill me, or that the other Dorises will attack, or that when it comes time for me to leave, I won’t be allowed to.”

“You’re two days in and sounding like it’s been a lifetime,” I said with a frown. “We shouldn’t have left you there.” I moved a bit, trying to think through our options, but also trying not to dislodge her. “Shit, if that’s the cost of the social option, then … well, fuck. We do battle, I guess.”

Loyalty Increased: Amaryllis lvl 26!

She laid her hand on my arm. “I’m just venting,” she said. “I’m not suggesting that we pull me out. It’s three percent of my existence, and when it’s the full hundred percent, when I’m that instance of me, I can manage. If it were long-term, a year? Then I would say better to get me out as soon as possible. But I will have a replacement, I’ve been working on that, and it won’t be more than another week, which I’m confident I can handle.”

“I don’t want you to be unhappy,” I said.

“More than that,” said Amaryllis, smiling at me. “You actively want me to be happy.”

“Okay,” I said, leaning back. “In the interests of manipulating you into more consistently telling me when you’re not feeling well, I will let this be, and not take any rash actions.”

“Thank you,” said Amaryllis. “Trust me that if I’ve had enough, or think that something concrete needs to be done, I’ll tell you.”

“Loyalty up, by the way,” I said.

“Really?” she asked. “When?”

“When I suggested we go against Blood God Doris to save you,” I said.

“Oh,” said Amaryllis. “Yes, I suppose.”

“You suppose?” I asked.

“I don’t know,” said Amaryllis. “I think it was that I believed you would.”

“Of course I would,” I said, frowning a bit.

“Yes, and that’s ill-considered,” said Amaryllis. “But it was still the thought that you would do that for me. It was me realizing that you were entirely serious. It gave me happy thoughts.”

There was a knock at our cabin door, and I sat up. “Come in!” I called.

Raven poked her head in, checked that we were decent, then stepped all the way in. There really wasn’t a point in her checking, because I would have said something if we were naked, and further, locked the door. My mind went to what Amaryllis had said about the assumptions of sex, and how that had bothered her, and I wondered whether she thought the same about Raven double-checking.

“Juniper, can I talk to you for a moment?” she asked.

“In private?” I asked, looking at Amaryllis.

“If that’s alright with you,” Raven replied.

“I was just leaving to speak with Grak,” said Amaryllis. She pulled away from me and sat up, and after a moment, I followed suit. “So even if it’s not alright with Juniper, he’ll have to do without my company.” She slipped off the bunk where she’d been laying with me and then scooted past Raven. These weren’t exactly luxury accomodations, so there was a fair bit of that on the ship.

“Mute us, please?” asked Raven, as soon as Amaryllis was gone.

“Already done,” I said. I was using vibration magic to block the sound of our conversation, which was standard practice for me, since it was usually pretty cheap in terms of ‘breath’ so long as it was just one or two people, and helped me level the skill. “But you should get to the point quickly, because I’m getting worried.”

“Oh,” said Raven, “No, it’s nothing serious, just personal. Personal and serious, I suppose. If it’s okay, I’d still like to lead with the pretext?”

“The … pretext for talking to me alone?” I asked.

Raven nodded. “It’s specifically with regards to the dimensional bridge or tunnel that the Dorises have pointed out, which, as you said, is the second time that’s been suggested. If it goes somewhere, then it’s almost certainly not a place that’s widely known, and … the best guess is that it leads to Earth. We wouldn’t count on it, but that’s where we’d place money, right?” I nodded. “If Uther is stuck on that bridge, for whatever reason, however that might have happened, then I’m worried that if we get him unstuck, he’ll still want to go to Earth.”

“But that’s just the pretext for what you actually wanted to talk about?” I asked.

Raven sighed. “I wanted to talk about both,” she said. “But if we talk about the other thing, then I worry that’s all we’ll talk about.”

“I’m getting really distracted by the other thing,” I said. “You really shouldn’t have said anything about the thing with Uther being a pretext, and yes, I know, you were just trying to put me at ease.”

“Alright,” said Raven. She looked around the quite small cabin for a moment.

“You can sit next to me,” I said. “Sorry, it’s that or standing. It’s going to take quite a bit of leveling for me to get star magic to the point where I can expand the interior of all the rooms of a moving ship.”

Raven moved over and sat down on the bunk next to me. It was more than enough space for two people, but maybe she was just a bit nervous, or maybe it was that we usually kept our distance from each other. A part of me was hyper-conscious that it was a bed, where people sometimes had sex, the sort of thought that I could recognize as infantile, but which still sat there in my brain.

“Amaryllis and I had a long talk last night,” said Raven. “The matter was somewhat delicate. She was requesting my blessing, as a member of the Council of Arches, to modify her soul. She would like some minimal carnal feelings toward you, ideally responsive in nature.”

“Ah,” I said. “I’ll be honest, that’s not unexpected.” Fucking awkward, but not unexpected.

“I said no,” said Raven. Her eyes were downcast.

“Oh?” I asked. Now that was unexpected. “Why?”

“I was alive for the entirety of the Second Empire,” said Raven. “I saw what essentialism was. There were never that many essentialists, but you could apply for a change to your soul. If the essentialists felt that it had merit, and especially if you could pay, they would change you. There were bad cases. ‘Miscalibration’ was the euphemism of the day. A man would come back from the soul mage and kill himself from overwork, or a mother would forget to take care of her children. Soul magic was good at creating obsessives, and the soul was complex, so accidents happened.”

“But you’re not here to talk to me about accidents, are you?” I asked. “You’re here to argue against the general case. If Amaryllis altered her own soul in a way that was detrimental, we would be able to see it and reverse it. We’re not so worried about fringe circumstances or a careless, overworked soul mage without enough oversight.”

“We should be worried, since she’s a soul mage too,” said Raven. “She can alter her own soul, and yours. There are feedback loops that would occasionally happen to imperial essentialists, though they were largely kept quiet. One modification leads to another, until it’s gotten out of control. Two soul mages together are especially dangerous that way, because they can keep pulling themselves deeper and deeper, spiraling until they become monsters, at best focused only on themselves, willing to waste away, at worst, inflicting themselves on everyone else.”

“We have measures in place,” I said. “Such as requiring that any self-modification go through the Council first.”

“Measures that you’ve willfully ignored,” said Raven.

“Sorry,” I said. “With Bethel, I was,” raped, “confused about what I was feeling and not really in my right mind. I didn’t know what I should do or how else to deal with it.”

“And turning off pain?” asked Raven.

“Exigent circumstances,” I said. “The point of the rule isn’t to be hardlined about it, it’s to create some checks for safety and sanity. If it’s life or death, or even just major trauma, without the possibility of even talking to anyone, let alone getting consent — we’re not a major organization, we’re seven people, we’re allowed to be nimble. As it stood, I probably would have died in that blacksite if I had to feel all my injuries.” Technically it was spirit, not soul, but I wasn’t such an ass that I would argue technical definitions instead of getting to the meat of the argument.

“I’m pointing out that there are exceptions to rules,” said Raven. “It’s the kind of thing that sets me on edge.”

I frowned at her. “Is this your true objection?”

Raven let out a groan. “I’m well acquainted with that argument. It was one of Uther’s favorite rhetorical tricks. If you started arguing with him about anything, he was liable to say, ‘but is that your true objection?’, implying that you weren’t making your argument in good faith. Or even if it was ‘good faith’, measured by intent, perhaps you were constructing your arguments from whole cloth because of an emotional reaction that wasn’t amenable to reason or argument. It was sometimes exhausting to talk to him.”

“That was Arthur,” I nodded. “And yeah, it was exhausting. Not all the time, not even most, but sometimes.”

“Well, if you’re asking about my personal feelings, then I can tell you, but it wouldn’t be an argument, and I don’t think that I would convince you,” said Raven.

“I technically haven’t said that I would say yes, if she asked me,” I said. “But … I guess it would depend on what our friends had to say on the matter. And yes, I would like to hear your feelings, in addition to your logic.”

“My feelings,” said Raven. She sat back on the bunk and lifted up her legs, hugging her knees to her chest for a moment. “Uther and his wife had a similar problem. In that case, it wasn’t a problem of mindset, it was of means. After the Wandering Blight, after everything below her sternum had been replaced by an entad, she was physically frail. That aspect of their relationship was simply gone, because so much of her had been stripped away, down to her core.”

“And you want me to use the same solution?” I asked. “Have sex with whatever reasonably attractive women we find on our adventures, then go back to Amaryllis like it’s nothing?”

“Is sex always meaningful to you?” asked Raven.

“It is,” I replied.

“Was it with Maddie?” she asked.

I was stunned into silence for a moment. “No,” I finally said. “No, it was not. It was — I was in a bad place, trying to — do you want to talk about this?”

“We already have, a bit,” said Raven. “I was just pointing out that you’ve made exceptions in the past.”

“Sleeping with Maddie was a mistake,” I said. “I felt terrible afterward. Partly that’s because it was just … bad sex.”

“In what way?” asked Raven, raising an eyebrow.

“Gah,” I said. I looked at her. “You know, just … she was kind of laying there, not moving, not making any noise.” I felt my stomach flip as I thought about it. “You know, the more I think about it, the more I think I’m not comfortable with continuing this conversation. And if you’re about to explain that from some perspective, it wasn’t actually bad, I would rather not hear it.”

“This is one of those things that’s important,” said Raven. She didn’t seem particularly angry with me, though she might have had a right to, but I could feel the weight of her grievances with me. “It’s important because you’re important, the threats we face are your threats, and beyond that, your wife is asking for permission to edit her very soul because you have some complicated feelings about sex. If other people are kept completely in the dark about what those feelings are, it makes it hard for us to offer proper advice and counsel.”

I grumped. She was right. “I don’t know what to tell you,” I said. “I tried meaningless sex, hoping that it would bring meaning, and it probably left me feeling worse about myself than any other single thing I did. I didn’t really want to do it then, and I don’t want to do it now. I don’t think that’s a viable option, at least for me.” Obviously I could probably edit myself to enjoy it, but that didn’t seem like it would help with Raven’s objection.

“Would you have felt differently if the sex had been good?” asked Raven. It was hard not to hear that as an accusation.

“I don’t know,” I said. “I feel like a shithead for saying ‘yes’, but that’s how human brains work, it’s positive and negative reinforcement. If she’d been really into it … I never actually got her side of it.”

“And you don’t want me to talk about my side of it?” asked Raven.

“Your side being … times where there was some synchronicity?” I asked. “Some possibly deliberate parallels?”

She nodded.

“I don’t want to hear it, but that’s because I’m a coward,” I said. “I think it would be good for me to hear, if not to take a lesson, then at least so we can know each other better. I want to be your friend.” Even before it left my lips it sounded weak and pathetic. I should have phrased it differently, called us ‘true companions’ or something.

Loyalty Increased: Raven lvl 4!

“I had a terrible boyfriend that I think was supposed to be you,” said Raven. “It was during that period when I had given up. I didn’t know what it was all for. My self-imposed quest to find Uther had failed completely. I was living in Five Spires at the time, in a little apartment, trying to write my memoirs. It was shocking how little everyone knew or cared about me. We were legends, sure, but I could walk down the street without anyone recognizing me, and even if I gave my name, Raven, people would just assume that I was named after the historical person. Aside from the attempts to recruit me, promote me, or otherwise make money off my existence, I was invisible.” She turned to me. “Scene set?”

“Uh,” I said. “Sorry, but not really. I don’t even know what century you’re talking about, I’ve never been to Five Spires, and I honestly don’t have a good grip on what life before the Second Empire was like, if that’s even what you’re talking about. Sorry.”

“This was during the Second Empire,” said Raven. “311 FE. Five Spires is and was a huge city with five absolutely enormous, inviolable white spires, of which there are a few around Aerb, with no known purpose. Five Spires has five of them. Each is about two city blocks across, square at the base, tapering in, and then flaring back out into another square at the top, this one with rounded points at the corners. You can climb them, using an interior stairwell, but it’s two thousand seven-hundred feet to the top, meaning that people only do it for the experience. Locals just kind of ignore the Spires. The better neighborhoods are to the north and south, where they get sunlight through the whole day, while the worse parts are in the east and west, where you’re in the shadow of these things for either the morning or night. It was once a major trading port, thanks to a thick river that winds through the spires, but bulk teleport killed that, and the city has coasted on having superior organizations to keep it afloat for most of its existence. I was downtown, north of the Spires. They made me feel … I don’t know, like there was magic and grandness in the world. I would just stare at them sometimes. It made me feel nice.”

“And there was more magic in the world then,” I said.

Raven nodded. “More during that era than now, but less than during Uther’s time. Or maybe it was just more spread out, commonplace. Airships crowded the air around the Spires like flies,” she said. “The city of Five Spires paid a tithe to a dragon, I think.” She frowned. “There were shuist parlors on every corner that had been perfectly arranged so that you could spend five or ten minutes sitting in the center, which would make you focused and revitalized. And there was such a variety of cultures, so many of which have been watered down and mixed into a dull brown by the centuries. Five Spires was one of the cosmopolitan centers, even in Uther’s time.” She sighed. “We’ve lost so unbelievably much.” There was pain and longing in her voice, not just for a better age, but for this entire other life with Uther. “No telephones, no radio, no wires running everywhere. There were other forms of long-distance communication, all now excluded, but for the most part it was about books, pamphlets, broadsheets, and criers.”

“Okay,” I said. “Scene set.”

“You were just trying to calm me down,” said Raven, giving me an accusatory but not all that serious look.

“No,” I said. “You weren’t that upset. But if you can be a bit detached from whatever you’re feeling … I think it would be a good thing.”

“You’re right,” said Raven. “Thank you.” She sat for a moment, cheeks still a bit pink. Maddie had gotten like that sometimes, especially in the evening, a bit flushed, even if she wasn’t embarrassed or even particularly emotional, though embarrassment definitely exacerbated it. “I’d started writing in the Society of Letters again, under a pen name. That was the only place that I really felt at home, but it had changed so much. They were imperialists, who were sometimes fine, and other times would just say these shocking and offensive things that it took me too long to realize were part of the zeitgeist. When I wasn’t doing that, I was trying to live a normal life, though that was hard too, because all these people around me had no idea the things I’d seen. I did my writing for my memoirs and to the others in — well, it would probably skip a lot of explaining if I just said a coffee shop.”

“Come on,” I said. “You know that I love explanations.”

“I guess I did know that, yeah,” said Raven. She gave me a half smile, which wasn’t much, but was enough to make me feel a bit better. “Before smoke magic was excluded, they managed to get some big farms up and running, harvesting and processing enough rare herbs that smoke bars were common. The effects were low grade, for the most part, at least the legal ones. You would go up to the stoker and get a glass bottle filled with fresh, charged smoke, and then you would sit down at the bar, or in a comfortable seat, feeling the effects.” I had done my fair share of reading on excluded magics. Smoke magic was primarily concerned with the alteration of perception, with the higher levels being able to push that perception into becoming reality. It had no connection with the he’lesh smoke magic, which was a completely different take on smoke-as-magic (that was just how Aerb was sometimes). “I would take something called Spire’s Shade, which made everything seem a little more rigid and grounded. To make a long story short, there was a man — seventeen, actually, so … your age — who went to the same smoke bar that I did, at the same time I did, every day. I would smoke up and write letters, or work on organizing the memoir, sometimes writing it, rewriting it, throwing bits away. Other times daydreaming.”

She looked dead ahead at the wall. “I talked to him once or twice, and then I got obsessed. He was an engineering student, hoping to work for the railways, a depressive, like you, and … I guess I saw something of Uther in him. Not Uther, armored titan of a man wielding a sword alongside his many magics, but Uther the poet and writer, slaving away at his next creative endeavor, head bent above his desk, as he — tried to remember stories from Earth, I suppose, or put his own spin on them.” The room was silent as another piece of the edifice in her mind was chipped away. “Benji had that same look to him sometimes. And he was a thinker, like Uther, imaginative, with these grand ideas that he loved to talk about, always somewhat dour about them. I would follow him when he left the smoke bar, pretending that I needed to walk the same way. I made no secret that I liked him. A puppy dog would probably be the accurate way to describe me. I had nothing else going on in my life. We became very one-sided friends. He tolerated me. He liked to talk, and I would attentively listen.” She gave a little laugh. “He had no idea who I was, obviously. To him, I was just some fifteen-year-old human.”

“And you started dating?” I asked.

“For about a week,” said Raven. “I just … I wanted someone. I wanted an anchor. Someone who could make sense of things, even if their version of sense was lacking. And yes, with him, it was awkward, physically.” She looked over at me. “Was Maddie a virgin?”

I really, really hated the answer that I had to give. “I don’t know.”

“I wasn’t,” said Raven. “I don’t know if that can give you information about Maddie, but for me? I had been having sex for a few decades. Four decades, I think. I felt —” she hesitated. “I felt like I could do what Uther did. I felt like I could have these flings, these romances, always without commitment, always without any pretense of it lasting.” She was quiet for a bit. “I hadn’t quite been Ell, when I was with Uther, and I can feel that I’m no longer quite that with you. Ell have this infuriating way of failing at things, over and over, making the same mistakes a hundred more times than a human would. You can shortcut it by realizing where you’ll eventually end up and just forcing it, even though you aren’t quite there mentally, but not all of us do. Sometimes you have to burn your hand on the stove a hundred times just to have it sink in.”

“That sounds horrible,” I said.

Raven shrugged. “We were a dashed off bit of worldbuilding.”

“Sorry,” I said, trying to make it clear from my tone that this was sympathy, not apology.

“Benji, the one that I think was supposed to be you,” said Raven. “He was another in a long line. But he was different, because I felt something with him, a foolish notion that there would be a future of some kind. And he was also different because he didn’t even like me. And all those things that you said about Maddie? I felt that from Benji. That indifference toward me that at the time I thought was his general malaise, but I later realized was just that he didn’t actually care about me. That realization came when he was trying to get me into bed.”

I was feeling unclean. I hadn’t wanted absolution, but I hadn't really wanted her to twist the knife either. She was just saying what it had been like for her, which could maybe be extrapolated to Maddie and maybe couldn’t, but either way, made me hurt.

“I liked sex, Juniper,” Raven said. “But with him, it was this crushing realization that I cared about him and he didn’t care about me, that he was drifting through this relationship that I had foolishly started, and it had led to him trying to find some refuge from his misery by way of my body.”

She smoothed out her clothes. “It was quite possibly the worst sex of my life,” said Raven. “It was like we were on different planes of existence. It would have been one thing if that was what it had been from the beginning, if we were just strangers looking for a good time, but it’s not what we were.”

“I’m sorry,” I said, and tried to convey that this was an apology, not sympathy.

“If the situations are the same,” said Raven. “And I won’t say that they are, because I don’t know, but if they’re the same, then … Juniper, the things you did with Maddie were the thoughtless, inconsiderate actions of someone who had lost his place in the world. That doesn’t excuse it, and it doesn’t absolve it, it just explains it.” She sighed. “At some point, you have to say that tomorrow is a new day. Feel bad about it, because it was bad, but then move on and stop letting it define you.”

“Thanks,” I said. “I guess.”

“I don’t actually know if any of this was helpful,” said Raven.

“Helpful is relative,” I said. “It’s given me a better picture of you in the dark years. Sometime soon you’ll have to tell me about how you came to be head librarian. But you came here to talk about something specific.”

“I did,” said Raven. “I suppose the question is, would you be in favor of letting Amaryllis change herself for you?” she asked.

I paused as I thought about that. “I’d be more comfortable going the other way,” I said.

“The other way?” asked Raven. She was staring at me with her brow furrowed.

“Meaning that I could cut out the part of me that wants sex,” I said. “And then we’d have no problems.”

“You can’t do that,” said Raven.

“Well, not without consent of the Council, no,” I said. “But the problem isn’t Amaryllis, it’s the mismatch between us, and that’s one way to solve it. I suppose you would say no to that too?”

“I would,” said Raven.

“Well, the vote doesn’t have to be unanimous,” I said. “Technically, I think it just has to be a meeting, though I can get why Amaryllis would want to whip votes before any kind of meeting took place. She’s not immune to feeling shame, just to showing it, if it would get in her way. Better to have a meeting where everyone has been talked to privately and the meeting itself is a formality. And I can’t imagine that people would vote differently for her than for me.”

“You can’t just swear off sex,” said Raven. “It’s a part of you, it’s — it’s human.” She seemed aghast at the very notion.

“Well, no,” I said. “Because Amaryllis is definitely human. I think that to remove this last point of contention in our relationship, I could do a minor edit.” And as I said that, I could feel some sense of loss at removing that part of myself, which went beyond just the idea of not feeling pleasure. Maybe for Amaryllis, it wasn’t a part of her identity, but sex was a part of mine. It was tied up in memories and thoughts, whole ways of being. I wasn’t lying though. I would leave it behind, for her, and by definition, I wouldn’t miss it.

“Do you really think this is the last point of contention?” asked Raven. Her eyes were wide. “Juniper, there are so many things that mark the two of you as different, so many ways that you know you would make a better match through changes to your soul or hers.”

“You’re saying that there’s a slippery slope,” I said.

“Sometimes the slope is actually slippery,” Raven replied. She had a faint scowl.

“I know,” I said. “I’ve argued with Uther too, remember? I’m not even saying that’s wrong. Just in this one particular instance, it’s different. It shouldn’t affect anyone but us. It’s not attached to other ethical or moral problems.”

“So if you had different tastes in food, or movies, sufficiently different that it caused any friction, would you change that?” asked Raven. There was a sharpness to her voice, but I figured that she was also curious, trying to take some measure of how far I would actually go.

“Look, I’m a hypocrite,” I said. “I can admit that’s what I am. But if I were to try to make some weak defense for my hypocrisy, it would be that a choice of what to eat or what to watch is hardly likely to rise to the level of actual dissatisfaction.” Amaryllis hadn’t said she was dissatisfied, and I wasn’t sure that I would call myself dissatisfied either, but it was the relevant metric. It was still new. Maybe when the novelty wore off I would feel differently.

“You know as much as I do that life is filled with special circumstances,” said Raven. “We tell ourselves that it will be just this one time, and then it becomes a pattern.”

“How about this,” I said. “Let’s say that somehow, Amaryllis and I could average all our values. That wouldn’t actually work, because it’s not just values, it’s how the spirit interacts with those values, but if we could, somehow, take the average of our spirits as well … I don’t think that would be morally wrong to do, it would just be a question of whether it would be a good idea.”

“That was the endgame of the Second Empire,” said Raven. She had backed away from me slightly, retreating to the far end of the bed we were sitting on. “Induct new people, take on their values as you force their values on them … it made it easier to work together when you could make sure that everyone actually valued the same things. And, of course, things got sanded away. They weren’t a hive mind, naturally, their abilities didn’t rise to that level, and they had no knowledge of spirit except by its absence — that’s not the endgame for us. It can’t be.”

“Okay,” I said. “But I already said that I was planning to be a hypocrite. I’ll just change this one thing about myself, and even if the same logic makes sense for other things, I won’t do them. Besides, I’m the one with the problem. I’m the one who can’t just accept things the way they are.” I wasn’t even sure that was true, since it was possible that I would adapt. Humans were famously adaptable.

Raven turned away from me for a moment.

“You were never tempted?” I asked. “You never thought about your attraction to Uther, especially after he was gone, and thought that you’d have been better off without it?”

“Don’t make this about me,” said Raven, turning back to glare at me.

“I’m not saying that you should have,” I said. “I’m just asking. You were saying that people went to soul mages to alter things about themselves. I’m sure sometimes it was unrequited love. That had to have happened, right? And I’m wondering whether you, at the equivalent of fourteen or fifteen, ever thought about having that done to you.”

“I had too much marking my soul,” said Raven. “Thirty years I was with Uther. It left scars.”

I nodded. I still hadn’t looked into her soul, and didn’t plan to, because there was a chance there were things in there that could hurt me. It wasn’t just the memetics and antimemetics that she’d been exposed to, it was almost certain that Uther had installed whatever defenses he could. “But you did think about it.”

“I did,” said Raven. She got up from the bunk and stayed facing away from me. For a moment I thought that this was where I was going to get a monologue from her, but instead, she just left.

“Shit,” I said to myself.

I tried to imagine the speech that I’d thought she might have given. “You see, Juniper, we can’t just cut out our bad feelings, that’s treating the symptom, not the cause. If you ignore that cause, all you’ll do is manufacture pain down the road. These feelings need to be struggled with, worn down, and finally, bested. It’s through struggle that we become better than we were, it’s through that pain, sweat, and emotional labor that we grow as people. Beyond that, soul magic is the mutilation and eventual death of the self. You know that, because you have had every opportunity to alter yourself, and refused. You felt it when Fenn died. You didn’t cut or even dampen those emotions, because you knew that it would be a betrayal of who you were.”

Maybe that was what she would have said, maybe it was just my own arguments. It rang false to me, at least in this situation.

I lay in bed, ruminating for a bit, then got up and went out of the room, on deck. Raven was nowhere to be seen, and Amaryllis and Grak were still in conversation elsewhere in the ship. Our party was so small. I missed Pallida, as strange as that thought was. I missed Valencia. I missed Fenn too, obviously, though if she were to come back to life, it would cause all kinds of interesting problems.

I waited for a beat, but she didn’t appear.

Some day, the narrative was going to work in my favor.

“Doing well?” asked Captain Bonny, clasping me on the back and standing beside me on the railing to look out on the lands below us. “There’s something that I’ll say for you, I always have nice weather when I’m ferrying you about.”

“I’m a water mage,” I said.

“That would do it,” our Captain said with a nod. Her hand was still on my back. “You’ll protect us if anything goes wrong, won’t you?”

“Sure,” I said. “Nothing is going to go wrong though.”

Maybe I said it because I wanted a fight. Or maybe I said it because I wanted something to distract me. In either case, it wasn’t much more than two minutes later that a big black bird flew up to where we were and landed on the railing of The Underline.

“Go on, shoo!” yelled Bonny, who had elected not to move from my side, though she’d dropped her hand.

The bird turned and looked at me, then cocked its head to the side nearly ninety degrees.

“Juuuuuunipeeer!” it screeched at me.

Bonny bolted, moving faster than I would have expected, and I very casually popped my sword from the ring on my finger. I was unarmored, which was a problem, but I’d grabbed my bandolier, the crown, my pistol, along with all my rings.

“Hello little bird,” I said, trying to keep my voice gentle. I was multithreading, sending an alert to the others with vibration magic through the walls, which I could only do in a very crude way.

“Juuuunipeeeeeeeer, we’re cooooooming!” it screeched, turning its head the other way.

The question was whether or not to attack the bird, and I held off. I was anxious more than afraid, but this was coming out of left field, and I really liked to know what I was up against before blindly charging in. Maybe this was the famed exploding messenger bird of the Aqlith Highlands: I had no idea.

There was a burst of dried leaves from the center of the ship, and it sank slightly beneath my feet in a very disconcerting way. I brought my sword up for a parry, but parried only leaves, and saw what it was through the crown before I saw anything with my own eyes.

Standing in the center of the schooner was an enormous six-eyed doe, and beside it, a small crantek teenager.

“Is this your jackdaw?” I asked Solace, pointing at the bird with my sword.

“I don’t own it, no,” she said. “But I did send it as a messenger.”

“You couldn’t have had it open with, ‘This is Solace’?” I asked. “You had to damn near give me a heart attack?”

“It’s an art, not a science,” said Solace, frowning at me.

“And why now?” I asked.

“What in the fuck?!” shouted Captain Bonny. “Explain to me why there’s a giant deer on this ship!”

“They’re friends,” I said.

“Yes,” she said, voice still raised. “I got that from how you were talking to them, but that damned crow took a year off my life!”

“It’s a jackdaw,” I said. “And that’s the last remaining locus on Aerb.”

“That crow is a locus?” asked Bonny, frowning at me and glancing at the jackdaw with a skeptical look.

“No, the deer,” I said.

Bonny looked at the locus, perhaps taking some time to register that it had six eyes. “Right, that makes more sense. Look, I’m going to go back to captaining this ship, this is too much for me.” She stalked off. From what I knew of her, ‘captaining the ship’ mostly meant chatting with the crew, as there wasn’t much to do when the sailing was smooth (which it always was, because I had a good enough handle on the weather).

“Solace!” Amaryllis exclaimed as she came out of the cabin she’d been in with Grak. “You came?”

Solace gave her a nod. “The locus had recovered enough from the rupture, and I had no real ability to stop it.” She looked at Grak and gave him a smile that quickly faded.

“Just visiting?” I asked.

“I don’t know,” Solace replied, looking at the locus.

I was watching the two of them. The whole time I’d known it, the doe had been stuck in the bottle, unable to move beyond the bounds, and now that it was out and about, I could tell that Solace was wishing it wasn’t. Maybe that was because we weren’t ‘really’ in the domain, though that was a definitional quibble that I didn’t think Solace would go for. I could admit that there were safer places than a few hundred feet off the ground, but I was still happy to see the doe.

“You’ll be here a bit?” I asked.

Solace looked at the doe, then nodded. “I think so,” she said.

“Good,” I replied. “I assume Amaryllis had been keeping you apprised of what’s been going on?”

“She’s been giving dispatches,” said Solace.

“We could have used you a bit earlier,” I said. “I would understand not wanting to bring the locus into an EZ, but … we were planting a garden, and it would have been nice to have your help. Not even in terms of magic, it would have been nice to have someone with a focus on helping things to grow.”

“I’ve been busy getting things in order,” said Solace. “Amaryllis and I have talked about having the first of the applicants come into the locus’ domain soon. Not wanderers, obviously, but as close as we can come.”

“Do you mind if I talk to the locus?” I asked.

“Of course not,” said Solace. She looked over at Grak. “If you have time for a word?”

He nodded, and they went off together, leaving me and Amaryllis alone with the locus, or as alone as it was possible to be on a schooner.

“How did things go with Raven?” asked Amaryllis.

“Poorly,” I said. “I failed a SOC check.”

“Oh?” asked Amaryllis.

“I brought up her unrequited love for Uther,” I said.

“Ah,” said Amaryllis. “By way of comparison to our situation?”

“Yes,” I said. I was sometimes still surprised by how quick she was. “She left before we were really done talking. I don’t think she liked the idea of me using soul modification on myself.” I reached forward and patted the doe on her flank. She was looking out across the lands we were crossing over.

“On … yourself?” asked Amaryllis.

“To cut down my sex drive,” I said. “Or rather, sexual attraction. Or both.”

“Are you just being contrary?” asked Amaryllis.

I looked over at her. “No,” I said. “I’m offering the obvious solution, and if you think that it’s more obvious for you to be the one to change, then that’s something that we should talk about as a couple.”

“You mean as a fake couple?” asked Amaryllis. I looked at her, and she was giving me a raised eyebrow.

“Oh, obviously,” I said. “No, I’m not under some delusion that you have feelings for me, and I hope you’re not under the delusion that I have feelings for you. Sorry, I should have been more precise in my wording, that’s something that we should talk about as though we were a couple, so that we can keep our stories straight.” I wasn’t sure why I enjoyed this so much. Maybe it was the way she smiled at me.

“Juniper, this is serious,” said Amaryllis, but she was still smiling.

“Eh, we can talk about it later,” I said. “But if you think that you’re going to whip the votes and then hold a meeting while I’ve got my pants down — so to speak —”

Amaryllis laughed at that. It was rare that I got a laugh from her, and the turn of phrase hadn’t been intentional, but it was nice to hear. She had a pretty laugh.

“It wasn’t that funny,” I said as she kept laughing.

“Just the image of it,” she said, chuckling to herself.

“Well,” I said. “As I was saying, you’re in for the political fight of your life.”

“Against Juniper Smith,” she said, laughing again, harder this time.

“I’ll deal with you later,” I said, giving her a scowl. “I wanted to spend some time with the locus.” I was surprised to find that was actually true. I had a particular ‘locus mood’, one I tried to put myself in, which was partly Juniper-as-artist, or Juniper-as-dream-being. What with the ping ponging we were doing between exclusion zones, it had been quite a bit of time since I had seen the locus.

“Can I stay?” asked Amaryllis.

“Sure,” I said. “Just don’t think systematized thoughts.”

“Is that a hard and fast rule?” asked Amaryllis, smiling at me.

“Alright,” I said, “I changed my mind, I don’t want you here, you’re being too silly. Has anyone ever told you that?”

“Never in my life,” said Amaryllis with a happy smile. She came forward and kissed me on the lips, then walked away without another word.

“So that’s been going on,” I said to the locus. “Amaryllis with clones can be weird sometimes. I think her strategy, as much as I can figure it, is to compress a lot of the relaxation and stress reduction that she would normally get into a single instance of herself. It’s … kind of great.” I was hoping that it was a glimpse of how she would be once the universe had no more problems in it. “How have you been?”

The locus snorted, then turned to look out at the land we were traveling over.

“Yeah,” I said. “Out of the bottle, into the … uh …” I had really thought that my brain was going to come up with a great metaphor there. “So,” I said. “You’re out and about, and if you want to, when it’s safe, you can see more of the world than I reckon you could when you were at the height of your being.” I was patting its flank and watching it as it looked out past the ship. After a bit, it lay down and rested its head on the railing of the ship.

“These,” I said, pointing out at the forest we were crossing, “These are the shrieking forests of Perlon. The trees down there will let out a shrill yell at anything that tries to eat or damage them. An individual tree isn’t very loud, but if you set off one, you set off all the others, and at that point, you could be killed by the sound if you were in the thick of it. Well, maybe not you, but a mortal, for sure. For all that, it’s a pretty nice and peaceful place, if you don’t disturb the trees. People are really of different minds about it. Those who like the forests tend to call them the silent forests of Perlon instead of the shrieking forests.”

“They’re aspens,” said Grak, who had come over, his talk with Solace apparently concluded. “Also, I’ve never heard of Perlon.”

“Eh,” I said. “Sometimes I like to talk to the locus like that, about things that could be true. I was just saying whatever came off the top of my head. It’s an easier mode of talking, where I’m wondering out loud what kind of strange and mystical wonders this world might contain.”

“I see,” said Grak. “Do you need privacy?”

“Privacy on this ship is a bit of a luxury,” I said. “Did you want to talk?”

“A bit,” he said. “Mute us?”

“Already done,” I sighed. The party was smaller, but sometimes it still seemed to have a lot of people.

“Amaryllis had a long talk with me last night,” said Grak.

“Did she now,” I replied. Two of her clones were aboard the ship with us, and I wondered how many long talks she’d had last night.

“She wishes to modify her soul,” said Grak. “She wants to experience sexual desire, for your benefit.”

“Right,” I said. “And your answer was … ?”

“I think it is better for you two to work through it,” said Grak. “There are also other solutions. It is not my relationship though. I gave tacit approval.”

“Oh,” I said.

He shrugged. “You have your own say,” he said. “If it is something you both want, I will not stand in the way. If you do not want it, she will not do it.”

“True,” I said. “I’m undecided.” I cleared my throat. “How are things with you and Solace?”

“This was my first time seeing her since we were in Poran,” said Grak.

“Ah,” I said. “Right. No letters to each other through the fourfold flask?”

“No,” said Grak. “That is not the relationship we have.”

I was silent for a bit. “I’m not fully comfortable with that relationship,” I said. “That’s a me problem, not a you problem, I’ll own up to it just being me not trying hard enough to either put myself in your shoes or correct for my, ah, intuitions or biases, or whatever. But if you need someone to talk to —”

“I appreciate that, Juniper,” said Grak.

“But you’re not going to take me up on it?” I asked. “Look, whatever it is that my hang-up is, I can get over it. It’s not well-formed, it’s just … when I was growing up on Earth, we had a lot of taboos against people of wildly different ages dating, so the whole reincarnation business is triggering some part of that programming, even if it’s not really applicable. And as far as gender goes — maka was not a gender, so far as Kansas was concerned.”

It was tempting to call Grak non-binary, as that was technically accurate, but to me that implied some level of gender-divergence or nonconformity, which was not the case for him: he was a fairly average dwarf. There were long Groglir words for sexual preference, and by that system he would probably have been ogorikiaded, but that didn’t map very cleanly into Anglish, and the cultural connotations were complicated, especially because they would have been different depending on which dwarfhold you were talking about.

“Solace is comfortable,” said Grak. “She brings affection and aggression to our relationship. She doesn't love me. I don’t love her. We are friends who share a bed.”

“Hrm,” I said. “Which is fine, in the short term, but you want a pairbond …”

“I do,” replied Grak. “There is a sadness in momentary things that will always be momentary. I am trying my best not to be sad.”

“The adventuring makes it difficult to find other options,” I said.

“It is not a problem I need solved,” said Grak.

“Okay,” I said. “I was just … trying to think of a solution, I guess.” Surely dwarves had some kind of matchmaking system. I knew that cross-pollination between dwarfholds was relatively common, and even read one of Grak’s books that was specifically about a romance between two dwarfs, one from a ‘foreign’ dwarfhold, in an arranged marriage, but it had skipped over the actual mechanics of how that match had been made. (Because it uncritically glorified arranged marriage, Grak had issues with the book, but he’d lent it to me after a conversation we’d had about Amaryllis, on the theory that it might help me to understand the institution a bit better.)

“I know,” said Grak. “It is your way to think of solutions to problems which do not require you.”

“Well, if you need to talk,” I said. “And if you need a break, like a week or a month where we go without you —”

“You would die,” said Grak.

“Maybe, maybe not,” I said. “It was just a thought.”

“Once you have won the game, you can make me a heaven,” said Grak. “I can wait until then.”

That weirded me out, but I said nothing, because that was the endgame. I hoped that it would be soon, but who knew how much fucking shit there would be to get through. After not too much more time with me and the locus, Grak left us alone, and I decided to go on about some of the completely fictitious creatures below us to the locus, who perked up a bit at my descriptions. I was using up some of the creativity that I would need for making inktads later in the day, but it was more fun than doing yet another piece of kit, because (at least so far) ink magic didn’t allow me to create flora, fauna, or other neat bits of worldbuilding.

After some time, Solace returned to us, and laid her hand gently against the locus, who huffed at her.

“It’s time,” said Solace. “This is your domain, but it is also not.”

I said nothing. It was fine by me if the locus stayed on The Underline, or if it went back, but it was good to know that we had a Deus Ex Dominia on hand in case things got really out of hand. On balance, I preferred going in with the smaller group, knowing that if the shit ever really hit the fan, we had backup. Every dangerous thing we did, there was a chance that we would have to use Bethel or Valencia as a safety net of sorts: of the four shot glasses, one was with us, one was with Amaryllis in Anglecynn, one was with Amaryllis in Poran, and the last had been sent to Valencia.

“Please,” said Solace.

I took a moment and used the Crown of Eyes to see what the world was like to the locus. It was a wild abstraction of where and what we actually were, everyone on the airship floating upon a cloud instead, gliding over a vibrant, fantastical landscape. Some of the people, crewmen, I thought, were only vague cloud-impressions in humanoid shape, doing nameless work to make sure the cloud would keep moving. Everyone else was there with us though, all represented through locus logic. Amaryllis and her clones were a skulk of foxes, mildly threatening in their posture; I was a tall and mighty stag, which I liked; Grak was a moss-grown boulder; and Raven was a literal raven, though that impression/abstraction was a bit less clear to me, and being really uncharitable, maybe the locus was just confused.

Most striking was Solace though. She wasn’t her teenage self, she was a hag, stooped and withered. She was holding onto a rope, which was tied around the neck of the locus.

I didn’t have much time to take that in though, because they both disappeared, taking my view with them.

On the Merits of Eternal Suffering

The office was the first door to the left down an industrial hallway, and in contrast to the exposed concrete and wires, it was fully furnished and stocked with enough antiques that I thought it had probably been the work of a few weeks to get everything just so. Where the office up above had more books than it seemed like one person would ever need, this office had only a single bookshelf, with most of the room being empty, or filled with the kinds of curios that I had started to get used to while in Anglecynn, things that cost a lot of money and took up a lot of room, but weren’t really useful except as conversation pieces. An exaggerated relief map of Aerb, set into a wooden stand, caught my eye; we were spending more time going by airship now, and the geographical proximity of places had started to matter more, an inversion of how things were normally done in tabletop games. I kind of wanted that map, and some murderhobo part of me was thinking that I could take it if we killed him, nevermind the fact that we had so much money we could just buy one for ourselves.

“My surrender is unconditional,” said Captain Blue-in-the-Bottle, holding up his hands as we entered the room. He looked similar to how he’d looked a week and a half before, but the hat was missing, and he was a different person, the facial features not what they had been.

“It’s not him,” said Grak.

“No, it’s not,” said the Captain. “This is just a shell, but I thought that you would be more amenable to talking this way.”

“We’re not,” said Amaryllis. “If your surrender is unconditional, show us where your real body is.”

“I’m getting the place ready for my true death,” said Captain Blue-in-the-Bottle. “I know when I’m beaten, but there have been many plates spinning within this facility, and the facilities above, all of which need to be unspun in a slow and methodical way. If you kill this body, I will continue the work of unspinning those plates, but —”

“Unconditional means without conditions,” I said. “You’re setting requirements.”

“No,” said the Captain, shaking his head. “No, not requirements, per se, I’m simply stating the reality of the situation. To bring everything screeching to a halt would be an unmitigated disaster, and while I have struggled to come to terms with the fact that this is likely the end for me, I won’t have that disaster on my head.”

“Fine,” I said. “What would that disaster look like? Why would it happen?”

“The dead man’s switch,” said the Captain, giving us a smile. “Not one that I designed, or ever wanted, but one that exists all the same. If I die a true death, then necromancy will likely go with me, and half a million souls will be sent to the hells. I’m disarming, as much as possible.”

“Disarming how?” asked Amaryllis.

“Spiking them,” replied Blue, looking between us in confusion. “Bottling the souls. What else could I mean by disarmament?”

“Wait,” I said. “You’re just … giving up?”

“I’ve said that I was, yes,” replied Blue. “You have a method of tracking me, the will of the world, and a frightening amount of force, if even half of what they say about you is true. You came to me once and showed that you cared nothing for the zombies. If a threat proves to be meaningless to someone, why have that threat at all? I don’t want to send those souls to the hells, I never did, it was only insurance against action by the Empire or other forces that particularly cared about damnation. Which you don’t.”

“What’s this facility for?” I asked. “Answer now.”

“My exclusion zone has been raided on a number of occasions,” said Blue-in-the-Bottle. “I have thus far been successful in driving away those who would trespass with malintent, but it always comes with losses, both in terms of zombies, citizens, and infrastructure. I decided, long ago, that it was better for me to move everything of importance underground. Not only is it easier to defend, but it better cloaks my business.”

“Get to the point,” said Amaryllis. “Now.”

“I have no business contacts within the Empire, but more than a few outside of it,” the Captain admitted. “The Empire is where the bulk of business is, but I’m forced to deal only with those who sit outside it. This facility creates things for them.”

“Then who?” asked Amaryllis. “The Unglians?” They were imperial non-members, famously isolationist and xenophobic, a lot of which came from the particular way they’d been scarred by the Second Empire.

“The economics wouldn’t work out,” said the Captain, shaking his head sadly. “Deprived of access to the train network, the requirement for two instances of teleportation, input and output, mean that my peculiar industry is only of value to those places without much cheap labor of their own. No, my business is with others.”

“The hells,” I said. I’d had a sinking feeling about that, and wanted confirmation. If Blue had such a warped view of the world that he was willing to do what he had done thus far, it was entirely possible that he was making natal souls en masse.

“The hells, but not only the hells,” replied the Captain. “There are other pockets of civilization that are unconnected to the Empire, or as unconnected as a ‘polity’ can get in these days. And I am certain that some of those goods do eventually make their way into the Empire, having passed through so many hands that it’s nearly impossible for anyone to tell what their initial source was except through the kinds of careful forensics that hardly anyone has the time, money, or will to engage in. I’ll open my ledgers to you, naturally. Perhaps this all could have been avoided if I had been honest and forthright from the beginning, but no, I imagine that you were bound for my head one way or another.”

“And …” I said slowly. “What does your trade with the hells look like? Not material goods or labor, surely?”

“I trade in the only thing they have any real interest in,” said the Captain. “Souls.”

Amaryllis turned and looked at me with a raised eyebrow and a slightly sour look. It was a ‘can we kill him yet?’ sort of look. Sending natal souls to the hells … well, that was pretty bad. Worse, in some ways, than what we’d already known he was doing, though not entirely unexpected.

“And what’s your defense?” I asked. “You have one, I’m sure, you had a defense for every claim against you when we were on our way down here. You’re damning people to the hells.” I was sure that he would push back on ‘people’, though the natal souls did eventually develop down in the hells.

“The Empire believes in the supremacy of oblivion,” said the Captain. “Not everyone shares that belief. Your own tuung are one such group, I believe, preaching the supremacy of existence? That is my defense. Those that I damned to the hells go in with clear eyes and full consent. They believe, fully and firmly, that this is the choice for them.”

“Clear eyes and full consent?” I asked. He nodded. Not natal souls then. “But you’re the one responsible for educating these people?” I asked, trying to shift my perception of what we were actually talking about. There was a reason that Arthur had been such a big fan of defining terms before any debate started.

“In the broad sense, yes,” replied the Captain. “In terms of the strict day-to-day, no.” He smiled at us. The zombie he was controlling had its gums pulled back too far from the teeth. “Would you like a tour?”

“No,” said Amaryllis. “We want the location of your real body. If you’re overseeing bottling of the zombies, continue with that.”

“Not all of the zombies,” said the Captain, nodding at her. “Only those who served no useful function except as a deterrent. The others, of course, I hope will remain in one capacity or another, though for that to happen, you would need to keep me alive. You have thought about what will happen in the wake of my death, haven’t you? There are quite a lot of people who directly depend on me and my zombies, though I suppose they’re not imperial citizens, and I don’t know whether that might or might not be important to you. It will be the largest humanitarian and refugee crisis since — well, I’ve heard there was an exclusion in Li’o, though I haven’t seen any numbers on the displaced.”

“We weren’t planning to kill you,” I said. “We were hoping that you might see the error of your ways.”

“There is no error in my ways, I’m afraid,” said the Captain. “Only a disagreement on fundamentals. You believe that it’s better to become nothing than to suffer pain. You believe —”

“I don’t believe that, actually,” I said. “My allies have standing orders to allow me to go to the hells, should I expire.”

Captain Blue-in-the-Bottle, or the body he was wearing, looked me over. “So you don’t disagree?”

“That’s a choice that I’m making for myself, not one that I’m making for others,” I said.

“Interesting,” he replied, stroking his chin. “So it’s a choice you would deny others?”

I paused and thought about what I was trying to get out of this conversation. It wasn’t some philosophical discussion on the nature of choice and consent, it was some understanding of how Blue-in-the-Bottle saw himself. “You think you’re right,” I said.

“Of course I do,” he replied. “All people think they’re right. If they didn’t, then they would realize that and think otherwise.”

“And has that happened to you?” I asked. “Was there ever a moment you realized that you had been wrong and been forced to adjust?”

“Certainly,” he replied. “I would be a terrible businessman and a worse scientist if I was incapable of admitting that I was wrong. I was wrong about the nature of the souls that I had trapped in the bodies of my zombies, but I made my own investigations and accepted the uncomfortable truth.”

“But you didn’t actually change anything,” I said. “You looked at the zombies and made excuses for what was happening to them, excuses for how it was good and just that you were doing these things.”

“No,” said Captain Blue-in-the-Bottle. “I have been quite clear on this point, haven’t I? The existing zombies were quickly cycled through, their souls bottled or damned as best I could ascertain their wishes, and the new ones were given full knowledge of what the effects of zombification would be. There are quibbles of consent, but I must say, consent was obtained.”

I didn’t know whether I could take him at his word, but was really thinking that I probably couldn’t. Maybe he thought that he was being honest, or that he’d had consent, but someone powerful like him, asking consent from people without power, or people who’d had coercion applied … it was the kind of thorny stuff that you could spend all day on. Even if I could trust that he was approximately correct, and using words in the same way that I was using words … he was making sense to me, but I didn’t know if he was right. It was easy to say that I would have done differently in his position, but there was a good chance that I would have made all the same excuses or the same ‘concessions’ that didn’t amount to stopping. Again, he was reminding me of Arthur, and the way that Arthur would talk about things. That made sense though: Blue-in-the-Bottle had been born and raised in the Second Empire, which was at least partly cribbing from Uther’s methods of thought.

“Whatever,” I said. “We’re going to bring all this to a stop, and if we were ever to start it up again, which I don’t think we will, it will be with an international conversation and the full-throated support of the Empire of Common Cause.” And that basically meant that it was never going to happen, which I was pretty sure we all knew.

“Morality of the least common denominator,” said the Captain, shaking his head but smiling, as though this was faintly amusing. “I suppose you’ll stop the trade in souls as well?”

“We will,” said Amaryllis. “Obviously.”

I had mixed feelings on that, but Amaryllis was saying these things at least in part because we would have to account for them later: I couldn’t simply say, ‘well, if they really do want to go to the hells, we shouldn’t stop them’. At some point, probably after we’d gotten the Captain to completely step down, the international community would have to be called in. There would be interviews and after-action reports.

“Take us to your body,” I said.

“Of course,” he replied, bowing slightly in a way that I found annoyingly ingratiating. “I’ll take you by the most direct route.”

“Stay clear of us,” said Grak. “If you come too close, the body will die.”

He didn’t seem terribly surprised by that, nor worried, and with some maneuvering around, he moved past us. I would have been worried about him running, but it was clear this wasn’t his ‘real’ body, and if he had a panic room, then he’d already had ample time to get there. If anything, the worry was in the other direction: he might be stalling for some reason. But again, he’d had plenty of time, and it didn’t seem like another few minutes or hours were likely to make the difference.

Once we were outside his office, he guided us down the corridor. There were no labels on any of the hallways we went past, though there were clearly places where labels had been, rectangular discolorations on the walls. For having unconditionally surrendered, the Captain had still done his best to make it hard for anyone coming down here to find their way around. I looked at the mapping entad a few times as we went, multithreading, and saw that most of the distribution it indicated had quieted down: he was more likely to be in one specific spot.

We didn’t see anyone else as we moved through the utilitarian corridors, but I saw plenty through the Crown of Eyes. Its range was fifty feet, which wasn’t all that much in an open field, but was more than enough when I was in the heart of an underground complex. Fifty feet meant five stories up and five stories down, and there were many levels to this place, as well as many people.

All the zombies were standing stock still, staring straight ahead at spots on the wall, not focused on anything in particular. I could only see them when they were facing each other. They were wearing a shapeless outfit, without sleeves or pant legs, leaving them in nothing but vests and shorts. It was easy to tell them from the humans, because their eyes didn’t move, not so much as a saccade.

The humans were more interesting, and more worrying. They were sitting still, for the most part, not engaged in any work. The whole facility had apparently been shut down, leaving people sitting in their office spaces and warehouses, some of them in quiet conversation (I really needed to learn how to read lips) and others just huddled together. I saw a couple hugging, and from the movements of the woman, I thought she was crying. I tried to keep my head straight, to look for evidence of things that Blue was keeping hidden, but these were broken people in what looked like the last days of their way of life. The only comparison that I could make was to tornado season in Kansas, and those rare few times we’d gone down into the basement to ride it out. My dad always had this look in his eyes that I was seeing on these people, tension and anxiety, along with a resignation that it was completely out of his hands.

The people were on the younger side, almost all humans, with few wrinkles but a certain gauntness that I associated with grim dystopia, though that might have been me reading into things. Their clothes weren’t quite uniforms, but there had apparently been little in the budget for dyes, makeup, or other embellishments. The furnishings of the rooms they were in were likewise sparse and functional, though not particularly shoddy, which was what I might have expected. Things were big, thick, and solid, built to last for a hundred years, which was the kind of timescale that Captain Blue-in-the-Bottle had been working on for quite some time.

There were offices and warehouses, assembly lines and break rooms, bedrooms and bathrooms. I saw a teleportation room, with now-familiar grids in place to mark where incoming shipments would arrive. I also saw a room with hundreds of zombies lined up in tightly packed rows, which were apparently not part of the bottling process that the Captain had outlined, or maybe were just down the priority queue. My guess, from what I could tell of the kaleidoscope of views I was looking through, was that they were backup labor, stored because there was no particular need for them.

The layout of the underground compound, at least what I could see of it, changed as we went. In the beginning, it was mostly receiving, with the assembly coming later, but the further in we got, the more residential areas I saw, underground dormitories, a dining hall, and what I thought was probably a gymnasium. The question of what all these people were doing for food was at least partially solved by a brief glimpse into a farming room: they were eating kear and its byproducts, like the dwarves. I had assumed that there was more than one entrance to this place, because even a large freight elevator wouldn’t have been enough, but there was another option: the people down here just never came up, living their whole lives underground. It was clear, from this bigger picture of the place, that Captain Blue-in-the-Bottle had borrowed some practices from the dwarves. Terrence had said that he didn’t know anything about what was going on underground, and if he was telling the truth, it seemed like most of these people were living their whole lives (and their eventual undeaths) without ever seeing the sun.

It was getting hard to stomach the idea of not putting an end to him.

That thought was going through my head when I saw the maternity ward. I came to a stop, and the party stopped with me, looking at me in confusion. Their weapons were drawn, and they had been for quite some time, but now they looked like they were ready to kill, all except Grak, who was paying attention to the wards he had around himself, and his magical sight.

“Problem?” asked Amaryllis.

Only a fraction of the room was within my fifty foot radius, but it was similar to the other zombie storage rooms. The difference was that all of the packed-together zombies were women, and more than a few of them were visibly pregnant. A needle was attached to each one of them, which snaked along the floor to a large vat at the front of the room that was filled with an off-white fluid. I saw a few people in there, what I assumed to be medical personnel, sitting in chairs away from the zombies, or moving through the rows. The only other thing I noticed, before averting my eyes, was that there was much more in the way of species variety.

“Zombie mothers,” I said.

“Ah,” replied the Captain, stopping where he was and turning back to us. “You have some form of distance viewing? Unfortunate. I would have explained to you ahead of time, rather than have you see it first and need an explanation afterward.”

“There are pregnant zombies?” asked Amaryllis.

“The flesh is dead,” said Captain Blue-in-the-Bottle. “But it can still sustain life, given the right injection of nutrients. That is what’s being done, in one of those rooms that it seems the prince can see into.”

“And then what’s done with them?” I asked.

“After a birth, some work is put into repairing the zombies,” said Captain Blue-in-the-Bottle. “Births are generally somewhat premature plural births, which gives the best chances of success, and reduces the amount of damage to the zombie. Four or five births per is typical, though it’s as high as ten in some cases. Healing magic on the zombies is quite inconsistent and costly, with entadic solutions being the —”

“The babies,” I said, gritting my teeth. “What happens to the babies?”

“Oh,” replied Blue. “I have a neonatology division, somewhat to the east, but, apparently, beyond your vision?” I didn’t give a response to that. “The babies are cared for, fed and changed, until they can be transferred to the childrearing wing of the complex.”

I closed my eyes for a second. “Ah, fuck,” I finally said.

“Don’t make the mistake of thinking that there is something sacred about birth,” said the Captain. “There is nothing unique or special about it, there is only internal programming and social constructions around it that dictate its special place. It was one of the achievements of that Second Empire that we stripped the sentimentality for birth and death from the general public, but that achievement clearly did not last. When you die, you leave behind a body, and zombies excepted, that body is simply matter with only a tangential connection to the soul and to the person who once was. We become worm food, if we are not used. It is quite similar with birth. Any idiot can give birth, and no birth need be accompanied by any particular motherly or fatherly love. That’s simply the way it’s always been done, the dread inertia that has brought low so many mortal institutions. That disgust you’re feeling at what you’re seeing? It doesn’t come from a place of logic, it comes from a place of raw emotion, emotions that fundamentally do not map to the world as it is.”

I felt my heart sinking. If this was the kind of thing that the Captain had been trying to save for later, if he’d been trying to acclimate us to his way of thinking so that he could spring fresh new horrors on us that would look better in comparison … well, that meant that there was probably something worse. I focused on water magic again, trying to figure out the scale of the operation, how many of these zombie mothers there were, how many children were being raised in this underground facility in what were effectively mass orphanages. Some of those barely-felt blobs of water were, indeed, smaller than others, but how many, it was very hard to say. Thousands, maybe tens of thousands. It was hard to pick out the children, even with the size difference.

“The children are given good lives, above what most in the Empire can hope to have, and even if they weren’t, —”

I muted him. I was sure that he had his arguments, but I was pretty confident that if I argued back, he wouldn’t be amenable to reason. He was really reminding me of Arthur, and in some ways, of myself. Heshnel, the dark elf flower mage who had briefly been a part of the party, had been a member of the Second Empire, but he had been a reluctant defender of it. Here, the Captain was barreling ahead, without even the slightest admission that he might be wrong. I was sure that he would concede ground, if pressed hard enough, especially if he thought that death was on the line, but the reason he was talking to us seemed clear now. He wanted to convert us.

“This is going to be a clusterfuck,” I said. “We’re probably looking at more than a hundred thousand refugees, many of them small children, and the eradication of a way of life within the exclusion zone.”

“You’re in favor of Plan B now?” asked Amaryllis.

“He’s put his neck on the chopping block,” said Grak.

“He’s done that because he thinks you’re like Uther,” said Raven. “Uther very rarely killed those who begged for mercy, and almost none of those times made it into the history books.”

I tried to think about it, and draw parallels to how we had handled Blood God Doris. It was different though, because she was stuck in this cycle with negative feedbacks, wanting things to be different but not knowing how to make it that way, incapable of structural changes by herself. Captain Blue-in-the-Bottle was just so damned self-assured, so impervious to any shame or humility.

And I didn’t necessarily think that he was wrong, at least in principle. There wasn’t anything sacred about births, there were probably just a whole host of knock-on effects and hidden benefits that you would have to work through if you wanted them to be handled differently. That was an argument for caution and an argument for thorough investigation, not an argument for not ever changing how it was done. There were people on Earth who argued for home births, or using a midwife instead of a doctor, or suffering through the pain of childbirth, or all kinds of things, and there were a lot of arguments back and forth about how it should be done. I had read a lot of those arguments, in preparation for Amaryllis giving birth. And as for having two parents, a nuclear family, I was sure it was the same, hidden problems that would crop up if you tried to just barrel into an optimal way of raising a child. My guess was that the Captain had worked from base principles, possibly with some testing or the application of grossly unethical science (or, possibly, “science”). Whether or not he was actually exceeding the average around Aerb was anyone’s guess, and untangling it would take weeks or months of work, with a lot of the conclusions being subjective. I was, needless to say, extremely skeptical of the Captain’s motivated conclusions about quality-of-life in his underground city.

“Juniper?” asked Amaryllis.

“Sorry,” I said. “Let’s go get to his real body.”

“And the plan, when we do?” she asked.

“I don’t know,” I said. “I think that pacifism might not be an option. If we don’t kill him, then after what’s revealed here, I’m pretty sure that we’d have to constantly be protecting him.” It was harder to kill someone who had (apparently) completely surrendered, but were we really going to keep this guy alive just on principle? I thought not. “We’ll find his body first. According to the Dorises, we’re going to the right place.”

“And the thought of a double-cross has occurred to you, if they’re still in communication with him?”

“It has,” I nodded. “But if he’s leading us this far into his facility in order to spring a trap …” I didn’t want to tempt fate by finishing that sentence. It wouldn’t make much sense, and it had better be a pretty fucking good trap.

“Is there anything I can help you with?” asked the Captain, looking at us. He had stopped talking at some point.

“Two questions,” I said. “Why raise almost exclusively humans?”

“Humans are among the most adaptable of the mortal species,” he replied. “Sometimes that adaptability lends itself to pathological behavior, which can be a boon in certain circumstances, including this world that I’ve made beneath the ground. Humans need a tincture to make up for the lack of sunlight, but in terms of psychology, they can handle it better than all but dwarves, and dwarves come with their own problems.” He looked at Grak. “No offense.”

Grak watched him in stony silence.

“Second question,” I said. “What age are they when you kill them?”

“The word ‘kill’ is a strong one,” said Captain Blue-in-the-Bottle. “There is no force, no coercion, it is a decision mutually agreed upon and then carried out by my people. The death is painless.”

“What age?” I asked again. I wondered whether he wanted to get caught up in a debate about what constituted force or coercion.

“It is a delicate answer I have to give,” he replied, frowning. “I rather think it better to speak about the generalities before we approach the specific. At what age do you think that a person is capable of making their own decisions?”

“Answer the fucking question,” I said.

“Or what?” he asked. “I have already given my unconditional surrender, all my lands will be salted, my industries stripped apart, my people spread to the winds, if not killed outright, and I myself have little doubt that I have met my match, and this is simply the end of me — with what leverage can you demand that I answer?”

“We can offer information,” I said. “Haven’t you wondered why we’re here?” That was a gambit, and a poor one, but it was better than suggesting to him that, no, really, promise, we’re not going to kill you, ignore the swords.

“Aside from the obvious?” he asked. I nodded. “Well, now that is intriguing, a final mystery before my demise. Very well. They’re eight years old. Now, to answer your obvious objections —”

“Jesus Christ, what do you think you could possibly say that would sway us?” I asked.

“You’re feeling outrage,” said Captain Blue-in-the-Bottle, his voice hard. “It’s not productive. We don’t tend to make good decisions when overcome with emotion. My books and methods are open to you. You can see the teaching plans that I have devised for the zombie matrons, read through the copious studies that I have undertaken to find the right time for such a trade to be made. They would rather live longer, certainly, knowing what they will be facing among the infernals, but that trade is the entire purpose of their existence, which they well know.”

“And none resist?” asked Amaryllis. She had an eyebrow raised, and the look of disgust had never left her face. She was pretty clearly done with this.

“There are roles for those who decide otherwise,” said Captain Blue-in-the-Bottle. “Did you expect me to say that I left them no choice? Of course I do. And I need workers for my enterprises, obviously, workers that must come from somewhere. Those who are born and live in the underground are suited to the environment, and obviously, before the four of you came in with your sledgehammers, some degree of secrecy was helpful. There are incentives, yes, but no force.”

If this were back in high school, and we’d been sitting at the gaming table, I probably would have girded myself for a long conversation between Arthur and Tiff about what constituted ‘force’ and what particular qualities incentives needed to have for them to qualify as force. Maybe they had even had a conversation like that once. But here, it was just sickening, because Elisha Blue had gone ahead and done it, regardless of what anyone thought on the matter, satisfied in his own reading of reality.

“Take us to you,” I said with a sigh. “You’re right that we need to go over your studies and procedures, as well as conduct some interviews to find out what’s actually been going on here. We want to avoid a crisis as much as you do.”

“You said you would tell me about what brought you here,” said the Captain. “I have, as ever, held up my end of the bargain.” That was somewhat the opposite of the impression he’d left on  people, at least going by his biographies, but it was possible that they were wrong. More likely, he’d just bought into his own press releases.

“A dragon instructed us to, on pain of harassment and death,” I said. “Perisev.” She’d never said we couldn’t talk to him, nor gave any indication that we weren’t to breathe a word of this to anyone. I probably would have told him anyway.

“Ah, a pity,” said the Captain. “And seemingly dangerous for her, if you truly are the next Uther.”

“She gave us the task before everything that happened in Anglecynn,” I replied. “And if we have to kill her as a consequence of saving your life, then so be it.”

“They have their own dealings with the hells, I hope you know,” said Captain Blue-in-the-Bottle. “Each dragon is a micronation of its own, with a capable military just by virtue of having a dragon at its head, constrained only by their loose Confederacy and the fear of retaliation. In fact, there are a number of dragons who I have dealings with, though nothing my manufactories make is of much terminal use to a dragon. I would be happy to give you their names, which you seemed interested in before.”

“We are,” said Amaryllis. “But that can wait until we’ve seen you in the flesh, as it were.”

Our host nodded, then turned and began walking again, as though nothing had happened, as though this wasn’t the last few moments of his life.

I kept on the lookout for anything else that needed an explanation, whether through my eyes or those of anyone else. The Crown of Eyes was fairly generous in what it let me see through, though part of that was because of Six-Eyed. There were very few pests in the underground, none of the rats, mice, or more exotic rodents that I might have expected, but more than a few insects, whose views were incoherent enough that they didn’t tend to be helpful.

As we made our way down the central corridor, which was big enough that you could have driven a car down it without worrying too much about scraping the sides, we went through another transition, this time to a fully residential area. Where the bunks, halls, and kitchens before had been mixed-use, this was nothing but places for people to live. I saw children, lots of them, fifty or more in each of the classrooms, sitting quietly at their desks while a teacher and a pair of zombies sat at the front. There was the same grim fatalism there, seen clearly on every face, mixed with confusion and uncertainty on some of the children. If Blue-in-the-Bottle hadn’t copped to it, maybe I would have noticed on my own that there were virtually no teenagers.

It made me feel sick to my stomach, but if Blue-in-the-Bottle really was giving up … well, whether we killed him or imprisoned him, this whole fucking mess he’d made would have to be dealt with. We were delivering a decapitating strike, one way or another, and there’d be so many fucking people who would have to find new lives, or be given them, by us or the Empire. Everything he’d said was right, at least about that. It was an ongoing humanitarian crisis as it stood, but in just a few short hours, maybe as little as minutes, it would be our humanitarian crisis. The Empire had a base just outside of the EZ, and they could be called in, but no fucking way did they have the staff or resources to deal with this, especially not since the Office of Imperial Disaster Relief was still at essentially full utilization in Li’o. Resources had been moved following Mome Rath, reserves depleted, goodwill spent, and now there was going to be another, quite different disaster following in its wake. We were going to have to talk numbers at some point. Maybe it would make sense to do another Sacrifice and boost Logistics as high as it would go, because there were so many fucking children here, and I didn’t think that anyone had the capacity to take care of them, especially not with whatever lessons Blue-in-the-Bottle had been putting into their heads.

We finally arrived at a vault door, which had already been opened up, and the Captain’s avatar stopped there, standing beside it. Inside was a large room, filled to the brim with machinery and people, most of them zombies, the whole of it centered around a single shriveled man on an immense throne. It wasn’t really a throne though, more of a massive magical-industrial contraption with a human at the center of it, tanks of liquid piping things around and wires hooking directly into him.

“You’ll forgive my appearance,” said a zombie close to the withered body as she gestured to it. “There are many forms of senescence, from the degradation of the body to that of the soul, and beyond. It has taken nearly everything that I’ve learned through my many years to fight against them. And now that you’re here, I offer my full concession and surrender.”

The withered body on the throne let out a little sigh. It was barely human, and I could understand why he was speaking through a zombie (if not precisely how).

“What would you like to do with me?” asked the zombie, cocking its head to the side. “If a dragon has told you that I must be killed, will you defy that order?”

“Here’s what we need from you,” I said. “We need a total halt in all production. We need your reserve zombies deactivated and bottled. We need the children moved out of here to somewhere that’s more in line with modern standards of education and welfare. We need as much information as you have: research notes, commitments to various parties, a census, itemized lists of material resources, an org chart — in short, everything. I doubt that you had plans in place for ensuring continuity, and there’s bound to be a whole lot of institutional knowledge contained in your head, but we need everything that we can get in order to ensure that this isn’t as much of a disaster as it might otherwise be.”

“You will have it,” replied the zombie. “I will caution that I keep records only for my own self, not to comply with any authorities, which do not touch me, nor for anyone else, as I never intended to relinquish my control. And in case it was not obvious, this is far from the only site I have.”

I had seen that coming from a mile away, but it still hurt to hear. “How many do you have?” I asked.

“In total, eighteen,” he replied by way of the zombie’s mouth. “Each of them separated from the others, running on independent systems. Their locations have largely been dictated by the underlying geology of the exclusion zone. Some are deeper than this one, though that comes with its own engineering challenges.”

“Total population?” asked Amaryllis. Her face was devoid of emotion, which was frightening to see. I was pretty sure she wouldn’t just kill him out of the blue, but she wanted to.

“I don’t take a census,” said Captain Blue-in-the-Bottle. “Of zombies, I can tell you directly that there are approximately ten and a half million.”

Amaryllis was giving him — the withered body on the throne — a measured stare. “If you meant to deter people from attacking, you should have advertised that.”

“Does it change your mind?” asked Captain Blue-in-the-Bottle’s zombie. “Surely not. And if you’re simply criticizing strategy, then you must realize that an ever-increasing number of zombies would demand the kind of response that I have long been hoping to avoid. It would also surely raise questions about how so many were being created, as well as what purpose they were being put towards.”

“You think we’ll spare you,” said Amaryllis.

“I don’t have a good measure of you,” said Captain Blue-in-the-Bottle’s zombie. “I think that it’s well within your capacity to kill me and then bottle me or send me to the hells, whichever you would prefer. I also think there are obvious problems with that course of action, which you’ve shown some concern for. In truth, I am very old, held together mostly by necromantic magic. I can act and feel through my zombies, but it is a dull affair. I took many precautions to prevent my own death, but I have never seen much like the four of you, and recent history has shown that those who delude themselves into thinking they can fight you suffer only ignoble deaths, their hopes and dreams laying shattered on the ground.” The zombie spread its arms, and on his throne, the Captain spread his too. “Do with me what you will.”

“Seems like a real lesser of two evils situation,” I said. I turned to Raven. “What would Uther have done?”

“I don’t know,” she said. “He would have come in with his army of bureaucrats and — and solved things.”

“He’d have solved the problem of maybe as many as twenty million children?” I asked. The number was a guess, based on what we’d seen, and what the Captain had said about his complement of zombies.

“Less than that, I would think,” replied the Captain, but he didn’t elaborate beyond that.

“How much less?” I asked.

“A quarter of that, perhaps,” he replied. “Five million below the age of eight.”

“That’s fucking ridiculous,” I said. My mind went to the logistics of it all. You’d need millions of pounds of food every day to feed them, you’d need millions of gallons of water, you’d need systems capable of carrying away waste, multiple factories to churn out clothes that they’d worn through, not to mention the power generation that you would need to keep the lights on, the beds that they would sleep in, the laundry facilities to wash their clothes, the showers to keep them clean … even if I could just handwave away the labor requirements by making zombies responsible for everything, and the energy requirements through in-house natal souls, the Captain had to have an incredible footprint on the planar economy just from everything that he would have to import. His whole EZ was six hundred square miles, which wasn’t nearly enough to keep everyone fed, and if he’d been using kear, he’d have made lacework of the underground in short order.

“He’s too big to fail,” I said, feeling my stomach drop. “There’s no nation on Aerb that can absorb this many non-productive people. And even if they could, the Captain has to be importing from all around the world. The EZ is the size of a major city.”

“Uther would have found a way,” said Raven. “He’d have cut the knot.”

“Somehow,” I said, nodding. “Or he would just never have been presented with such a scenario in the first place. He would have been met with unchecked aggression, forcing a violent end. Not a concession and a looming logistical and humanitarian disaster.” I looked up at the body of Captain Blue-in-the-Bottle. “How do you keep everyone alive?”

“Are we at that point, questions?” he asked.

“I have a more important one,” said Amaryllis. “How do you make and keep contracts with the infernals?”

“I have a stable of non-anima and a variety of infernoscopes,” said Captain Blue-in-the-Bottle. “Payment comes in the form of bulk teleport, whose provenance I am not privy to. As for conclusion of the contract, that requires a special technique that I do not believe is common knowledge in the outside world. It is possible, once you have the anima exa, to inject the soul into a specific hell, and even specify a specific location. I’ll teach it to you, of course, and the schematics are yours.”

This was Captain Blue-in-the-Bottle, casually talking about how he spoke to infernals through a non-anima. Devils were famously convincing, and a part of me wanted him to be a victim, to have this whole thing he’d set up be the result of being sufficiently convinced by a devil. Maybe he was a dumbass for setting up a meeting with them, but if he’d been talked into being the man that he was … well.

“And you consult with them often?” asked Amaryllis, apparently thinking the same thing I was.

“The threat of the infernals is overblown,” said Captain Blue-in-the-Bottle. “They can read people frighteningly well, I’ll admit, but their threat comes mostly in playing people off each other, or in knocking down the weak-minded. The non-anima only ever speak with my zombies, who do not betray any emotion or inflection that I do not wish them to have. If the infernals learn anything, it is just about me, and what do I fear from them? I’m already the most reviled man on all of Aerb. There is no one to turn me against, no way to use whatever they might find for leverage.”

Amaryllis looked at me. “You’re taking the lead here,” she said.

“It’s going to take a series of long meetings,” I said. “We’ll be doing a phased stepping down of operations here. There’s no nation on Aerb that can deal with this, but we’ll somehow find a way, working with the international community. I don’t think that we can do it without Captain Blue-in-the-Bottle’s assistance though.”

“Okay,” said Amaryllis, letting out a breath. I could see her change her mindset, all of the disgust and unease washing away as she reoriented herself to the task at hand. From experience, it would crop back up, but this was something of a centering technique, one meant to get her in the right mindset for what was to come.

I expected dissension in the ranks, either from Grak or Raven. I half expected Raven to go kill the Captain with her sword of frozen time, cutting his mortal form down with a single stroke. Unlike with Pallida killing everyone at the blacksite though, I wouldn’t have been not-so-secretly relieved. We did need the Captain for a peaceful transition, and once that was done, we could kill him if we needed to.

I was waiting for the other shoe to drop, to be honest. There had been times, in my DMing career, where I had subverted the expectations of the players and thrown them into some kind of weird scenario where they had to navigate a difficult humanitarian crisis. Most of the time though, I didn’t go in with that in mind, or if I did, then it would still be a challenge in some other way. Here, Captain Blue-in-the-Bottle was rolling over for us, going limp and tapping out as soon as we’d come back. Fighting him would be no more difficult than fighting a corpse.

But no, that really seemed to be all there was. He was capitulating. He’d seen the writing on the wall and put himself forward as the one person who could actually make this transition go smoothly. He had to have known that once we’d disentangled him from his operations, he probably wasn’t long for this world, but it was clear that it was going to take a long time, and in his shoes, I might have made the same play. Of course, the logical thing to do was to wait until we had exposed some weakness, or lowered our guard, and then kill us one by one, which meant that we couldn’t expose weakness or lower our guard … but I wasn’t sure that he would actually go there.

We spent a few hours in that room with the Captain, much of it while sitting on the floor, looking through boxes of papers that had been wheeled in for us. It was all useless, of course, because the folios and ledgers had been filled in by Blue or someone working with him, and they would have to be compared to the actual reality on the ground at some point. Most likely, we would have to engage in our own audits of the labyrinthine underground complexes, but this was the start of it, reading the official record and trying to work out what exactly had been going on.

Through it all, there were zombies watching us, standing impassively. As for what they were doing elsewhere in the complex, that was anyone’s guess.

Amaryllis took some time out to sync with her clones, which occupied a fair chunk of her time. Most of it was necessary though: we wanted to get the balls rolling in Anglecynn and Poran as quickly as possible, and there was no faster method of relaying information than having Amaryllis do a clone merge. Within a few hours, two separate working groups would be pulling things together to deal with the situation, which was far, far greater than we’d known. The Underline would be moved to the imperial outpost outside the NLEZ, where they would be brought in, for all that it would do any good (and in the end, possibly some considerable harm given that we were far more nimble than any imperial office, and were doing something of dubious legality).

Eventually though, we had needs that were going to have to be met, biological and otherwise. Our choice was between continuing indefinitely within Grak’s ward, sleeping and eating in shifts, or to go up top. The whole while, the machinery of the catacomb city was ground to as much of a halt as it could, the daily routines that had been established by what was apparently an army of civil servants dashed against the rocks when we’d arrived. Almost all of that was according to the Captain, of course, though I’d seen enough of it through extra sets of eyes to think that it was probably the truth. There were decisions that would need to be made, and actions that could only really be carried out by our so-called captive.

The more I learned about Captain Blue-in-the-Bottle’s power as I read through his documents, the more I thought that it was total bullshit.

“I can see, hear, and feel through their bodies, though that takes some effort,” he said, when asked to confirm what was in those books. “Likewise, I am capable of controlling them directly, though only one at a time, and then, I am limited by my distance to them, as well as my own understanding of what it is I would like the body to do. They can be made relatively independent though. In the early years, I was limited to simple motions, but after some time, I was capable of tapping into what they knew in life.”

The zombie he was using to speak took in a breath in sympathy with his body on its throne. “It was well known that the soul contained some fraction of what a person knew how to do, but necromancy reaches beyond the soul, into some deeper and more mystical part of a person’s being. There, pathways can be accessed in death, allowing a wide variety of actions to be performed, including complex ones, or those dependent upon precursors. My zombies can weave baskets, for example, though I am personally ignorant of that art. It was through that method that I came across the ability that allowed my city to flourish: while I am, by the decree of the exclusionary principle, the only living practitioner of necromancy, that restriction does not apply to my creations. Further, I am at liberty to pull from one zombie and place into another, copying pieces of them, allowing skills to multiply.”

I had wondered about that. The math simply didn’t work out otherwise, if he had millions of these things. It was also clear that he was interacting with the spirit in some way, though ignorant of it as its own separate art. Perhaps if the Second Empire hadn’t imploded, they would have rediscovered it through the art of necromancy. It was all somewhat academic; we were going to bring an end to the era of necromancy, just as soon as we could.

Eventually, we started to flag, and I told Grak to put up a ward around the Captain.

“I don’t know if it’s safe,” he replied in Groglir. “I’ve spent much of this time trying to tease apart the magic at work. It is unclear this is even him, except that the Dorises tell us so.”

“We can test it,” I replied back. “Isolate a zombie, put up a ward, something like that?”

“We can,” he replied. “But I do not want to be responsible for killing millions, or sending them to the hells, or whatever other tragedy he might have set in motion.”

“Fair enough,” I replied, but I was a little bit unnerved by how much hesitation he was showing. Grak usually did his best to give good estimates of reliability, being specific about what the weaknesses and vectors of attack were. A little bit of quibbling over the definition of ‘safe’ was usual for him, which I appreciated and respected. This was more than that. He was right that it wasn’t fair to throw him into the great unknown and then clasp him on the shoulder and say ‘well, you did your best’. But without Grak to completely neutralize the zombies, I wasn’t sure that we had a safe way of doing things. We could kill the Captain, certainly, but that would bring lots and lots of problems of its own, orders of magnitude worse than the problems that had been keeping the Empire off his back for so long.

“We need this done,” said Amaryllis. “We need to be able to extract and regroup. The Empire is going to want to come in, and we want to have plans in place to keep ahead of their plans, which are almost certainly going to be much worse.” She said that with utter confidence that I wasn’t feeling. It was true that the Empire probably had plans that ran to hundreds of pages covering a large number of scenarios (uprising, coup, natural death, and diplomatic success, at a guess), but it was also probably true that these plans had quite a bit of meddling and red tape involved in them. We commanded the resources necessary to fix it mostly by ourselves, though it would take nearly everything we had, I was pretty sure.

Grak did tests on the zombies, putting up wards and then telling Captain Blue-in-the-Bottle to possess them, or see through them, or give them remote commands. He complied, but for the first time, he looked annoyed and ill-at-ease.

“You plan to cut me off from my zombies,” he said.

“Of course,” I replied. “We can’t leave you here to do as you please. Is that going to be a problem?”

“You’re speaking of shutting down an immense amount of labor,” he replied. “The people who live underground need food, clothing, water, air, many things which the zombies provide for them.”

“And you’d have us believe that you operate on a razor-thin margin?” asked Amaryllis. “That a disruption of a day would be enough that everyone living here is at risk?”

“The zombies provide security,” replied the Captain. “There are criminals and outlaws in my domain, just as there are anywhere else. If it were just production, then perhaps it could be justified, millions of obols poured down the drain, but it’s not just production, it’s the very backbone of this society.”

“It’s unfortunate,” I said. “But we don’t trust you to do as you say.”

“I am ready,” said Grak, coming to stand beside me.

“Are you?” I asked, looking him over.

“Yes,” he replied.

“Then do it,” I said.

It was the second time that I had sat by and watched Grak go about some very important warding. Unlike with the locus, this time we knew that it wasn’t actually the solution, just a stop-gap that would let us get to the solution. I was only a little bit nervous: a fuck-up here would be catastrophic, and there was still a chance that we were walking into a booby trap, but so far the Captain had told us the truth and acted like he was trying to minimize the impact of his death, or possibly to position himself as too useful to kill, and either way, he hadn’t issued a threat.

When the ward was up, I went over to poke at one of the zombies, which swayed slightly but otherwise gave no sign of noticing or reacting.

“Are we good to leave?” I asked Grak.

“Possibly,” he said. “I will put up more wards to keep him confined.

Captain Blue-in-the-Bottle, the real him, let out a rasping breath, trying to speak, but no words came out.

“He’ll keep,” I said. “Hopefully the rest of the facility does too.”

“I don’t like this,” said Raven.

“Why?” I asked. “The stink of death that pervades this place, the millions of lives and millions of undead that might get doomed to the hells, the obvious imprint of the infernals here, or something else?”

“The narrative,” said Raven. “It’s wrong.”

“Okay,” I said. “Well, let’s get topside, speak with the Empire, and then we can see where we stand.”

But naturally, it couldn’t be as easy as having to deal with literally millions of people trapped underground with the mechanisms of their government stripped away and the source of their sustenance removed. No, after we left the manor, there was an enormous black dragon waiting for us.

Push and Pull

It was a bit of a waiting game. We had to wait for Amaryllis to sync with a clone, we had to wait for reports to come through the Fourfold Flask, and we had to wait for some kind of secondary deal with the Dorises. When we’d finally negotiated with them, we were able to use the compass to find Perisev, who was streaking toward Poran at insane speeds.

We teleported over as soon as we had the information on her destination, which put us in the basement of one of the bigger buildings that had been constructed to house the tuung. Many of them were there, hunkered down, since the call had gone out that there might be an attack that they could do little about. I tried not to be too affected by the way they looked at us, like everything would be alright now that we were there. I doubted my ability to protect them.

We went to the surface and made a beeline for the domain of the locus, where Solace was waiting for us. The locus itself was nowhere to be seen.

“You’ve invited danger,” said Solace.

“No,” I replied. “Danger is coming to us through no real fault of our own. We were well within the time limit that Perisev proposed. The only thing that I would have done differently would be to kill her right then and there, but I didn’t have a way of doing that.”

“And you have a way now?” asked Solace, folding her arms across her chest.

“Maybe,” I said. “We’ll try.”

“Good,” replied Solace. “I was never particularly fond of dragons. If they threaten us, slay them.”

“It would be better if we could use the domain,” I said. “I’m stronger here. Not a druid, not by a long shot, but if the battle can be here, then that might give me an edge.”

“Of course,” nodded Solace. “Just be warned that plants don’t particularly appreciate dragonfire. You would probably do well to ensure that as little of the domain catches fire as possible.”

“Understood,” I replied. “And thank you.”

“I am on your side, Juniper,” replied Solace. “Even if I’m called to serve a higher purpose.”

I nodded. I didn’t see her as an adversary, just someone who wasn’t fully aligned with the party’s goals. Maybe I had been deluding myself for too long that we were ever pointed in the exact same direction.

“Can the locus fight?” I asked.

“Can, yes,” answered Solace. “Whether that will happen, I can’t say. We’ve been at cross-purposes lately. The freedom from the bottle … it hasn’t been the success that I had hoped it would be.”

I could see the domain through Soul Sight, and it hadn’t moved at all. The transition between the lushness of the land that had once been bottled and the Isle of Poran wasn’t so stark anymore, as a lot of work had been done to smooth it out, but the domain itself didn’t seem to have expanded so much as a foot. At least it hadn’t shrunk.

We took off through the woods, walking quickly until we eventually came to the tree at the center. I was mildly surprised to see that there were people there, a small collection of very diverse species who were looking uncertain, anxious, and in one case, pretty pissed off. I hadn’t known that Solace had started bringing people in as potential druids. They were all pretty useless to us, since none of them were druids, just hopefuls, and I decided that I would ask about their backstories later on. It was the kind of thought that I immediately chided myself for, but the thought did still pass through my head.

Amaryllis made introductions, and I ignored basically all of it. No one mentioned that they were secretly ultraplusgood magi, or that they had a 99.99th percentile entad, or anything else that was relevant to the situation at hand. I hadn’t gone into the day thinking that I was going to be fighting a dragon, and even this small bit of socialization, this C-plot that was surely going to simmer in the background, was setting me on edge even more than getting blasted by dragonfire. It felt like the Dungeon Master promising me that there were more plots ready and waiting in the wings. Once Perisev was dead, once we went through the months of effort cleaning up Blue-in-the-Bottle’s crimes against the mortal species, there would be more things waiting, another cast of characters to meet, more battles to fight, sub-plots and side-plots and character arcs of one kind or another.

“We have about an hour,” I said as I looked down at the compass. “That’s a guess, based on her current speeds.” She was traveling more than twice the speed of sound, which was faster than dragons were supposed to be able to go. It made no fucking sense, given that dragons propeled themselves through the air using their wings, but draconic flight was magical as well as physical. It did give me pause though, because it was really, really fast.

“Start in on the souls then,” said Amaryllis. “Try to go faster than you went at the arena. Once she’s here, we should assume there are seconds between when she comes into our range and when the fight begins.”

I nodded, and went into my soul to make the appropriate sacrifices to increase Essentialism high enough that I could get the virtue. We had a single soul mage’s soul left intact in our possession, Yarrow’s, and his would be the soul that I scaphed to keep Essentialism high enough that I wouldn’t have to worry about it running down due to the maluses involved.

I felt like a miser as I spent hard-earned skill points, knowing that it would take more training and more downtime to get them higher. The cost was one that only I could pay, and ever since the respec, I didn’t have skills that I didn’t care about losing. I settled on dumping Alchemy, which I’d gotten quite high in the process of creating the chlorine trifluoride, and which we wouldn’t be able to take advantage of until after this was all over anyway. Thrown Weapons also got sacrificed, which was the second time for it, and while I would be able to get it back up with Scaphism, it was going to be more effort than it was worth to train it up again.

Once that was done, I scooped out Yarrow’s soul, then went through the process of eating other souls, each of them handed to me by Amaryllis. I was fairly indiscriminate this time, taking anything that might even remotely have a combat application, including every magic that I came across, and every once in a while, I checked the virtues that I was unlocking. All the souls went back into bottles when we were done with them, occasionally with notes about what was left in them, if it had been something that I couldn’t scaph (like a skill I hadn’t unlocked, or something not currently on my character sheet). We had a disproportionate number of vibration and still mages, a grim reminder of how many innocent people I’d ended up having to kill in Li’o.

We’d tried to time things so that I was finished right before Perisev showed up, but she had slowed slightly on the approach, and that gave plenty of leeway.

“I’m still not equipped for aerial battle,” I said, after looking over the new list of virtues for the second time. “There’s nothing to stop her from making a few passes and laying on the dragonfire. Grak’s ward will probably hold, but that only protects us, not the locus, not the domain, and not everyone else.”

“The best option might be to throw me,” said Grak.

I stared at him. “Seriously?” I asked.

“I can annihilate blood and bone,” he replied. “Dragons are resistant to magic, but not invulnerable. Throw me, then throw yourself.”

The Thrown Weapons 100 virtue was called Throw Anything, and we were in the domain of the locus, where I had extra ability to fudge the rules a bit.

“I don’t think it will work,” said Amaryllis. “Reimer and I have been sending letters back and forth, and his interpretation is that Grak wouldn’t count as a weapon, not without more degrees of reasonableness than we have access to. Further, there are some penalties for throwing that aren’t dealt with by any of the virtues. I’m not saying that it won’t work, only that there’s a good chance that it would fail, and shouldn’t be our first plan of action.”

“I could burn bones to increase strength,” I said, frowning.

“We have a different problem,” said Raven, who had been looking at the mapping entad. “Perisev has come to a stop.”

“A stop?” I asked. “She was moving at twice the speed of sound.”

“And now she’s not,” said Raven.

“Well, I just sacrificed a bunch of skill points and used up a bunch of souls, so she had better fucking show up.” We’d been taking a risk, we knew that, but if she’d been making such an effort to move so quickly across Aerb, why was she stopping now? “Fuck,” I said. “If she stays stopped, she can make all our prep time a waste.”

“We need a backup plan,” said Amaryllis. “The clock is ticking. We’re at one point lost every two minutes. We could take the Egress to her.”

“We can’t properly control the Egress, so I’m doubtful that’s wise,” said Raven. “She could knock us out of the sky. I could take Juniper alone with my personal travel entad, but that would mean leaving Grak behind.”

“Where is she, precisely?” I asked.

Raven grimaced as she zoomed in the map. “She’s in the heart of a city,” said Raven. “Nels Bilo, which isn’t a large one, maybe a quarter million people in the metro area.” She looked over at me. “If we bring the fight to her, then we’re going to a battlefield of her choosing, one with civilians.”

“That’s irrelevant,” said Amaryllis. “Not wholly, but we need to get back to Necrolaborem to deal with things there, which we can’t do with Perisev breathing dragonfire down our necks. A quarter million in the metro area means much less in the central business district, and even a large-scale fight will result in the deaths of hundreds, thousands at most. When compared against the millions of people in Necrolaborem — don’t give me that look, Raven.”

“You’re talking about the deaths of innocents,” she replied.

“Amaryllis is right,” I said. “We’ve burned through limited resources that we can’t spare. Get me there, and I’ll take the fight to Perisev. Collateral damage will be high, but —” I stopped, listening to myself. “Shit. I’m pretty sure that this is the reason that Perisev moved against us. How you feel about the chosen one depends on what you think they’re chosen to do. She didn’t just send us against Captain Blue-in-the-Bottle in order to fuck with us, she did it because she wanted to get a judge of my character. She knew that it would show my values, one way or another. Or maybe just the limit of my capabilities.” I sighed. “I should have told her that once Blue had served his function, we would send him to the deepest hell to be tortured for eternity.”

“There are opsec reasons that we shouldn’t do that,” said Amaryllis.

“I was never planning to,” I said. “I want him to suffer, but that suffering wouldn’t actually accomplish anything. You shouldn’t want your enemies to suffer, you should want them to reform. But look, I lost a point off all the skills talking about this, so it can wait for another day. Raven, are you ready to go?” I wished that we could have brought Grak with, but Sable wasn’t a workaround for the teleportation key’s limits, and I was sure that asking whether there were workarounds for Raven’s entad would just be insulting.

“We need a way back,” said Raven. “Especially if she chooses not to engage.”

“Teleportation key is still on cooldown,” said Amaryllis. “We don’t have anything that could move the Egress, though we could bring it there separately after the fight is over, or if she runs.”

“It’s not possible to use the Egress without violating the Sky Treaty,” I said. “But I guess we’re talking about killing a dragon, which probably overshadows that violation in the eyes of the Draconic Confederacy.” The consequences of this whole thing would probably echo for months, if not years, and I simply didn’t have the time to worry about it. “Raven, ready?”

“Okay,” she said after a moment of hesitation and another look at the compass.

She grabbed me by the arm, gave me a brief questioning look to make sure that I was ready, which I answered with a nod, and then we rose together in the air as the world warped around us, becoming a thing of magic and light together. That only lasted a brief moment before we were above the ground again, slowly falling down between a pair of buildings, into an alleyway. I hadn’t seen Perisev through my own eyes, but I had seen her through the eyes of others: she was sitting in the center of a park, upright and looking quite calm. Almost everyone in the fifty-foot range of the Crown of Eyes was looking at her, or if not looking, then hiding.

“She’s not far,” said Raven.

“I know,” I replied. I took a deep breath. Heightened as I was, I was inviolable, and even if I weren’t inviolable, I had more than maxed out enough skills that I could defend against dragonfire, and likely her melee attacks, along with whatever magics she had mastered. I was feeling that intoxicating raw power that I’d had against Onion, and while it was fading, with five different penalties working against me, it wasn’t fading that fast. I halfway wished that I had kept going with Still Magic, but I had stopped at a skill of exactly 99, which kept me from Meta Stilling. Halting all of my skills from decaying sounded great, but it also sounded like exclusion bait. If I was going to accept the Dungeon Master as a dungeon master, then I couldn’t just be like Reimer, freely pushing the game to its very limits, not when I didn’t absolutely have to.

Perisev saw me as soon as I came around the corner, and her stance changed in a moment, from imperious to something cat-like, down on all fours with her back arched, wings spread, and tail sticking straight up in the air. I ran at her anyway, going full speed, every step boosted with blood magic, draining my bones for power. When I was halfway there, she let loose with a gout of pure black dragonfire, and I parried it away from myself, the wash of heat stopped by still magic before it could touch my skin.

Almost as soon as that was over, Perisev pushed off the ground, springing into the air with unnatural grace and speed, flapping heavily and accelerating in a way that should never have been possible for a winged creature. I grabbed myself by the collar of my armor and threw myself after her, but Riemer had been right, because while I could ignore how physically impossible that was, I wasn’t able to make it more than perhaps a hundred feet in the air before the air resistance and generally poor aerodynamics of my body robbed me of my momentum. I wished that I had the Ring of Incorporeality, which had been lost during a scuffle in Anglecynn, presumably eaten by the Cannibal.

“Come back here!” I shouted after Perisev, and though I doubted that it would do much good, I let loose with a volley of gem magic, as well as an attempt at vibration magic, and finally, threw my sword after her as hard as I could.

She wasn’t coming back.

The sword returned to my hand, boomeranging backward in utter disregard for the laws of physics, and I let myself drop from the air toward the ground. The park where we’d had our brief and unsatisfying fight was on fire, and would probably burn for quite some time. I used what air magic I had to starve the fires of oxygen, but it was dragonfire, which was, naturally, better than normal fire at keeping a flame going in the face of having the air sucked out.

“She ran!” I called to Raven, who was making her way over, fully armored up.

“I saw,” she replied. “The compass hasn’t updated yet, but I watched her until she was just a speck. With the speeds she can move at, we’re never going to catch up. On top of that, if she’s moving at speed, she can strike at us before we have a proper warning.”

“She shouldn’t have picked a fight if she wasn’t willing to finish it,” I said.

“She’s using hit-and-run tactics in order to assess your capabilities,” Raven replied. “She also probably knows that you used prep time in one way or another.”

“Fucking Onion,” I said. “I blame him.”

“Blame the fact that you demonstrated new capabilities in that fight that didn’t transfer over into subsequent ones,” said Raven. “Or blame the careful inquiries that Amaryllis made when she was trying to get souls. Tommul was watching us the whole time we were in Anglecynn, but it would be foolish to think that Perisev wasn’t watching too.”

“Time is ticking away,” I said, careful to keep the sound from leaving our area. “If she’s on the run —”

“Then you should accept that the costs are sunk,” replied Raven. “You have some time until you’re back down to normal, we can guard until then, but we’re going to have to find different strategies.”

“Or I could go higher,” I said. “Meta Stilling.”

“Was that a part of the deal you attempted to make with the Dungeon Master?” asked Raven.

“No,” I said. “And if it would risk getting still magic excluded … well, it’s not a lynchpin magic, but it would be one of the worse ones for me personally to lose. Sunk costs or not, powering up was a significant investment.”

“What you need is a way to fly,” said Raven.

“Yes,” I replied. “There’s a silvered surfboard at the castle in Glassy Fields, but even that wouldn’t be fast enough to keep up with Perisev. Hit and run is a viable tactic for her pretty much no matter what.” I had always hated flying monsters in D&D, both because three-dimensional fights were hard to conceptualize and represent, and because air superiority invalidated huge chunks of the normal game experience, leaving a guy with a sword sitting on the ground staring up at the sky with a scowl and no possible recourse. Perisev’s sheer impossible speed in the air compounded that problem: she could move just close enough to launch a ranged attack, then zip away to safety.

It was frustrating. I’d been prepared for her to come in swinging, for us to have a minutes-long epic battle that would have ended with one of us dead. Instead, it looked like she was going to try to wear me down. The first blast of dragonfire back in Necrolaborem had shown her that Grak could put up a moving ward against it, while the second blast had shown her that I could parry it. Beyond that, she’d tested my ability to find her: she’d been waiting in this small city for me.

She didn’t know that the clock was ticking, but she was being cautious about how she attacked, and that was going to eat time. It was smart, but I hated it.

“Alright,” I said as I chewed on my thoughts, trying not to stress about getting weaker with every passing moment. “I’m putting on Meta Stilling, may the Dungeon Master have mercy on my soul.”

Raven nodded, and I took a bottle from within my bandolier, pulling out the soul of a still mage I’d killed back in Li’o. It was the work of only a moment to scrape out his skill and take it for my own, which put a stop to all five of the skill decay afflictions currently affecting me.

I wondered if this was how religious people felt when they transgressed against their gods. Absolve me of my sins, o lord. Or let me pay penance. Something, anything, just don’t strike me down.

“Okay,” I said.

“Keeping skills high is not actually a plan,” said Raven. She was looking at the compass. “She moved in the direction of Anglecynn, but appears to be stopped for now, with her probability distribution spread out over a wide area near the Achrish Grass Desert.”

“I think it’s time to go back to Poran,” I said. “We can still wait for her there. We don’t have a large enough collection of fast travel entads to chase her, not at the speeds she’s going.” There were a number of travel entads included in the collection that Amaryllis had gotten from Anglecynn, but most of those were relatively slow or otherwise limited, and for that reason had largely been left in circulation, acting as crucial parts of the Warrens.

“Did you want to call in the Egress now?” asked Raven. “We have less than an hour to wait on the teleportation key.”

“Hrm,” I said. “We’ll call it in. Let me draft a note.” I took the Fourfold Flask from my bandolier, then a pencil and paper, and after a quick moment, put it into the slot that Primaryllis would be checking. (The Fourfold Flask was cool: I didn’t really like using it as a glorified international cubby hole, but now was not the time to be raising that objection again.)

“No movement.” said Raven, after fiddling with the compass for a bit. We were waiting in silence, still tensed.

There were people around us, and they were starting to move. I saw some of them running between buildings, taking cover. I don’t know what they made of us, but I had switched my armor over to the element of fire, in anticipation of the dragonfire somehow getting the better of me, and I hadn’t yet switched back to something that was a little less eye-catching.

“It would have been good for us to get an open line of communication with her,” I said. “Then we could at least talk about our problems and try to work out some solution that works for both of us.”

“She thinks you’re an inadequate protagonist,” said Raven.

“Well, if that’s true, fuck her,” I said. I frowned, with my hand on the cup, waiting for the telltale feeling of the note being grabbed. Amaryllis was taking her sweet time. I looked over at Raven, who was still fiddling with the compass, not that it was showing anything new. The Dorises didn’t actually give updates in real-time, which we’d been warned about. “We didn’t leave Necrolaborem in the best of shape. If this cat and mouse stuff goes on much longer, there will be problems there. We kind of decapitated their dictatorship without leaving anything in place.”

“That’s true,” said Raven. She was staring at the compass, and I was watching through her eyes, seeing that there was nothing to see, just a blob of probability marked on the map for where Perisev was likely to be.

“I do wonder whether this subversion bullshit is a result of how things went with the Dorises,” I said. “We went into the big scary abandoned blood facility and made friends with the boss monster there, so for Captain Blue-in-the-Bottle, instead of a giant fight against hordes of zombies, or zombie mages, or whatever horrible creations he might have had, he concedes to us and then tells us about a lot of the problems that have been quietly festering for hundreds of years and need to be dealt with because we stuck our noses in it. Or, not because of it, but because we’re the ones who might be able to. And then Perisev doesn’t come in for a straightforward fight, one-on-one, or better, her against the party, she’s doing this bullshit.” I waved my hand in the air, gesturing vaguely at all the bullshit.

“You think that the Dungeon Master is responding to you?” asked Raven, looking up at me.

I felt the note I’d left slip from its compartment in the flask. It would take some time for her to write a response. “I don’t know,” I said. “Yes. I just don’t know whether it’s retribution or something else. Not that I would have preferred a giant fight through hundreds of zombies, but it would have been a lot cleaner, and the efforts to get souls bottled, and to find homes for all those children, that would have come afterward, with some catharsis.”

“We’re not going to find homes for all those children,” said Raven. “The world simply doesn’t have the will, even if it technically has the means, which it might not.”

“Yeah,” I said. “You know, it occurs to me that there’s a parallel to Uther and his mass dracocide. There were lots of them, too many mouths to feed, more than the world could handle. So he just killed them all.”

“That was different,” said Raven. “You know that.”

“I know,” I said. “Probably one of the worst things that Uther did though, and he escaped with the moral high ground.”

“No one knew about it,” said Raven. “It was a secret that he kept. Whether it was moral to kill those dragons or not … There was no containing them. He thought about trying to educate them, but they were dragons, notoriously independent and willful creatures.” That got an internal ‘yikes’ from me, which I decided it wasn’t the time to verbalize. “But there were worse things that Uther did, depending on how you’re counting. His treatment of the orcs gets him lambasted in certain circles.”

“Well,” I said. “From my perspective, he took a lot from how the United States and Canada treated the natives. Removing orcs from their families, deliberately erasing their history, all these methods of cultural destruction, changing their ways of life through force — I mean, he had to have been thinking about that, right? He knew his history as well as I did, probably better.” I was still waiting on a message back from Amaryllis. Sections of the flask were getting used, those set aside for other channels of communication. “Whatever,” I said. “I’m still going to kill Perisev.”

“I didn’t say you shouldn’t,” replied Raven.

“And I’m still going to kill Blue,” I said. “But I’m going to wait until after we’ve figured out how we’re going to deal with all the people he’s got under his thumb, rather than killing him and then dealing with the mess afterward. Call me an incrementalist, I guess.”

“It was a slur in Uther’s Court,” said Raven, wincing slightly. “Not literally, but it was one of the worst things that he could call you when you opposed one of his reforms.”

“Doesn’t surprise me,” I said. I was going to explain some of his high-school age philosophical outlook, but I got the message back from Amaryllis, and opened it up to look at it. “The locus is getting skittish,” I said, reading directly from the note. “Amaryllis doesn’t know why that should be the case, and Solace doesn’t know either. There’s no sign of any dragons so far. Amaryllis is worried that while we have eyes on Perisev, we’re open to other attacks.”

“Tommul?” asked Raven.

“Unclear,” I said. “Tommul lost an eye, and he backed down in Anglecynn, though maybe that was the imminent threat of the Cannibal keeping him at bay, rather than common sense. I’m not sure where a dragon gets a replacement eye from, or if he’ll just be permanently maimed.” Dragons had generalized magic resistance, which didn’t always work in their favor. “And I imagine that he’s pretty pissed off about people thinking that it was me who took out his eye.”

“She’s on the move,” said Raven. “Distribution is skewed, but it looks like she’s moving in the direction of Poran, ETA is an hour.”

“The Egress is faster than that,” I said. “I’ll have Amaryllis send it, we’ll be on our way back, I guess. No idea whether she actually means to hit it, or if she’s just baiting us again.” I looked at the map through her eyes, and had a strangely familiar sensation that took me a bit to place: it was like watching someone else use a computer while wanting to snatch it away from them so I could be in control.

I wrote out the note, hoping that I wasn’t making a mistake of some kind, and was thankful that the note was grabbed from the flask almost as soon as I’d put it inside.

Gilding the Lily

The Egress was incredibly fast, and landed in the park five minutes later, going well in excess of a thousand miles an hour in order to do so. It was a better ship than the Underline in pretty much every way but its controls, which were nothing more than a map you could use to select your destination. In a lot of ways, it stripped to the bone the entire notion of using a ship to go from one place to another, taking out all of the interesting things about sailing or shipping, like feeling the movement of your travel, or caring about weather, or steering. If it weren’t for the fact that it was moving through the air in big arcs, it might as well have just teleported people from one place to another.

We got aboard, and I resisted giving a wave to the locals, who were mostly still hiding, either from us, or from the dragon that had briefly landed in their town. I went to one wall of the ship, where the silver skin showed a crude map, and selected our landing site in Poran. It would be good to reunite with the party: I was still keyed up, and didn’t like the idea of giving our enemies two fronts to attack us on, as much sense as it had made at the time.

If you were in the Egress when it was flying, you had no sense of acceleration or movement. It was, for the most part, just waiting in a room for a pretty boring few minutes as it did its thing independent of controls. That was one of the reasons that it was pretty simple to send without passengers: no one needed to touch anything.

We were in the air for about thirty seconds when the attack came. Fifteen foot long claws ripped through the skin of the ship like it was made of aluminum foil, and just after that, as the outer layer was peeled back, the magic of the entad failed, the inertial dampers no longer in play, and all that hidden speed coming to the forefront in the space of a single moment, leaving me flying through the air as the ship disintegrated around us, the last shreds of its magic applied unevenly.

If I hadn’t maxed out Still Magic and Heavy Armor, there was a good chance that I would have died, but I was no mere mortal, at least for the moment. I stopped myself with the wrong orientation, my feet pointed toward the sky and my head away from the bulk of the wreckage, but spun myself just in time to see the follow-up attack coming. My brain was having trouble keeping up with what was happening, and I only registered the claws being gold, not black, seconds after it had actually happened.

Tommul let loose with dragonfire, and I parried it, cleaving the flame with my sword, splitting it perfectly in half, with my body perfectly positioned between the two halves of flame. Maybe having learned from last time though, he wasn’t content to just breathe fire and then watch me roast, he rushed in with claws out and teeth ready to bite. The size difference between us was enormous: he could have eaten a whole mouthful of Junipers. His ruined eye was still ruined, scarred over.

I threw my sword at him and started to drop, knowing that I wouldn’t be able to go faster than him with gravity alone. I didn’t hear the sword hit him, but it would have been pretty damned hard for it to miss, given that he was bigger than the broad side of a barn, and as soon as the sword returned to my hand, I activated its ability, mirroring his wounds — all his wounds.

He swiped at me and missed, because he could no longer see, and I kept falling, trying to get the hell out of his way. I was looking around for Raven, trying to make sure that she had survived, but the pieces of the Egress were still falling, and it was hard to tell what anything had once been. Raven could survive a fall from any height, I was pretty sure. I vaguely recalled her having done that when she’d gotten blown off of Mome Rath, though I hadn’t been there for it. It was mostly a question of whether she’d been able to survive that initial deceleration.

Tommul was flapping his wings and moving around erratically, which made sense, because all of his marvelous draconic sight didn’t amount to shit when he had a second gouged out eye to join his first. He let out a jet of dragonfire, spinning his head slightly to cover the area around him, but I wasn’t anywhere nearby.

I stopped myself in midair.

“Hey!” I shouted to him, amplifying my voice.

He flapped more, but he had zeroed in on my voice, and after only a moment’s hesitation, he dived toward me, spewing out fire, which I easily parried. When he was close enough, claws forward, I dropped down, trying to angle myself so that we would just barely pass by each other. With my infinitely sharp sword extended, I was able to cut him, making a yards-long gash that was at least a foot deep, and another cut through part of his hind leg that I’d gotten lucky enough to swipe at.

I mirrored his wounds again, and was gratified to see gold blood trailing behind him as he followed through on the dive. He slowed and stopped, much lower than he was before, and I dropped down after him, trying my best to land on him. All I had for propulsion was throwing myself, which was simultaneously more effective than should have been physically possible, but less effective than I had been hoping it would be.

I got to him as he was still flapping in place and landed on his back, spamming the sword’s ability to open up eight more wounds, then I lurched to the side to cut at the joint where his wing was attached to his body. He turned back toward me, and blasted me with the full force of his dragonfire, and half my mind was focused on stopping it while the other half was focused on making my cuts. The flames actually touched me this time, not quite stopped by the Still Magic. My armor was inviolable, but I was not, and while the elemental armor was in fire mode, it still didn’t protect me completely. I could feel the dragonfire burning me, and it was horribly painful even with the sensation dampened, but I did my best not to let that detract from separating his wing from his body.

I didn’t get all the way through, but at a certain point, the bone and ligament suffered catastrophic failure, and Tommul began to fall. I stilled myself and spammed the sword’s ability again, feeling only slightly gratified when I saw a wing rip clean off, with the second following close behind it. I turned my attention to the dragonfire, trying to stop it from burning me where I was unprotected, bringing to bear the full weight of every magic I had, air magic to force it to burn without oxygen, still magic to freeze it in place, vibration magic to cool it down, until eventually it went out, with no more than a horrifying burn on my face to show for it. It was a fifth degree burn, down into the muscle of my face, and I wished that I had kept pain off completely instead of turning it back up for diagnostics. I poured on the healing, which offered only partial relief: sudden and intense trauma had a tendency to drive straight down into the soul.

He had burned my entad bandolier, and the Crown of Eyes, and I hoped that I’d gotten them put out fast enough that they would recover. I was thankful that I hadn’t taken more of my gear with me: the pistol and shotgun that were a normal part of my kit had been left behind.

When Tommul hit the ground, he kicked up dust and dirt, making a loud thumping sound that could probably have been heard from miles away. I watched for a moment, seeing if he would move, then grabbed the collar of my armor and threw myself to him, assisted by gravity for the long drop down.

I wasn’t clear on whether he was dead or just unconscious, but I moved in at speed anyway, and started hacking away at his neck, which let out gallons of shiny golden blood once I was far enough in. He heaved once, and I darted back, but it was just his last breath, not a gout of flame.

Tommul, the Wise and Mighty, defeated!

“Good riddance,” I tried to say, but my face still hurt, and the muscles hadn’t healed in quite right. I was going to have to fix that, and soon, but Amaryllis had the backup copy of my body data stored on a natal soul. I didn’t know how I was going to get back to her.

Tommul had landed in a forest, shattering trees when he came down, and there were small bits and pieces of the Egress still raining down. I was watching for her though, and I finally saw Raven, her cloak billowing out behind her, helping her to descend like it was a parachute. Her body was limp beneath it. I started running through the trees, trying to track her descent. I finally caught up to her a hundred yards from where I’d started, and made a leap up into the air in order to catch her, stilling us both to give us a softer landing. She wasn’t moving or opening her eyes, which was a bad sign, especially since she wasn’t able to sleep.

“Fuck,” I muttered, trying to ignore the pain in my mouth as I spoke. I reached forward to open her eyes, but my fingers were stopped by the invisible barrier that protected her head. She was breathing though, and her heart was still beating away in her chest. I reached down to take her hand, and pumped healing magic into her, hoping that it would help. Her eyes fluttered open after just a moment, and she stared up at me.

“Wha’ happened?” she asked.

“Dragon attack,” I said. “You okay?”

“Prolly just brain damage,” she replied, slowly sitting up. “Your face.”

“Yeah,” I said. Whatever damage the Crown of Eyes had taken, it was still functional, and I could see scars, mostly on the right side of my face, where I’d been hit with a full blast that all the magic I had access to couldn’t quite save me from. It was reddened but otherwise normal, the healing magic having taken me through the early stages of the burn and out the other side. I was no expert in burns, but it seemed to me that it would probably be back to normal in a few days, maybe with a different skin color there.

“You got her?” asked Raven.

“Him,” I said. “It was Tommul. I cut off his wings and then slit his throat.”

Raven sat up. “The compass,” she said, looking around and patting her pockets, before finally stopping and looking at me. “Poran.”

“Probably,” I said. “Are you ready to go?”

“I,” she said, then stopped, looking around the meadow. “The Egress, was it —”

“Unrecoverable,” I said.

“Then how’re we getting there?” she asked, getting into a sitting position. Her speech was slightly slurred, which wasn’t a good sign.

“I just need to believe,” I said. I stood and held my hand out to the side, willing the locus to appear. I was in its domain, and in theory, it knew what was happening with me, but I had virtually no sense of what it would actually take in order to get a message. The locus had come to join me on the airship, and then left to return to Poran. All that had been done with Solace along, which seemed like proof that — no, that was the wrong way to think about it.

I was standing in the domain of the locus. I was always standing in the domain of the locus. That domain wasn’t really a concrete thing, even though I could see its fuzzy boundaries. Instead, it was conceptual, artistic, a nebulous thing that I was a part of. The domain was a context, and I existed inside of it. It was like all my best ideas before I started nailing them down and making sacrifices in the name of consistency or realism, when they were still that elemental spark of promise. I was a part of the idea of the domain, sewn into that spark of promise at the base level.

Reimer, the alternate one who lived on Aerb, had told me that all my worlds ended up shitty because all I did was focus on the shitty stuff. I didn’t really think that was true. My worlds ended up shitty because I had a depressive disposition, and because my hot take on the real world was that it, too, was shit. People had trouble working together. There were leechers and mooches, petty authoritarians in every school, office, and shop in the world, fundamental biological truths that we were fundamentally biologically incapable of tackling, systems that got so big and so fucked that no one could ever unfuck them or replace them. Worldbuilding was, at least a bit, my retreat from the real world, but I kept bringing the real world into it.

In trying to commune with the locus, I was pushing back against that, tapping into the raw, elemental well of ideaspace, trying to find some spark that I could hold onto without letting it get attached to that poison of reality. I was capable of it, I knew that about myself now, though I wasn’t sure that I had before. It was the easiest path to thinking like a druid that I knew of, the best way I had of calling the locus to me.

It came as an image, that of a small girl in a blue dress, down on one knee, drawing in power from the fields of wheat around her before launching herself into the sky with a wide smile, and I held it there rather than developing it, trying my best not to contain the idea, or contaminate it. It was my instinct to attach rules, to think of explanations, to work out systems and the logical consequences of the rules I’d thought up, to attach costs, or metrics. I kept all that away from the germ of an idea, resisting the temptation.

I closed my eyes, then took off the Crown of Eyes, and held out a hand. When I felt fur, a wave of relief washed over me. That was only the first step though, the second —

I was on Poran. I opened my eyes and looked around. The change might have been subtle, but I had too much in the way of extrasensory effects, and water magic alone would have let me know that I was in a wildly different location, the rivers and creeks that threaded through the woods we’d been in replaced by the sea around us.

“Thanks,” I said as I put the half-melted crown back on, which let me see things from the point of view of the locus: there was a looming storm on the horizon that wasn’t there in real life. No one else was in the area, which I had to wonder about, given that the domain was where we planned to make our last stand. It was big enough that there were areas that weren’t occupied, but I wondered whether I had been taken somewhere out of the way on purpose. Raven was nowhere to be seen, which was a problem, since now I had no way to get her, but I wasn’t going to blame the locus for that, given that its assistance was a long shot.

“Mind giving me a ride to the others?” I asked.

In response, she lowered her head, and I climbed onto her. I had never been a fan of riding horses, but riding the locus was a lot different, and I’d done it enough to feel at ease. From her perspective, looking through her eyes, I wasn’t riding her at all, we were two deer, doe and buck, bounding together through the woods in a playful way, hurrying under the darkening sky. It was hard to know what the locus knew, but I imagined that it could feel the tension in the air and the threat of imminent attack.

The others were near the tree, and stood as they saw me approach. It wasn’t just the rest of the party and the wannabe druids, but a contingent of tuung as well, two fireteams that I recognized as being elites among them.

“Status report,” said Amaryllis as soon as I climbed down.

“Tommul attacked the Egress while it was in flight,” I said. “He’s dead now. Raven had the compass, but she’s not in contact with us right now. Fourfold Flask was with me, but it was in Rilke’s Strap, and that’s not working right now.”

“Let me look at it,” said Grak, holding out his hand. I took it off and handed it to him.

“Your face is fucked up,” said Amaryllis. “It hurts?”

“A bit,” I said.

“Which means that it really hurts,” she replied. “You took a blast of dragonfire?”

“I mean, I did fight a dragon,” I replied.

“Star Body?” she asked.

I glanced at the wannabe druids, who were close enough to hear, and made sure that our conversation was muted to them. Amaryllis was the one applying vibration magic to do the muting, but it still made me nervous enough to check her work. “The alterations are intact, but that one didn’t help me. It was never a guarantee. Flame breath at incredibly close range is a worst case scenario for dodging.”

“And you’re okay?” asked Amaryllis. “How’d you come back?”

“The locus brought me,” I said. “Not Raven, unfortunately, though I’m not sure why. She’s not going to be critical to the coming fight with Perisev though. I’m worried about her, but she can’t be the priority.”

Amaryllis frowned slightly. “You’re sure that your power will hold?” she asked.

“Yes?” I asked. “I have Meta Stilling, that was in the note.”

“I just mean,” said Amaryllis, shifting slightly to adjust her armor. “You made a prayer to the Dungeon Master. You made a compact. From what you said, it was explicitly for the next fight. You’re talking about breaking that compact. It’s not something that should be lightly done.”

“Oh,” I said. I tapped my foot. “Look, the fight against Tommul — I blinded him from the outset and from there, it wasn’t all that difficult. I’m not saying that I couldn’t have done it without the power I currently have, and there’s a chance that I would have died in the initial attack, or the follow-ups, but most of the real work was done with the sword, which took him from one eye down to none. Cutting his wings off and slitting his throat … probably not possible without an infinitely sharp blade, but I don’t think that it should count as the battle I was talking about.”

“Are you willing to stake your life on that?” asked Amaryllis. “Try to see it from his perspective. You made a promise, and you’re trying to bend it, maybe even outright break it.”

“If the Dungeon Master has a problem with it, then I’m pretty confident that he wouldn’t strip me of my power while we’re right in the middle of things, he didn’t with Mome Rath,” I said. “Perisev will be here in a half hour, based on the last information we have, to take me down a peg now —”

Achievement Progress: Super Exclusive 2/40

“That motherfucker,” I said.

“Juniper,” said Amaryllis.

“Something was excluded,” I replied. “It was —” I stopped in my tracks. I felt slower, less sure of myself, my sword no longer a pure extension of my being. But it wasn’t just that, it was almost everything else. Magic had been stripped away from me, sensation had been stripped away, it was all still there, but muted. And soul sight, which I’d been leaning on, was gone.

“Juniper, talk,” said Amaryllis.

“I think it was Essentialism,” I said.

Amaryllis closed her eyes, and I was sure that she was focusing on her own soul. I did the same, but I could already feel that so much was missing that was the only explanation. Scaphism was gone, taking the buffs with it, as was Skilled Trade.

“Fuck,” I said. I couldn’t gain access to my own soul. Spirit was still there, thankfully, but that was a very thin silver lining. I could feel that all of my bonuses were gone. Wherever the exclusion zone was, if there was one, it wasn’t here.

“This is bad, Juniper,” said Amaryllis.

“Good, in some ways,” replied Grak. Amaryllis looked at him for a moment, then nodded.

“No more burning through my own bones,” I said, trying to think through the implications.

“No soul links,” said Grak.

“That’s long-term,” said Amaryllis. “We need to be thinking about Perisev, if she’s still going to be coming in hard. Half an hour, less now? That’s not a lot of time, and we don’t have a way of stopping her, let alone killing her. Did you try memetics?”

“No,” I replied. “They’re not anticipated to work, are they?”

“No,” said Amaryllis. “Just curious.”

“When I went at Perisev, she bounced away before I had a real chance,” I said. “With Tommul, I started off blinding him. There wasn’t much time for testing in either case. We should send someone for the body, by the way. Butchering a gold dragon will probably give good materials.”

“We don’t have a plan for the next half hour yet,” said Amaryllis. “Let’s wait on talking about the next day.”

“Speaking of gold,” I replied. “It’s probably time for me to become a gold mage.”

“Now?” asked Amaryllis, furrowing her brow. “It’s not something that can be undone.”

“Like you said, we don’t have a plan,” I replied. “It’ll let me fly, that’s something. Perisev is frighteningly fast, and she’s going to try to roast me alive, so … best defense I have against dragonfire, short of being next to Grak, is still magic, and that combos with gold magic in terms of keeping the fire from actually touching my skin.” Still magic by itself, even at a high level, was inadequate.

“Call of the gold,” said Amaryllis.

“I can handle it,” I said. “Do what the gold wants, then fight the dragon after. And given that fighting the dragon might be necessary to keep the stash of gold … it’s not going to be a long-term arrangement.”

“Many gold mages say that,” replied Grak.

“If you object for personal reasons, I won’t do it,” I said.

“That would be idiotic,” said Grak.

“Really, really idiotic,” nodded Amaryllis.

“I’m just offering,” I said. I was worried that the offer would seem like a bluff to him, or coercion, and wanted to make sure that he knew I was serious. “We can find some other —”

“No,” said Amaryllis. “We’ll get the ritual set up. The plan will be for you to engage aerially as soon as she’s within range, and hope that you can beat her one on one. We’ll deal with the soul magic exclusion after it’s all over.”

I looked at Grak and bit my lip. “Is there an argument for Grak riding me?” I asked.

Amaryllis and Grak stared at me.

“I would have a bubble ward against dragonfire,” I said.

“You’ll be accelerating too fast for me,” said Grak. “I do not believe there’s any way to create something like inertial dampers using a ward around myself. I could slow you down with velocity wards, but that would defeat the point.”

“Alright,” I said. “Then let’s get the ritual going.”

Aside from needing a fair bit of gold, the call of the gold was the big drawback to being a gold mage. It put a cap on how long of a career you could have, and forced anyone you worked with to accept a number of unpleasant concessions, as well as spurring on conflict. The possibility of being asked to do something that you simply refused to do, and losing all power because of it, was something that would immediately stop most people from ever wanting to become a gold mage.

Naturally, polities had tried their hand at harnessing the raw power of gold mages, and done their own work in attempting to subvert the call of the gold. For the most part, none of this had worked. The polities of the world had done the obvious thing and held a reserve of gold bars, hoping to feed the gold mages little by little until they had reached their limits, whereupon service as a gold mage would be summarily ended and a new gold mage would be inducted using the same gold. This was the kind of good plan that failed more often than you’d expect on Aerb, because it was base munchkinry, and the designer of the world hadn’t particularly been a fan of that kind of thing, which was probably a pretty hard principle for any scientist to figure out. In this case, allowing that munchkinry would essentially just mean that gold-rich nations could fund superpowered police and transform the actual gold and wealth-seeking elements of the magic system into nothing more than correlations between a nation’s material wealth and their ability to project force, which wasn’t terribly interesting, since that was already a thing in both the real world, and on Aerb. It was the kind of thing that would have immediately occurred to me as a designer of magic systems, and had predictably been cut off at the pass on Aerb.

The first thing that the call of the gold would request of you would be to secure your store of gold, keeping it safe and inaccessible, so that it would be truly yours, rather than sitting in a bank, or worse, under the control of a sovereign. Aumann, the gold mage that we’d killed back in Barren Jewel, hadn’t just made a vault with wards around it at the top of a tall tower because he was taking sensible precautions, he had done it because he’d been required to. The call of the gold knew things independent of the gold mages, information like where gold was stored and what kind of defenses a vault had, and it would know if you tried to cheat the system. Worse, it knew what you knew, which meant that it was even harder to circumvent its will.

Being a gold mage was like having a little devil on your shoulder, one that was enormously greedy, didn’t trust people, and couldn’t be reasoned with.

I was almost looking forward to it, just to see what it was like.

We performed the ritual with five pounds of gold, with a street value of about ten thousand obols. It was only a small fraction of what we had available, but part of the point was to test it and see what kinds of demands would be levied against me in the first few minutes. From what we’d read, and information provided to us by outside sources (the kingdom of Anglecynn and Uniquities being the two big ones), it was entirely possible to fail as a gold mage in the first several minutes of having become one, simply because the demands were too high for you. We were well-positioned on Poran though, fairly far from any major cities, and I was hopeful.

The ritual itself involved placing the gold into an inscribed circle and then completing a few marks at the margins, which could be done with nothing more than a ballpoint pen. We’d had this all ready to go for ages: Amaryllis had a piece of paper with the requisite marks on it inside Sable, meaning that we could get it going in an instant, cutting twenty minutes or so of time down to more like three, every step that could be done in advance having already been accomplished months ago.

Skill Unlocked: Gold Magic!

Achievement Unlocked: I love gooooooold!

The gold shimmered once, signifying that it was marked, and then went inert.

I lifted off the ground as a test. It was disappointing, more like slowly drifting up instead of actually flying, but it was still more than two hundred pounds of force, which was certainly something. Even at this relatively low level of gold, it would be like having a gun on me at all times, as well as the ability to stop a bullet dead in its tracks. That was a pretty great deal for only ten thousand obols.

Skill increased: Gold Magic lvl 1!

Take all the gold from the glove, came a voice in my head. It wasn’t my internal voice, but it was close, with a bit of gravelly depth to the sound. The call of the gold was different for everyone, and I hoped that I wouldn’t have to hear much more.

“Dump the rest of the gold, please,” I said.

“Okay,” said Amaryllis. “Anything else?”

“Nothing yet,” I replied. “I’ll let you know.”

Amaryllis didn’t waste any time. She didn’t push more gold bars from Sable, she pushed a whole pallet of them, all lined up and stacked, ready to go. I did a quick count and some sloppy guesswork in terms of multiplication, but it must have been more than a hundred million obols worth of gold. I had no idea we had so much.

“That’s a fucking huge amount of gold,” I said.

“Yes,” nodded Amaryllis.

Grak was staring at it. My best guess is that he was thinking about how much dwarvish labor had gone into mining all that gold.

Force her to give you the glove.

“Give me the glove,” I said, holding out my hand.

“Why?” asked Amaryllis, her eyes momentarily flickering to Sable, then back to me.

“I’m being asked to,” I said with a shrug. “The word ‘force’ was used, if you don’t hand it over, this whole thing is probably over right now.”

Amaryllis handed the glove over, looking slightly miffed.

Check it for gold.

I tried to pop more gold out, and nothing happened. I hadn’t expected her to hide an additional cache of gold inside the glove, but I wouldn’t have been terribly surprised. After waiting for more instructions, I cautiously handed the glove back to Amaryllis, who slipped it back on.

Mark the gold, said the voice in my head.

I didn’t need to ask what that meant, or how I would do it, because it was already a new bit of knowledge, one that had been put into my head. It was a simple sign, one that needed to be made while facing the gold and close enough to touch it. Maybe more importantly, it needed to be ‘mine’, in a way that was a bit nebulous.

As soon as that was done, I felt a rush of power.

Glass Houses

“I have reservations,” I said to the table of tuung. I did feel a bit odd, being the only human there, and I was definitely damp, since this room, like many in the complex at Poran, was equipped with a mister in the ceiling that sprayed at periodic intervals. Aside from me being human, I felt like there was a bit of undue deference to me. Amaryllis hadn’t personally written very much of the stories that the tuung had grown up on, but whoever had done the writing had done it with a skilled hand, in a way that made propaganda palatable to people who would learn, in the course of their studies, what propaganda was and how it was used. Amaryllis probably wouldn’t have used the term ‘propaganda’, but our group featured fairly heavily in it.

Aside from five of the first generation of tuung, who made up the core of the second generation working group, there was another, of the zeroth generation: Esuen, there by my special request. Her presence was a bit uncomfortable, but she had so far been silent.

“Go ahead,” said Liam. He was our chair. It was hard for me to remember that the tuung were young, because so many of them acted so old. They’d been raised in ideal conditions, and given an upbringing that most adults would have killed for, but they were still basically teenagers.

“The second generation is needed,” I said. “But the first generation, if you’ll forgive me, isn’t to the point of full maturity yet. The first generation is a work of social and cultural engineering the likes of which has only very rarely been seen on Aerb, and while I have full faith and confidence in all of you, what’s being proposed is basically using a prototype to build a second prototype before the first is even finished.”

“Argument from uncertainty and risk,” said Liam, with a nod, labeling it without condemnation or judgment. “Both have been addressed to my satisfaction. There will be inevitable drift, but there are correction mechanisms inherent to our culture. There are specific challenges that the second generation will face that the first generation did not, particularly, we will serve as our own teachers, the scale will be larger — it’s nothing that we’re not prepared for. These risks and costs need to be measured against the pressing need for more of us, and the significant benefits of being able to evaluate the performance of the first generation.”

“Alright,” I said. “But if this doesn’t work out, then we’d be adding to our problems, not taking away from them. It’s a huge investment on our part.”

“Do you believe that these are the end times?” asked Liam.

I stared at him for a moment. Despite my place of prominence in this neo-tuung culture (Miunun culture, I supposed), I was relatively uneducated on its tenets. I’d gotten the abridged version, rather than reading through any of the foundational texts, some of which had been written by Amaryllis, some of which had been written by members of the teaching staff and personally vetted by her. In terms of what they believed, there was a strong focus on selflessness and community, a duty to others, an adherence to the chain of command and the rule of law, honesty and the sublimation of desires, especially fear — she had pulled different parts from different cultures, some on Aerb, others on Earth.

This end times stuff though … it wasn’t unexpected, but I had never heard one of the tuung say it directly like that.

“Er,” I said. “I mean, yes, I think that the world is likely to, if not end, then be so radically altered that it’s barely recognizable, probably within the next few decades, if not the next few months. Or weeks.” Days, potentially, if we do something very right or very wrong.

“The world is ramping up,” said Liam. “We need to ramp up in response. A good portion of the second generation will be put toward this current crisis, but we’ll be needed in order to help resolve other crises that are sure to crop up before we reach the actual end. A large portion of why we want to push here, now, is because it will surely be a necessary step later. The resources needed for the second generation are in place — and we’re going to need them, most likely sooner than later.”

“Okay,” I said, letting out a sigh. There was a certain intensity to the tuung that reminded me of Amaryllis, and I had no idea how she had trained that into them. “I relent, and consider my objections to have been answered.”

“They won’t be tuung,” said a voice from across the table. Heads swiveled to Esuen, who had finally chosen her moment to speak. It was hard not to see her as an old woman, but no, she was still young, just not young in comparison with these people who were technically her children. “All culture, all language, has been stripped from them.”

“The culture is stable,” said Liam. “We’re not going to change it. We understand your concerns and your desires, but —”

“But you’ll do nothing,” said Esuen. “Who will die to bring the second generation to life?”

“Any of us would volunteer our life,” said Liam. “It will be a question of which of the volunteers can be most easily spared, and which is most biologically suited.”

It was a grim reality of the tuung that a male had to die in order to further the next generation, and something that I hadn’t really thought that much about. It was, in a sense, suicide. But if that was what was necessary to continue their species, then I wasn’t going to argue with it, and it had long been my opinion that suicide was your right as an individual. It did sit a bit uncomfortable though.

Esuen said no more, and seemed defeated and withdrawn, as she had for most of the time I’d known her.

“Juniper!” came a yell from across the broad rocks and sparse vegetation of Poran. I looked, and saw Valencia, who began running toward me with a smile.

“Valencia!” I called back as she met me with wide arms. I had known she was coming, but still found myself happy to see her. She wrapped her arms around me, and I hugged her back. It went on for just a bit too long, to the point where I was consciously aware of her pressing her body against my own, and then she pulled back. “You have muscles,” I said, looking at her. When we had rescued her, she had been thin and soft, and in the time since then, she had been working with Amaryllis on strength training, sparring, and overall physical fitness. It was still a little surprising to see clear signs of musculature where her bare arms showed.

“It’s been longer for me,” said Valencia. “Time chamber.” She was still smiling at me. I looked at her face, trying to judge how much time in the time chamber, but came to no firm conclusions.

“And … how are things?” I asked.

“Great!” she replied. “But I’ve missed you all a lot, and it feels good to be back, even if it’s only just for now. Amaryllis has scheduled me for two nights of partying before I go back, in between interviews. How’ve you been?”

“Good,” I said, by reflex. “Actually, kind of shit. I mentioned some of it in the letters, but I’m feeling like I would only be cut out to be the Chosen One in the long term if it were this rigid black and white world where it was always clear what was right and what was wrong.”

“Oh,” said Valencia. “You’d do horribly in that kind of world.”

“I would?” I asked.

“Yes,” she nodded. “You like greys. You seek them out. You like to look at simple things and point out how, actually, they’re complex, multi-faceted things in disguise. Do you not know that about yourself?”

“I guess,” I said, frowning at her. “I feel like you know me a lot better than I know you.”

“Well, the devil’s in the details,” Valencia smiled.

I gave her a glare. “Puns are the lowest form of comedy.”

Valencia laughed. “In that they're the bedrock upon which everything else should be built?”

“Have you gotten funnier?” I asked. “I remember you being quite dull.”

“Oh, well, teasing, now that’s far more elevated than puns,” Valencia replied. “And wait, aren’t you the guy who named her Seconmary?”

I grinned. “It really is good to have you back, even if it’s just for a bit.”

“You know that I would have completely solved the entire Anglecynn arc in about two hours, right?” asked Valencia.

“Yeah, I know,” I sighed.

“And then I would be the one married to Amaryllis,” she continued.

“Don’t you have some work to do?” I asked, teasing her a bit, but very much wanting to spend more time with her.

“Of course, and we’ll talk later,” she said. “I need Grak to fill me in on all the juicy details anyway.”

With that, she flitted off, and, I assumed, began eating through devils in order to peer deep into the minds of pretty much everyone around us. It was, according to at least a few moral systems, completely unethical, but I was skeptical that the second generation project would be a success without it. Beyond that, we would also need her to vet new interim leaders of the NLEZ, which had its own moral problems.

As much as I liked seeing her again, I felt a slight twist in my gut at the knowledge that Bethel was out there somewhere, by herself, with no adult supervision aside from maybe an Amaryllis. I didn’t have details on what was being done, and while I knew that they would tell me if I asked, I hadn’t asked. And if I was going to get Valencia back on the team permanently, it would mean dealing with the Bethel Question at some point, which would partially depend on how her socialization was going, and partly on how much we needed her abilities.

(I had never asked Tiff if it was something the girls did too, but in sixth grade, the boys at my school had really gotten into eating things for minor amounts of money. It was almost always something disgusting, sometimes mushed up cafeteria food, sometimes bugs or plants, and sometimes things that weren’t edible. The worst I ever ate was a napkin with some boogers on it, and before I did it, I sat there trying to psych myself up, not just in terms of getting ready to do it, but trying to visualize this disgusting thing, to make myself believe that it wouldn’t be so bad. And it was bad, naturally, and all the mental prepwork hadn’t done anything for me at all, and might have made it worse.)

I flew across the island to where Amaryllis and Raven were. They had a patio table they were sitting at, with papers spread out on it.

“Status?” asked Amaryllis.

“No new calls from the gold, the second generation is good to go with some logistical and cultural issues to figure out, I invited Esuen to the meeting apparently just to get her depressed about her children, whatever, it’s fine, where am I going?” I said all this at a rapid pace, because I didn’t want to get bogged down in any of it.

“Glassy Fields,” said Amaryllis. “It would have been better to do it with The Underline or The Egress, or with other people, but it’s a prime candidate for a high tier gold mage to smash straight through it all. The wards shouldn’t be able to withstand you, and you can see them, so you should be able to solo it. Beside that, it was one of the first quests that you accepted, and should be one that we knock out before making the suicidal attempt at sneaking past Fel Seed.”

“Alright,” I said, hovering slightly. “Now?”

“Wait,” said Raven. She looked over at Amaryllis. “There’s some discussion between us about narrative and meta-narrative. The crux of the issue is attempting to figure out what we can expect from sending you on tasks that should be simple and fast given your power level. The debacle at Speculation and Scrutiny is a strong argument in favor of you not making this attempt.”

Amaryllis shook her head. “There will be more funds there, more gold, some entads, and presumably something more, unless it’s really just a quest to obtain loot, which seems unlikely given prior evidence.”

“Amaryllis has a theory,” Raven began.

“No, it’s less likely to work if we tell him,” said Amaryllis.

“Do you really think that we’re not characters in this story?” asked Raven. “That everything we discuss is safely hidden off-screen?”

“Glassy Fields was one of the earliest quests,” said Amaryllis. “But it wasn’t one that we could have actually done early on. The nature of the exclusion zone is such that it became much more feasible to do as time passed, and at a certain point, became trivial. We could have done Glassy Fields just after Grak got his big virtue. We could also have hired The Underline or something like it, and dropped straight down to the castle with only relatively minor enemies to fight.”

Raven frowned at her. “Amaryllis thinks of this as a test.”

Amaryllis sat back in her chair and rolled her eyes. “Yes, a test that works less well if the protagonist knows about it, which means that it’s less valid now.”

“Sorry, what was this test supposed to be?” I asked. “What outcomes were you expecting, and how would you differentiate between them?”

“It’s a go/no-go test,” said Amaryllis. “If it goes off without a hitch, it’s a sign that the Dungeon Master agrees with the long-term plan of wrapping things up. If there are complications, but it ends relatively quickly, then that’s also probably a sign that we’re clear to move toward the end game. But if it spawns two more quests, and is clearly only the first step in a long chain, then we know that moving against Fel Seed is unlikely to produce the results we’re hoping for.”

“We still don’t understand the structure of quests,” said Raven, folding her arms. “It will be a data point, but that won’t mean anything, it will just shift the probabilities.”

I stopped hovering and grabbed a chair to sit at the table with them. “Can I lay some knowledge on the both of you?” I asked.

Amaryllis was watching me carefully. “Sure.”

“There comes a time, in almost any tabletop game, where the party will sit there spinning its wheels, trying to figure out what they should do, or what’s required of them, or whatever else. Sometimes they’ll metagame and try to figure out what the DM has prepared, and other times it will stay on the object level. As the DM, it just gets boring, and tiring, and you want them to get on with it. And as a DM … it depends on your particular style, but for me, it never actually mattered, because I was making most of it up as I went along.”

“That’s what I’m saying,” replied Amaryllis, frown still on her face. “We don’t know whether the Dungeon Master of Aerb is ready for this to end, or whether it’s the equivalent of the beginning of the night, when he’s fresh and full of ideas. There are many things that a brief quest to Glassy Fields tests for, but even if it’s just a data point, it’s one that we need.”

“Treat him like he’s just a dude,” I said.

“He’s an entity that has full control over the entirety of our existence,” said Amaryllis. She looked like she wanted to yell at me, but was politely and calmly refraining from doing so. We had these kinds of conversations when talking about the Bible, more than once, because I had a tendency to personify God, and Amaryllis had a tendency to deify him.

“Right,” I said. “But what I’m saying is … imagine that he’s me, and how I would behave.”

Amaryllis shook her head. “It would depend on how you were feeling that day, and what you had planned, and what you had been reading lately.”

I looked up at the sky for a moment and thought about that. “I guess.”

“Juniper, I’ve had long conversations with both you and Reimer about your particular style,” said Amaryllis. “It’s not something that I ever thought I would be an expert on, but here we are. How things go with Glassy Fields will help to illuminate elements of the scenario we’re in. We just suffered major losses, does that mean that we’ll have a bounce back, a period of rest and respite, or is this the start of intensification? I would argue the latter, but that might be a good thing, if it gets us closer to a satisfying end to all this.”

“She hopes that it will be a blowout,” said Raven.

“Alright,” I said. “So do we agree that this is up to me, whether we want to risk an explosion of complexity and quests when all we want is loot and a confirmation that we can head into the endgame?”

“Yes,” nodded Raven.

“I suppose,” replied Amaryllis. “It’s a less effective test now that we’ve had this conversation.”

“Narrative depends on viewpoint,” said Raven, sounding exasperated. “Uther goes into this in Degenerate Cycles, which I know you’ve read.”

“It’s conceivable for someone to disagree with Uther, isn’t it?” asked Amaryllis. “And as Perisev said, Uther and Juniper are playing under different rules, different frameworks. I don’t think the distinction that she proposed, stories placed against stories about stories, is necessarily the one that makes the most sense, but it’s at least an explanation for what’s going on. Juniper’s preferred frame is that the difference is mostly a matter of DMing style, or attitude, and I don’t know that’s right either, but —”

“I’m going to take off,” I said. “It’s not that I don’t care about this, because I do, but if I were the Dungeon Master, I would want someone to take the initiative instead of talking in circles for another hour or two. Grak fixed Rilke’s Strap, so you can talk to me via the Fourfold Flask if you need to, unless I get killed, or have to run an errand for the gold, or whatever.”

“Are you okay?” asked Amaryllis.

“Yeah, fine,” I said. “Ready for some real downtime, but that’s going to be in short supply until I give up gold magic. Maybe once I do, we can find a time chamber and I can just … take a year or so to not have any obligations.”

“I’ve been in a time chamber with you, Juniper, you would want out before three weeks were over,” said Amaryllis, which she said with a smile, but still kind of stung, because she’d done who-knew-how-long so far without problems.

“Well, whatever,” I replied. “Don’t have too much fun without me.”

By far the best part of being a gold mage was being able to fly. I grabbed the map, put it into my bandolier, then lifted off into the sky, allowing the Isle of Poran to grow small beneath me. Once I was far enough up, I pushed hard, flinging myself through the clouds and hoping that I had enough drag that it would look like I punched a hole through them. That got me damp, but I dried off quickly once I was through the other side, using gold magic to push the water away, and I sailed on, faster than the speed of sound, toward Glassy Fields.

It felt good to be on my own. I was on a mission, but still, it was freeing, like I had permission to temporarily stop worrying about what was happening in the rest of the world. My mind tried to go to the millions of people in the NLEZ, but I directed it elsewhere, which wasn’t hard, given how vast and beautiful the land below me was. Aerb hadn’t gone through the same things Earth had gone through, and was far more wild and untamed. Industrialization had been quite different, and colonization had arguably not happened, or at least not to the extent that it did on Earth. If it weren’t for a half dozen different things, I might have called it a fantasy world in the derogatory sense, the kind of place that you would dream up as a coping mechanism for the real world.

Those half dozen different things though … they were pretty important deal-breakers. I could imagine an Aerb that didn’t have them, no consequences for the use of void, no risk of exclusion (and better balancing so that exclusion wouldn’t be necessary in the first place), cut a few of the exclusion zones that were actively creating misery, make a few updates to sapient rights, eliminate the hells so that soul power wasn’t a moral problem, things like that. It wouldn’t take much work, for a god.

I wasn’t going back to Earth, when it was all over.

Flying through the air, feeling my raw power push back against the turbulence, I couldn’t imagine sitting in high school listening to a teacher who didn’t want to be there give a lecture to students who also didn’t want to be there, about things that no one was very interested in. Maybe college would have been better, and maybe it wouldn’t have, but after that would come a career in some field or another, and I knew enough about the working world to know that most people didn’t like their jobs. From what I knew about myself, I didn’t think that I would be the exception, almost no matter what field I ended up going into. Even if the people of Earth got their collective shit together, I wouldn’t have put good money on being happy there.

On Aerb … even if I had to give up all my magical powers, and my knack for picking up new skills, and just be a regular guy going to a regular job — well, I was a multimillionaire, so I just wouldn’t have to, and my smoking hot wife who probably wasn’t just pretending to love me was effectively the leader of two, soon to be three nations — the deck was stacked in favor of Aerb, simply by my circumstances. But even if it hadn’t been, even if I were living as the average Aerbian, or some version of myself that had a parallel to what I would have been on Earth, I still thought that I would have liked Aerb more, just on its merits.

Aerb had big towers that no one had an explanation for. It had rivers that sometimes ran backwards, fish that exploded if the light of a full moon touched them, metals that turned soft like putty when you sang to them, billions of tiny little things to seek out and understand, to soak in and enjoy. Earth had that too, it did, but the scale on Aerb was so much different, so much larger.

No one was asking me to come back, or telling me that I should, but I had read enough stories about people transported to another world to know that it was common. I had always hated that aspect of the Narnia books when I was growing up, how the children always had to go from being kings and queens to weak, powerless children in the middle of the worst war in their world’s history. If I had to go back like that, to return to fifth period English class with only a slowly fading memory of what had happened … It was a haunting thought.

Luckily, there was a Zone of Adventure to distract me.

Glassy Fields was relatively benign, as exclusions went. Thousands had died when the exclusion happened, but no one lived within the zone, and it generated no unhappiness or depression. The exclusion zone just sat there, a place that was hostile to life, but which didn’t require or really even suggest that life should come in. It was, in some ways, a graveyard for glass magic, and unhappy in that respect, but it was old enough now that it was a tourist spot, a place with towers built around the edges to look in, and souvenirs that you could buy from shops that were just off the rail lines. Glassy Fields was an exclusion, but it was one whose tragedy was far in the past, and like the Boundless Pit, there was nowhere else you could see something like it.

When I was ten years old, a big ice storm had come through while we were visiting my uncle in Ohio. It had coated the trees, the cars, the power lines, and everything else in a thick shell, and probably my favorite memory of that year of my life was getting to go out and see all these things encased in ice. Sometimes I would break the ice off, other times just look at whatever was frozen inside. It was virtually certain that the glass magic exclusion zone had taken that memory as the germ of inspiration.

Spotting the zone was easy, because it had a very distinct difference from the meadows and forests around it. There was a bit of a glare from the sun, but only in a few places where the glass was curved just right to reflect sunlight up to me. As exclusion zones went, it was on the larger side, a hundred miles across, and shaped a bit like the side profile of a bell pepper, with a fat end and a narrow one.

Everything in the zone was coated in glass, and anything that sat on that glass for more than a few seconds would slowly have glass grow around it, until finally it was swallowed up. The glass wouldn’t grow to more than a foot of thickness, but once it did, it would start to harden, becoming more difficult to penetrate or shatter. It was, I thought, less pretty than the ice storm, so thick that the shape of what was underneath was mostly lost. The trees in particular looked a bit like mushrooms, with the way that the tops were made big and bulbous. In addition to the casings there were also spikes and edges, the former looking like stalagmites, the latter like snow drifts, but far more deadly, because whatever process was making those shapes, it left them incredibly sharp.

It wasn’t all glass. There was water, and there was life. Only a few varieties of plants could live in the zone, all of them with some kind of adaptation, lifting up little proto-roots just a bit faster than the glass could swallow them up, or floating on top of the water. It wasn’t all that much, but the sparse greenery made the place feel more pleasant, and I far preferred a living environment to one that was dead and entombed.

There was danger, naturally, as there was in most exclusion zones. The sharp edges were the most worrying, at least for people who weren’t me. It was entirely possible to walk through Glassy Fields without armor or magic, if you were careful enough, but a single wrong step might slice open your leg, and if you fell, you were likely to take more injuries. I had heard that there were rare edges that were themselves so hard and rigid that they could cut straight through steel with only the slightest pressure, but I wasn’t sure that I believed that, since the stories of exclusion zones were often overblown. Glassy Fields was benign, and quite pretty in its own way, but because of the tourism industry on its outskirts, there was a lot of incentive to hype it up.

I was immune to Glassy Fields. Both still magic or gold magic had the power to completely prevent sharp things from cutting me, and the fact that I could float over the glass made it so that I wasn’t even touching it.

“I am Superman,” I muttered to myself. “World of cardboard, and such.” The eerie beauty of the place was making me slightly nervous, and I had to consciously remind myself that with gold magic active, I was one of the strongest beings on the hex. Even without it, there was nothing to hurt me.

The vidrics were a small animal that had shards of glass instead of fur, with a fox-like shape and bounding movements, their reddish internal organs visible beneath the glass. They hadn’t originated in the exclusion zone, but once they’d been introduced (or possibly discovered it on their own), they had spread like wildfire. Their glass fur kept the glass from building up on them, and they had the magical ability to travel through reflections, which in this place meant that they could do as they pleased. One by itself was little enough trouble, but in packs, they could slice up a person in a hurry.

I saw them watching me as I floated through, and casually changed my armor over to its fire form, which was the most intimidating among them. The fox-like creatures gathered, dozens of heads sticking up over glass ridges, and I tried not to pay them any attention, because if one of them attacked me, I could obliterate it.

The castle wasn’t too hard to find, because like almost everything else in Glassy Fields, it had been well-preserved. It wasn’t anything too grand, just a summer palace of Uther’s that he’d rarely used, which had been turned into a full residence by one of his descendants before the exclusion had hit.

I went up to the front door and placed my hand on the barrier of glass there. I hesitated, then used the entirety of the force of my gold magic. The glass shattered apart, with pieces of shrapnel bouncing backward toward me, then off my skin. It was a loud bang, probably loud enough to deafen me if I didn’t have a wealth of defensive magic. Amaryllis had seemed to think that I would be able to bypass the wards through brute strength, but as it turned out, I didn’t even have to worry about that, because there didn’t seem to be any wards at all. It wasn’t clear whether they had failed over time, been crushed by the glass, or suffered some other fate. The door was locked, and I spent some time trying to open it gently before finally giving up and blasting through.

The interior of the castle had stale air, and I flushed it away, generating air currents by pushing the air with gold magic. I stepped inside and began looking around, the Crown of Eyes letting me know that there was no one looking at me, vibration letting me be assured of the deep stillness of this place, water magic showing no vague humanoid outlines.

A part of me wondered whether this place had always been meant as a test. It was possible the first moment the quest had appeared had been set up not for then, but for this kind of quest, whose context was communion with the Dungeon Master. There was something nauseating about the circles you could end up going in, if you really wanted to, and I wondered whether religious people ever felt this way, like the Christian God was just constantly testing them, putting out signs that might not be signs, maneuvering the world in ineffable ways. If I broke down the doors and found nothing but the loot we expected to find, would that be because that was what had been set up here, written down in some yellow legal pad long ago as a payoff to a risk I could take, if I wanted to? Or would it be a message, a sign, permission to go after Fel Seed?

I tried not to think about it, because that way lay, if not madness, then at least a seven hour conversation with Amaryllis. I wondered whether I brought that out in her, because I knew that in committee meetings, she tended to be straightforward and efficiency-oriented.

I was on a time limit. The castle had been battened up tight enough that the glass hadn’t forced its way in, and the protective shell had secured it, but cracking open the door had let the glass start to flow in, and given time, it would encase everything on the inside as well. For many, many reasons, there was no hope of ever turning this all into a base, but it still gave me the feeling of cracking open and desecrating a tomb, even though I was pretty sure that no one had actually died here (they’d died getting out of the zone as the glass spread, not within the castle itself).

We didn’t have a layout of the castle, but we did have something of a manifest, which had been written down by one of Amaryllis’ ancestors, then transferred into books, and finally passed down to her. I didn’t know whether it would all be together, or how large of a space I was looking for, but I was hoping that I would know it when I saw it. It would have been good to have Grak along, to check magic for me, but he would have had to ride in Sable, and as much as I liked Grak, I felt guilty about using his abilities, especially when he was busy trying to work on important necromancy-related problems. Unless there was something wholly unexpected, he could have soloed this whole quest by himself, with mobile wards to annihilate glass and the ability to pass through wards even Uther himself had set up. Instead, I would rely on my ability to pulse magical sight, trying not to do it too often for fear of building up a penalty that I would have to wait on.

As castles went, this one wasn’t all that big, and my quick search for magic items only lasted about ten minutes, most of which was spent ducking my head into various rooms. The room that I was looking for was on the third floor, close to what appeared to be the staff quarters. There were, contrary to the item manifest, four silvered surfboards set into special racks instead of just one. That wasn’t a huge surprise, given that when I’d made the item back on Earth, it had been in a set, given to the party at far too low of a level. The utility of them was questionable for my case, but it allowed for fairly rapid flight, so long as they all stayed near each other.

Most of what was here had been taken, with obvious spots in this armory where they would have been kept. There was a small stand with poles that I would have guessed held rings or jewelry, all of which were missing. A magical armory like this wasn’t actually much use unless you had a whole host of magical items that you weren’t using, and the exclusion had been slow enough that most of the stuff had been taken by those who were fleeing the encroaching glass. My guess was that the surfboards hadn’t been taken because they were too unwieldy, though that raised the question of what might have happened to whoever could make them fly. My best shot-in-the-dark guess was that their owner had been one of the early victims.

I gathered the surfboards up, then set them down, my eyes drawn to what looked like a wardrobe. I had always loved wardrobes, partly because I had seen so few of them, partly because my young mind had fixated on them as a gateway to somewhere fantastical. I listened to it for a moment, just double-checking, and wishing again that I had Grak with me for backup. Failing that, I at least wanted my soul sight. A pulse of vibration magic showed nothing magical. I touched the knob with far more caution than it warranted, then opened the wardrobe door.

There was nothing inside.

I stared at the empty wardrobe for a bit, wondering if that was a sign. I would have expected outfits, or something else that would befit a magical armory like this, but instead it was just vacant, whatever it had held taken away. I stared at it for a moment, and decided not to accept that the only thing the wardrobe was there for was holding clothes, a job that it wasn’t actually doing at the moment.

I’d had plans, maybe stupid plans borne of paranoia, but plans nonetheless, for how I was going to uncover the secret of the wardrobe. Instead, the very first thing I tried, pulling the wardrobe from the wall, revealed a secret passage to a second room. The room was small, I could see that right away, but there was something in the center of it, a matte black outfit of some kind that was unaccountably floating in the air. It was tattered and torn in places, and my mind immediately went to entadic designs and the ways that they sometimes faked signs of use.

I pulsed warder’s sight and saw the ward right away, but wasn’t knowledgeable enough to know what it signified. A quick test with my pinky let me know that it wasn’t of the annihilation variety, and a single, golden punch was enough to overload whatever capacity the warder had given the barrier.

The black outfit wasn’t an entad, it was a uniform, one that consisted of a shirt and jacket, with inserts at the elbows for padding. The vest was thick and heavy, armored, and it had pouches at the bottom of it, which had all been opened. I wasn’t really paying attention to that. My eyes had landed on the two patches on the shoulder.

One of the patches had a cob of corn, and on either side, what I assumed was a team or division name, “Corn Squabble”.

The other patch was the flag of the United States of America.

“What the fuck,” I said softly. I reached out and touched it. It felt entirely real.

A Grueling Calm

“I’m going to need to rest soon,” I told the call of the gold as I landed in Necrolaborem. “Too much fighting and flying today.” It had been one of those long days, the kind that stretched on forever by virtue of having started early and been crammed full of taxing things.

There was no response. I was allowed to sleep, I was pretty sure of that, but I was worried that I was going to be on call, as it were. It was late, and I’d had a bit of trouble finding Necrolaborem, since the sun was down. Celestar and the multi-colored stars seemed to provide more illumination than on Earth, but that didn’t help me much when there was cloud cover. I could move the clouds with water magic, but it was a real limiter on speed. I hadn’t brought the teleportation key with me, in part because I was the person who least needed it, but a part of me wished that I had called in for it to be bulk teleported to me.

An Amaryllis was waiting, with tuung around her, and greeted me as I went toward the manor.

“I’m beat,” I said. “Where can a guy go to get some rest?”

“We were going to have a short get together,” said Amaryllis. “Would you be okay putting in an appearance, maybe a half hour or so? You can pass off sleep to the tuung, better to keep you fresh while you’re a gold mage. Night is a bad time to use your powers, but I might end up sending you out.” When she said ‘I’, she meant a different instance of her. “You’re good for social time?”

“Uh,” I said. I thought about Valencia being local, for once, and what I might miss out on. “Sure.”

“It’s not actually a party,” said Amaryllis. “Just to make that clear. It’s an hour-long break from doing anything resembling work, so that we don’t fry ourselves. Studies show —”

I waved a hand, and she stopped talking. “I am sure that I’ll be interested in those studies later, but for now, I just want to rest and relax.”

“Okay,” said Amaryllis, nodding. I couldn’t tell whether she was relieved or disappointed that she wouldn’t have to quote some scientific literature back at me. “Elizabeth will lead you down.”

“You’re not coming?” I asked.

“Someone needs to stand guard over the night,” she replied. “Besides, I’m already there.”

“Okay,” I replied. “Just checking.” I moved forward and gave her a kiss, and she leaned against me for a moment before letting me go.

Elizabeth was tuung, naturally, though one that I hadn’t gotten much more than an introduction to. It was hard for me to tell them apart, especially because the ones that didn’t have inktad or entad gear all dressed virtually identically. We moved through the still-smouldering front part of the manor, then into the elevator, which was guarded by more tuung.

“How are things?” I asked her.

She looked over at me, seeming unsure that I was speaking to her. “Plans are moving along. I don’t have a full situation report on the second generation or on the ongoing cultural diagnostic efforts. I apologize.”

“No,” I said. “I mean, how are you, personally?”

She took a moment to mist herself with the little tank at her side. “The adjustment to the outside world continues apace.”

I chuckled at that. “Do they not train you to talk about your feelings?”

“Not while on duty,” she replied.

“Shame,” I said.

“And how are you?” she asked.

“Oh,” I replied. “I didn’t think I would have to answer that.” I looked at the walls going past us. The elevator had been sped up, but it was still quite a ways to go down. “Being a gold mage has more annoyance than I thought it would. I felt like I would be pushed around and asked to make trade-offs that would be difficult, but it’s mostly been a slog. Too much time flying, not enough goofing off. Do the tuung have goofing off?”

“We do,” she replied. “Amaryllis felt it instrumentally important to allow us freedom and leisure.”

“Hrm,” I replied. It seemed to me like it would be hard to relax when you knew that it was just there in order to get back in shape for the grind. Mandatory relaxation wasn’t quite an oxymoron, but it was close. There was something about the phrasing she’d picked that rankled me, though it wasn’t clear that it was supposed to rankle. “You specified ‘instrumentally’?”

“For the sake of accomplishing some goal,” replied Elizabeth, nodding.

“No, I know the jargon,” I said. “I was just wondering why you felt the need to make it clear that it wasn’t freedom and leisure for their own sake.”

“There’s some argument within the tuung about the studies on which her understanding is founded,” replied Elizabeth. “Almost all of the studies cited in the design document for our civilization used humans or dwarves, with none being specific to the tuung.”

“The second generation committee never brought it up,” I said. “So far as I know, they don’t intend to make any changes on that front.”

“I wouldn’t know,” replied Elizabeth. The elevator came to a stop, and whatever else she was going to say died on her lips.

“Let me know if you’d like to talk,” I said. “If there are concerns that haven’t been brought up in the second generation committee, it would be helpful to me to know prior to the second generation project going into effect. The first generation was a proven success,” and we have an alternate timeline’s worth of data showing that too, “but if there are flaws, I’d like them to be addressed.”

“I’ll think about it,” she replied, looking me over. “In my leisure time.”

“Well, not to put too fine a point on it, but we’re going to have a hundred thousand tuung getting basically the same education that you got,” I said. “And that’s happening … maybe tomorrow.”

“I’ll think fast,” said Elizabeth. We stood together on the elevator for a moment, though it had come to a stop. “Was there anything else?”

“No,” I said.

“Then I’ll take you to the place that Grakhuil has set up,” she said, nodding.

The room was nothing special, just another utilitarian warehouse that Elisha Blue must have built. It had been transformed though, mostly with things that had been taken from Sable, and it was filled with the people who mattered most to me.

“Juniper!” Valencia called as soon as I was in the door. I blinked on warder’s sight for just a moment and saw that Grak had, in fact, created a bevy of wards around the room, which had bunk beds set up on one side of it for the four of them. “We were worried you wouldn’t make it.”

“Well, I’m here,” I said. “Is it a party, or what?” Two of Amaryllis were here, the one wearing Sable almost surely the prime version of her. They were deep in conversation. Grak and Raven were also together, talking, though they’d mostly stopped when I came in.

“Not a party,” said Valencia. “Just a time to relax and not think about work.”

It struck me that there were no tuung in the room, which was a little off-putting. They were a vital part of our operations, and they would be bearing the brunt of the costs involved in making even the smallest dent in the problem of Necrolaborem. I was sure that there were a lot of good reasons not to have them with us, but it still felt unequal in a way that rankled at me a little bit.

“There’s a changing screen, if you wanted to get out of your armor,” said Valencia. She gestured in a corner, where a folding barrier had been set up. “You’ll be sleeping here, right?”

“I’ll be passing off sleep,” I said. “The call of the gold seems to want me here though, in the NLEZ.”

“Ominous,” said Valencia with a nod.

“You wanted to talk about the Matrix?” I asked.

“I’ll wait until the armor is off,” she replied. “Unless you’re okay with talking while you change?”

“Sure,” I replied. “I just need to ask Amaryllis for a change of clothes.”

“She already thought of that and left you some,” replied Valencia.

“Of course she did,” I sighed. I went over to the screen and began stripping off my entads and armor. “So, you watched the Matrix?”

“Yes!” said Valencia. “Unfortunately, no one can be told what the Matrix is, so I had to watch it for myself.”

“Please tell me that this didn’t lead to an obsession,” I said as I took off my greaves. “I enjoyed the movie, but I don’t think that I could handle you being enthusiastic about it for days on end.”

“Oh, my Harry Potter days are long behind me,” said Valencia. “I spent some time in the time chamber, when I needed a break from Bethel. I gained some new perspective.”

“That’s a bit of a shame, if I read you right,” I said. “And that time was what, looking back on things that you used to love, or that were formative, and realizing that you’ve outgrown them?”

“Sure,” said Valencia. I wasn’t watching her, but I could hear the shrug. “What I really like is that there are happy memories to outgrow. I want to leave a trail of happy memories behind me.”

“So you liked the Matrix?” I asked. I had seen it, of course, but it had been years ago, and I hoped that I would be able to add something.

“It’s an interesting concept,” said Valencia. “But it’s a bit philosophically confusing, and I was wondering whether you had some insights.”

“You’re asking me for insights?” I asked. “I mean, I can try, but it seemed fairly straightforward to me. What didn’t you understand?”

“Well, I think I understood it,” said Valencia. “But … they talk a lot about what’s real and what’s not, and it was confusing to me how or why everyone accepted that there even was a real world. Neo takes the red pill, and then he doesn’t suffer from any misunderstanding of the nature of reality after that. He never thinks that the ship he’s on is yet another simulation, even though the simulations are supposed to be perfect, or close enough to perfect that it wouldn’t be hard to patch the flaws. And Neo’s not just being pulled out of the simulation, he’s being told that he’s the only one who can save the world, which you’d think would make him suspicious.”

“Okay,” I said. “So … you wanted a different movie?”

“No,” said Valencia, frowning at me just a bit. “I mean, I understand it well enough, the instinct people have to say, ‘I see clearly now!’ So often that’s just totally wrong and stupid. But the movie isn’t about that. It’s just … uncritical about the whole thing. So what’s it trying to say?”

“Er,” I said. “I honestly think that it is uncritical. That it is just a story about people waking up from a dream to see, for the first time, the real world, without very much time or thought given to, uh, anything like what you’re talking about. That uncritical way that it deals with the difference between truth and fiction, and how you can’t actually tell the difference if the simulation is good enough … that would undercut the metaphor, which is about seeing the true world, and, I guess, how seeing the real world can be painful or exhausting.”

“But it’s a bad metaphor for that,” said Valencia.

“I don’t know what to tell you,” I replied. “Sometimes there’s a powerful metaphor that provides people a language for something, and it doesn’t really matter whether the metaphor holds when you think about it for more than five minutes. As a movie, The Matrix had a lot of impact on the culture, some of it for the special effects stuff, some of it for the philosophy, and I think a lot of the philosophical impact wasn’t because it had any really new ideas, it was that it packaged them in a way that made talking about those ideas easier for lay people.”

“Are you talking about The Matrix?” asked Amaryllis, walking over to us. She wasn’t wearing a glove, and so of the two, was probably the clone. “Terrible movie.”

“Terrible how?” I asked, sighing just a bit.

“Why in the holy hell would they use green lines for their user interface?” asked Amaryllis. “And why are people able to bend the rules of the Matrix through sheer willpower? Who would code in such a stupid system?”

“Did either of you see the sequels, by chance?” I asked.

“There are sequels?” asked Valencia.

“You told me not to watch them,” said Amaryllis.

“Well, I don’t think that they really clarify much,” I said. “Just curious.”

“All I’m saying is that the movie takes the aesthetic of computer programming without taking the time to understand computers or how people interact with them,” said Amaryllis. “If there are reasons that people are able to bend the rules of the Matrix from within it, then they’re contrived reasons.”

“I mean, it could be —” I began.

“Contrived,” said Amaryllis, before I could finish. “A sensible program architect will have physics behave in consistent ways in accordance with the physical reality that they’re trying to create, rather than creating them from the beliefs of the people within the program. Surely the Matrix contains people who have mental disorders, and must be able to account for that, the simplest method being through making a sensible system architecture that connects with the mind through a series of inputs and outputs, rather than using the mind for construction and control of the body without an intermediary process.”

“Okay,” I said. “Granted. But what I was just saying to Valencia is that it’s not actually about that, it’s about the aesthetic, the metaphor.”

“It’s the misuse of the aesthetic that I dislike,” said Amaryllis. “Everything about the premise is interesting, but they fail to execute on any of that. Instead, they go with the chosen one going through a very typical hero’s journey.”

“Nothing wrong with a hero’s journey,” I said. “And look, I don’t want to defend a movie that’s like, two decades old, I’m just saying … you have to use the right lens. You have to understand the story on its own terms. It’s not a story about understanding the existential horror of living in a simulation, it’s about the red pill and the blue pill, which are stand-ins for all kinds of truths about the world, ignoring that truth is a murky concept. And yeah, it’s uncritical, and you can point that out, but you need to also use and understand the frame of the movie itself.”

“Alright,” said Amaryllis. “Fine.” She folded her arms across her chest. “Even if it’s a bad frame?”

“Eh,” I said. “You can point it out, obviously. I just think you’d get more out of it if you took it how it was, rather than how you wanted it to be.”

“Is this related to you going to Perisev’s?” asked Valencia.

“No?” I asked, more than stated. “I mean, now that you say it, sure, I’m sure there’s some connection to be drawn, but most of my time flying home was spent thinking about the Long Stairs, what was in them, and their connection to Earth.”

“Long Stairs?” asked Valencia. “That was … a campaign?”

“Yeah,” I said. “But … we’re not supposed to talk business at this party, right?”

“I might need to sync,” said Amaryllis, frowning at me. “Do I need to sync?”

“Uh, if you want the full context with Perisev, yeah,” I said. “Or I can just tell you.” I looked over at the other Amaryllis, the prime one, who was in conversation with Raven and Grak. “Do you not know anything about the Long Stairs discussion?” I asked. “Because it’s been a busy day for me, and both parts involved that.”

“Shit,” said Amaryllis. “Can it keep?”

“Sure,” I said. “Nothing is going anywhere, at least to my knowledge. This is endgame stuff that we’re preparing for.”

“Alright,” said Amaryllis. “I’ll tell myself to do three syncs, and we can discuss this tomorrow.”

“Stop turning the gears,” said Valencia. “We were supposed to be relaxing, remember?”

“Yes, sorry, it’s just hard,” said Amaryllis. “It’s definitely going to be one of those nights where I need a spell to sleep.”

“Do those work on the clones?” I asked.

“They do,” she replied. “But we can’t self-cast.”

“I can’t self-cast either,” said Valencia. “But I’ve never really had a problem getting to sleep, at least not these days.”

“Well, I’m going to get some rest soon,” I said. “I just need to check in with Grak and Raven first.” I looked at their little group. “And other Amaryllis, I guess.”

Amaryllis came close to me and gave me a kiss on the cheek. “I might give you some company tonight?”

“Sure,” I said, feeling my cheeks get a bit warm and resisting the urge to look at Valencia to see what she made of it.

I walked over to where the other three were talking, and caught the end of Grak’s sentence.

“— because if it did, the dwarves would veto.” He looked relaxed, but the day had definitely taken its toll on him, and beneath the stoicism, I was sure he was eager for sleep.

“They would?” asked Amaryllis, glancing at me for a moment before returning to Grak. “Just out of a sense of preserving the status quo?”

“Yes,” nodded Grak. “It has never been the dwarven belief that equality for individual groups is best served by equality for all. There are many factions within dwarfkind. The consensus is on protecting our own.” His tone was flat, but I knew him well enough to know that he was a bit flustered. Groglir had a habit of putting two opposed statements of fact next to each other without anything to join them, no ‘but’ or ‘however’. It was much more common for him to slip into that habit of opposed statements when he was agitated.

“I understand the mindset,” said Amaryllis. “But I don’t think I can explain how vehemently I disagree with the strategy, tactics, or morality.”

“It is what it is,” replied Grak.

“What are we talking about?” I asked, finally seeing my chance. “I don’t need a full summary, just a description of the topic.”

“Rights for sentients,” said Raven. “We were talking about entads and magical effects, which Amaryllis might technically be considered,” she gestured to the clone, who had sat down on a couch with Valencia. “Specifically, expansions of rights.”

“Huh,” I said. I looked over at the other Amaryllis, and she looked back at me before giving a small wave. “There’s an argument to be made that she wouldn’t qualify?”

“A strong argument,” replied Amaryllis. “In Anglecynn they’re actually structured as being owned objects.”

“Wait,” I said. “Really? Not people?”

“Sorry, I misspoke,” said Amaryllis. “The plan, if the clones were challenged, is that they are owned objects that nevertheless represent my will and count as being me. They haven’t been challenged, so right now, legally speaking, they’re not actually anything. The arguments have not been made one way or another, let alone resolved.”

“But they’re people,” I said. “Sorry if that’s politically naive, but — you said this relates to entads?”

“To a variety of magical effects,” said Raven.

“Alright, I guess I don’t have much input except that’s clearly wrong,” I replied.

“It’s complicated,” said Raven.

“In what way?” I asked. “If they can think and feel like a member of the mortal species, then they deserve rights, don’t they?”

“The issue of rights is a complicated one,” said Raven. “It’s not as clear-cut as that. Uther wanted to package everything up, to make a grand universal declaration, but he ran into problems, because people are so diverse, their needs so varied. A group like the Ha-lunde can be accommodated, but that’s not true of every group, and when rights conflict with each other, or you have issues like voluntary servitude, you immediately run into problems.”

“To be clear, we’re all against slavery?” I asked.

“Well,” said Amaryllis. “It depends.”

“Does it?” I asked. “Does it really?” I stopped for a moment. “Is this because of the existence of the slave species?”

Aerb had a few so-called ‘slave species’, typically those that had been created by ancient or complicated magics and had a pathological desire for ownership, or at least some kind of firmly rooted idea of themselves as belonging to another, or desire to foist autonomy off onto someone else. The exact implementations differed, but it was always biological, not cultural (else they would have been slave cultures, not slave species).

The whole thing was kind of skeevy, but that was what had attracted me to it, back on Earth. I didn’t often include those kinds of things in games, but for a period of time, I had been into transgressive worldbuilding, worlds that were different from our own in ways that violated basic precepts of modern civilization. Some of them got jotted down on sheets of paper that were then consigned to a folder and forgotten, others ended up in aborted draft documents on my laptop, and a rare few made it into a campaign. Some of it was just edgelord garbage, justification for a place that was not too different from the Doris Finch Exclusion Zone, or some of the hells. Other things were just extensions of real world pseudoscience, taking some dumb ideas that people had like phrenology and trying to ponder what the world would look like if those ideas were true. That was where things like the slave species had come from.

“I know it’s not how it is in America,” said Amaryllis. She was watching me, as she sometimes did, paying close attention to my face. “I know that there, you had more of a history of slavery than we ever had on Aerb.”

“There was slavery,” said Raven. “But Uther ended it.”

“Yes,” said Amaryllis with a sigh. “Along with his many other accomplishments, aided by a technological revolution, a sterling wit, gobs of charisma, and the most powerful kingdom on the face of Aerb. And I don’t mean to diminish that accomplishment, but he had a lot going for him in that endeavor, not least of which was, potentially, narrative force.”

Slavery hadn’t been booming business back in Uther’s day, it had been on a decline, largely consigned to those polities where it was so firmly institutionalized that ending it would have been nearly unthinkable. Uther did what Uther often did, which was to write the kind of revelatory tract that would have propelled someone else to instant fame and recognition. Against Slavery was fairly short, not more than a hundred pages, with a calm, easy-going tone and a dense thicket of citations, some of which were arguments and stories of their own. At the very end was the shortest section, which said, over the course of a paragraph, that if none of the preceding reasons were adequate, Uther would personally come to every slave holding polity on Aerb, one by one, and set them right, one way or another.

Of the thirty-one slave-holding nations, twenty-nine of them backed down, putting in place various schemes to step down and phase out the institution of slavery on a five year timeline. The remaining two faced Uther’s full wrath.

“Did he enjoy it?” I asked Raven.

“Enjoy what?” she asked back, confused.

“Did he enjoy sticking it to the slavers?” I asked.

“He did,” said Raven. “A bit too much. When he sent the book off, it seemed like he was hoping for an all-comers fight. And when there were only a few holdouts … this was later into his career, when he held a lot of personal power, when he was so beloved by Anglecynn that they barely batted their eyes at the thought of going to war for a just cause. I think, when we actually got there, storming the gates, he wanted to believe that these were all evil people, irredeemable.” She shook her head. “He gave them opportunities to surrender, plenty of them, called for them to throw down their swords, but the people who were guarding the bastions were the fanatics, the ones who had been convinced that ending slavery was an assault on their way of life.”

“Which it was,” said Amaryllis.

“Which it was,” Raven replied with a nod. “At the time, I felt like him, that they were terrible people defending a terrible tradition, amoral and greedy. But the more I thought about it, over the decades that followed, the more I thought that it just looked that way from the outside.”

“I mean, he was probably right,” I said. “The hand of fate probably conspired to place the worst people in the world before the path of his blade, and when he was finished, all the people who finally surrendered were the ones who had just been going along with things, just scared, desperate, people.” I personally didn’t have much sympathy for slavers of any kind.

“I suppose,” frowned Raven.

“Does it matter to the topic at hand?” asked Grak.

“Kind of, in a way,” said Amaryllis. “In theory, we might one day wield enough power to simply force changes in the same way that Uther did. If the dwarves don’t want magical effects to have recognized autonomy, then Juniper can lay out an argument and back it up with power greater than any individual polity would be able to stop.”

“Controversially, I frown on the genocide of dwarves,” said Grak.

Amaryllis rolled her eyes. “Obviously I’m not envisioning that, I’m envisioning almost everyone agreeing with us right away by the virtue of our arguments, backed up by the raw power we would hold. You don’t need to hurt anyone if they know ahead of time that you’re capable of doing it.”

“Except that it wouldn’t come out clean like that for me,” I said. “I’m not playing by the same script that Uther was. Look at where we are!” I gestured vaguely around us, at Necrolaborem. “This is a messy, complicated situation that’s not going to go away with game powers or killing the right villain. And that’s how it is in real life. You know that, right, Raven? Five hundred years, and you see that it wasn’t just a matter of good or evil, not once the thumb was off the scale? With Uther gone, that’s just not how it works?”

“The entirety of the world cannot be trusted,” said Raven. “So I can’t say that it would naturally be. We can’t even trust Earth.”

“We can’t?” asked Amaryllis. “I mean, I’ve had my doubts —”

“Sorry, I forgot, that was a clone,” said Raven. “There have been some recent developments, but apparently nothing that you felt necessary to sync for.”

“Alright,” said Amaryllis. “Give me ten minutes.”

“You’re not supposed to be working,” I replied. “And hey, sorry to turn in early, but it’s been a damned long day, with more long days ahead of me, so I’m going to get some rest, if not sleep. Also … you should tentatively sync with the clone that’s over at Perisev’s, there was information there that matches up to what Raven knows. So you’d need twenty minutes to get up to speed.”

“Next time we do this, we’ll have a debriefing session first,” said Amaryllis.

“Oh, also, have you synced up with the clone that was with me for taking apart Tommul?” I asked. “We had a discussion about postmodernism that maybe gives another piece to the puzzle.”

Amaryllis sighed. “Fine, go rest, I’ll get you up if it matters enough.”

I nodded. “Thanks. Sorry, I know it’s been a long day for you too, I’m just ready to crash.” I turned to Grak. “Can I talk to you for a second first?”

“Of course,” he nodded, though he seemed surprised. When I went to walk over to one of the bunks that had been set up, he followed behind, and I sat on a bottom bunk, running my fingers through my hair. I decided that I was greasy, and needed a shower. In theory, I could blast away the oils with gold magic, but my control wasn’t fine enough that I was confident that I could do that without obliterating my hair. “What did you need?” Grak asked.

“Just wanted to make sure you were okay,” I said. “I know you’re putting in work, worried that your wards aren’t going to be sufficient, or that you’ll be asked to do something that puts people at risk, and I noticed you weren’t talking too much when it was the four of us over there, so I just thought that the last thing I would do, while I still have scraps of will and energy left to do anything, would be to ask you how you were.”

“Thank you,” said Grak. He sat down on the bunk beside me, and it made me think about whether the beds would actually work for him. It was the kind of thing that I would have expected Amaryllis to think of, but the bunks had to have come from somewhere, and I wasn’t sure that they were built for dwarves, who came shorter and thicker than humans.

“Still thinking?” I asked, after what felt like a long time had passed. I’d switched to Groglir, and hoped that he would do the same. Sometimes it seemed like Anglish provided him with a shield.

“During my time at Barriers, I felt a weight of obligation,” he finally said, switching languages with me. “My father sent letters to me, once or twice a semester, and after every time, I would feel a wave of stress descend to blanket me. I would spend a day or two feeling miserable, not eating, my stomach unaccountably upset. I would have trouble falling asleep, and trouble staying asleep. Then, with time, that feeling would pass, and I would convince myself that I would be able to squeeze out another year, to keep my comfortable lifestyle going.”

“Hmm,” I said. “And you’re feeling that now?”

“It is entirely possible that I am the greatest warder the world has ever known,” said Grak. “It is possible that I can do things with wards that cannot be done by others, even in theory. And yet this is not a position of agency or power. I have no choices, no will to exert.”

“Sorry,” I said. “I never wanted you to feel that way, you know that I’m not just saying that, —”

“I don’t blame you,” said Grak. “I am just explaining my feelings. I make the wards I am asked to make, or more often, that I deem necessary given our situation. I provide for the team. But the goals of the team are not my goals, because my desires are to live a simple life with a few good friends and a riot of civilization to poke my head into from time to time. The world needs us, Juniper, but I have no strong desire to save it. It's an obligation.”

“Huh,” I said. “If I can make an analogy?”

“Of course,” he replied.

“There’s no love,” I said. “There’s duty, but it’s cold, soulless duty. You provide the defenses, but that’s not a fulfilling thing, it’s just rote work, for the most part. It’s a job that you have to keep coming to every day, even though you don’t like it at all, because you need to pay the rent.” Not that I had ever had that experience, but that had been my mom’s description of the working world. “You get through the work for the day, and hope that you’ve done enough, that you’ve earned some rest.”

“Yes,” said Grak. He was staring ahead.

“What can I do?” I asked. “We can arrange time in a time chamber for you, but I don’t know how close to a real break that’s going to be. It’s worked well enough for me, at least in the past.”

“Listening helps,” said Grak. “Speaking about it helps.”

“Okay,” I said. “That doesn’t seem like enough.”

“It’s not,” Grak replied. “But the weight of obligation will still remain. I will be instrumental in these plots.” In Groglir, the word that equated to ‘instrumental’ had connotations of ‘being used as an instrument’. “I cannot be replaced. I do not want the world in which anyone would try to replace me, because the outcomes would be worse. This is the crux. This is where the weight of obligation comes from. If someone could take my place, I wouldn’t feel the weight, and could continue on.”

“Hrm,” I said. “You need a goal.”

“A goal?” he asked.

“Yeah,” I said. “I mean, I’m driven by finding Arthur and ending the shitshow. It’s what I think about, when things threaten to seem overwhelming, which … yeah, is kind of where I am at the moment. There’s an endgame waiting, there will be answers, a resolution. That’s why I push on. But you don’t have that, because for you — I hate to put words in your mouth, but it seems like you don’t really care about Uther, or the resolution.”

“I don’t,” said Grak. “A heaven seems nice, but it is so disconnected from anything we do that I have no faith. There is an alienation from that goal, for me. The work that I do advances us toward it, but the connection is often murky. Sometimes all I can see are my wards.”

“You saved us from dragonfire,” I said. “We’d be dead if not for you.”

“This is true,” said Grak. “But it’s so … reactive. The building of the ward is the active part, and that is done without knowledge of if or when it might ever matter. I have layer upon layer of ward around me, all made just in case they might, some day, be useful.” He turned to look at me. “There’s nothing that you can do, but that you took the time is appreciated, more than I can say.”

“Alright,” I said. “If you ever need to talk, let me know.”

He reached over and squeezed my hand, then stood up from the bunk and quickly made a ward so that the light would be blocked out and I wouldn’t have to hear whatever else was going on.

I’d passed off sleep, which left me in the bunk, staying up at the upper bunk above me, thinking without actually feeling tired. I wished that I could have slept, but while the call of the gold would probably allow that, it didn’t seem prudent. There was a list of things that I should be doing while the call of the gold was active, and after an hour or two, I would probably go do them. But for a time, it was good to be all alone, to be thinking my own thoughts.

I didn’t want to think about Perisev, or postmodernism, or the Long Stairs, and certainly not Fel Seed. So I turned instead to my favorite hobby, building worlds and crafting adventures that no one would ever play.

Homecoming, Part I

It would be a homecoming, in a way, which was a bit of a funny thing for a house, if you really thought about it. Bethel curled up her body’s lips in faint amusement, without thinking about it. Valencia had asked about that, about how Bethel behaved when there was no one around, and it was a complex topic with complex answers.

There was a place that was more or less inside Bethel’s own mind, a memory palace granted by an entad that she’d been fed long ago. There, perhaps because of the nature of the entad, she had a physical form. She wasn’t a house in that part of her mind, she was her interpretation of Tiffany Archer. Most of the time, she pretended that the memory palace didn’t exist, despite its usefulness. The form there did have involuntary facial expressions that roughly mapped to emotions in a human way, perhaps because of the magic that was intrinsic to that entad.

Beyond that, she had her illusory form, which she controlled directly and precisely, and whose shown emotions were entirely deliberate, though sometimes copied from the version of herself in the memory palace. If not that, the emotions were lifted from previous observations of people, altered in some circumstances, but generally copied wholesale. For certain things, Bethel’s memory and cognition were both well in excess of a baseline human. In a way, her outward appearance was the sum of everything she had ever seen inside of her, or at least the parts that had stuck with her. She could fairly easily generate new expressions from whole cloth, but she didn’t often bother when one could be recycled. Valencia claimed that this was unnerving, and Bethel was taking that under consideration.

The other direct form of emotional manifestation was the entad body that they had taken from Li’o. It had been, for the moment, retired. It, too, had some kind of connection to her emotional state, which caused nearly-real muscles to twitch and contract. Like many entads, it was a mystery, particularly in the ways in which its core abilities were warped and enhanced by a connection to her. In its base state, the entad had only simulated relatively inert mortals, with pain reactions but not all that much else.

Bethel had wanted to blame the entad for The Incident, but Valencia had talked her around, as Valencia was wont to do. The entad was not to blame, because the entad had not been involved in other acts, other patterns of behavior, and if the entad contributed, which it might well have, it was only a small part of the story. Bethel had still wanted to get rid of the entad, a feeling which had grown deeper as time had passed, and as a compromise, it was kept in a warehouse somewhere else in the city, out of the sensorium and out of mind.

Valencia didn’t particularly like when Bethel called it The Incident.

“It’s distancing language,” Valencia said. “It’s a way of abstracting what happened. You’ve been doing it quite a bit, and it’s the sort of thing that, first of all, you use as a method of self-deception and disengaging from your own actions, and second, the kind of thing that Amaryllis and possibly Juniper will notice and hate. You need to engage with your own actions, you need to understand them as a part of you. It’s going to be hard to grow and change without that.”

From Valencia’s viewpoint, or at least what Valencia had said, the fact that Bethel had started using distancing language was actually a good sign. It was an indication that she was feeling something about her past actions, in whatever her version of a subconscious was. Deflection, minimization, and distancing were signs that Bethel understood that what she’d done was wrong, and was reflexively engaging in a relatively healthy form of ego protection.

Much of Valencia’s ‘work’, such as it was, involved simply talking to Bethel about various concepts of psychology, and how to recognize them within herself and others. These were, in Valencia’s way of thinking (or, perhaps, a devil’s way of thinking), the basics that needed to be laid down before any actual work could be done. As a metaphor, a person could not build a house without first building or acquiring the necessary tools. The business of toolmaking might seem unconnected with that of housemaking, but it was a vital precursor. Together, Bethel and Valencia had gone through most of the business of constructing the apparatus of change.

There were, to be sure, other ‘lessons’ in the course of this knowledge acquisition, sometimes clear and overt, other times mixed into normal conversation with such sneakiness that they would only become clear in retrospect, or at a particular conversational turning point. There was a particular focus on modeling people, understanding how they worked and why they did what they did, as well as what Valencia called the ‘moral landscape’. At first, Bethel had thought that Valencia would sketch out some rigid system of thought, of the kind that Bethel wasn’t wholly ignorant of, but instead, Valencia seemed all too willing to throw every possible moral philosophy at Bethel, even those that came to contradictory conclusions about how to behave.

“It’s not really about the systems,” said Valencia one night, while the two of them were drinking tea together. “They’re all subjective, all relative, all arbitrary, but that doesn’t mean that they’re worthless, or that they don’t matter. They have their arguments, and I think by studying a lot of them together, you can cross-pollinate those arguments, bring them in when you have to make a decision. And that way of thinking, trying to examine things from other points of view, to see how they work under different moral systems, helps us much more than looking things up in a book, or doing rigid calculations.”

“But as for making actual decisions?” asked Bethel.

“Take them as they come,” replied Valencia. “In point of fact, I don’t think that you’re the sort of person who is amenable to a rigid moral code created by someone else. But you are the sort of person who can think things through, weigh options, investigate the internal lives of others, and come to your own conclusions.”

“But those conclusions might be wrong,” replied Bethel. She took a sip of illusory tea, but paid some attention to the taste, temperature, and feeling of the tea in the pot, the better to be in the moment.

“They might,” replied Valencia, shrugging, as though it was nothing. “Our job is not to be always and forever right, but to seek truth and moral superiority. Our job is to try.”

Bethel had been doing ‘better’. She and Valencia had largely taken over the underworld of Orrangush, and were edging in on the overworld as well, partially by virtue of how connected those two landscapes were to each other. Bethel hadn’t killed anyone since arriving in the city, and had injured people only a small handful of times, always against aggressors, always when there was at least some justification for it. People respected power because they had to, but they wouldn’t always take statements or demonstrations at face value. Sometimes, that power had to be directly shown.

It was frustrating to declare to someone that there were consequences to their actions, and be rudely ignored. It was frustrating to take the high road every time, when it would be so easy to make problems go away with a quick slit of the throat.

“The world is unfair,” said Valencia. “It is manifestly and obviously unfair. Part of the way that unfairness manifests is that the side of good and decency is disadvantaged. There are burdens placed on those that are trying to do right. Their asymmetry is inherent and unavoidable, and the only reason that good will triumph, if it does, is because by happenstance the good have power over the evil. That’s the situation we find ourselves in. I have extraordinary power, as do you, but just because we have that power doesn’t mean that we are free of burdens. Being good will, from time to time, mean being annoyed with not being able to exercise your full power. It will mean going against your instincts and denying yourself satisfaction.”

“It seems like a bit of a raw deal,” replied Bethel, arching an eyebrow. “And irrelevant, if the end goal of the group, which I’m possibly still a member of, is to install Juniper with the ultimate power of complete godhood.”

“True,” replied Valencia. She was always easy to admit things that undermined her point, and always ready with some justification and context. It was, so far as Bethel took the time to understand Valencia’s methods, a way of instilling patterns of thinking. Valencia wanted to be called on the simplicity of her answers, she wanted the scrutiny, the better to make examination a habit. “But the end goal isn’t necessarily true, because the Dungeon Master might lie, and the timeline is equally unclear, perhaps weeks or months, perhaps decades. We don’t know what the future holds, so we must push ahead.”

“But we would be better driving toward that end goal,” said Bethel.

“Of course,” said Valencia with a shrug. “That’s what we’re doing. That’s why we’re here. This is the path that we must follow, if we’re to help end this world and create a new one.”

Bethel had thought, but not said, that she would never be allowed back with the others, and even if she was, she would never be a true member of the party again. What had been done was irreversible, save by methods that were considered too extreme, or difficult, or immoral to ever use. But one of the lessons that Valencia had tried to hammer home was that while certain things could never be undone, murder most obvious among them, we still had to push on ahead, leaving the past in the past, trying to do better, dwelling on our mistakes only in order to understand them, rather than for the purposes of self-flagellation.

So far as The Incident went, Bethel had finally gotten to the stage of self-flagellation. She knew now that it was not only her fault, and not only easily preventable, but also a part of who she was, or at least had been. In truth, some of the deep introspection she had given to The Incident would need to be applied to everything else in her life, the murders, the torture, all the rest, but none of that was so immediate and painful, and it could wait.

Valencia had sat down one day, looking troubled, not long after one of her morning trips through the city. She was going to get mail from elsewhere, Bethel knew, part of an arrangement that they had established early on, and which Bethel never pushed her on. She occasionally brought things back, sometimes useful entads, and though it wasn’t discussed, it was fairly transparent that the provenance of these entads was Amaryllis. On this particular day, there were no entads, just Valencia, no familiar smile on her face, her eyebrows drawn together.

“News?” Bethel finally asked.

“Yes,” replied Valencia. “I’m still processing and deciding what’s to be done.”

“Is this news local or planar?” asked Bethel. There had been some rumblings that their reforms in Orrangush were not going unnoticed by higher powers, though it was all quite pedestrian compared to what either of them were capable of. The ‘higher powers’ in question could be flattened in an eyeblink, if it came to that.

“It’s planar,” replied Valencia. She looked at Bethel. “Tell me, do you like our life here?”

Bethel thought for a moment before answering, which Valencia always encouraged. “I’m not much of a home here,” she finally said. “I liked how it was before. I liked our group, diverse but still bound together, much like a family. Everyone had their own room, with communal spaces and public facilities, going about their business, sometimes leaving but always returning. With just you … it’s not enough for me. Everything else added on though, I could take or leave. Orrangush is perfectly serviceable as a city, but I’m restricted in how much space I can take up. Ideally, I would be a large house with a family or two living in me, perhaps like a castle, if no defenses were required, servants living in their quarters, I suppose, the kind of home that has extensive grounds around it.”

“Have you been building up time?” asked Valencia.

“Of course,” replied Bethel. “The bottle was a better entad for space expansion though, with more freedom.”

“You said,” replied Valencia, biting her lip for a moment. “But you have time stored? Lots of it?”

“Approximately eleven trillion trillion units,” said Bethel.

“You said that it was worse though,” said Valencia. Her face betrayed no surprise, with a devil’s skill at revealing nothing.

“It allows more space, but less in terms of customization,” replied Bethel.

(Entads that had some portion bigger on the inside than on the outside weren’t terribly rare, but ones that were on the scale of the bottle were fairly uncommon. The one that Valencia had brought, which was probably sent by Amaryllis, was capable of opening a door to an extradimensional space that, on first appearances, seemed to extend to infinity. The interior was filled with temporary objects that couldn’t pass the border of the door, and would vary depending on what you were thinking about when you first opened the door. It was not, in fact, infinite though, being limited to approximately 120 miles from the doorway. After some experimentation, Bethel had been able to find a setting for the doorway that would allow her to designate everything beyond as a room, and had been accruing time chamber time ever since.)

“You wanted to be useful,” said Valencia. “You wanted to have a way to come back.”

“I did,” replied Bethel. “Utility and power are the only reasons that they would ever allow it, and I’ve done my best to make myself attractive on those fronts. What do they need me for?”

“The second generation of tuung,” said Valencia.

“What intervals?” asked Bethel.

“None,” Valencia replied. “They’re thinking of a straight shot, all hundred thousand at once, no check-ins or breaks. It would be approximately four days, ideally spent in Necrolaborem.”

“The exclusion zone?” asked Bethel, arching an eyebrow. “Is there a particular reason?”

“There are eight million people there who have been raised under a psychopath’s regime,” said Valencia. “Many of them are children. The aim is to greatly accelerate the second generation of tuung, then use them for the humanitarian effort.”

“You’re being rather clinical,” said Bethel. Usually Valencia put on a veneer of being her normal self, whatever the devil’s machinations were happening beneath the surface. She was quite open about this, and for that reason, Bethel had accepted it.

“It reminds me of my own childhood,” said Valencia. “Keenly, in fact. Clinical language is a way of avoiding my feelings.” She could have faked different emotions, but was choosing not to, which Bethel appreciated.

“All we can do is our best,” said Bethel.

“I know,” said Valencia. “I might cry about it for a bit, when I have time. And obviously what Amaryllis has done with the tuung, and is planning to do on a large scale very shortly, evokes some of the same feelings. But that’s not the question at hand. The question is how you feel about helping.”

“I’ll do it, obviously,” said Bethel.

“Yes, of course,” replied Valencia. “But how do you feel about it?”

“At first, butterflies in my stomach, I suppose. Nervousness about what it would be like to come back to them,” said Bethel. “I tried, momentarily, to play out how it would go, what they would all say, the apologies that I would have to make, and how they would be taken. How Juniper —”

“He won’t be there,” said Valencia. “He’ll keep his distance, for now.”

“Oh,” said Bethel. “Sensible, I suppose.” It did hurt though, in a way. Nothing was forgiven, and no apology would suffice. There would not even be an overture toward an attempt at reconciliation, not with him. “My second thought, following the anxiety, was that I should extract something from them, or punish them. Amaryllis in particular could be made to beg, or be forced to sacrifice. My mind went to the ways I could extract, and what I could extract.”

Valencia was silent, waiting.

“You would probably say that would be antisocial behavior, or a way of expressing my own feelings of weakness or insecurity, or sabotage of a good thing, reconciliation, in pessimistic anticipation of it turning sour,” said Bethel. “Something like that?”

Valencia shrugged.

“You’re of the opinion that I should just do it, be gracious and apologetic, mend fences,” said Bethel.

“No, actually,” said Valencia. “I’m worried that you’re not ready, and that things will come to a head, or you’ll get heated, or that they’re not ready, and they’ll act with retribution because of their feelings. But we’re talking about eight million people who were, essentially, slaves, and this might be one of the only methods of getting the humanitarian crisis under control. Reading between the lines from what she’s said, there’s no workable backup plan.”

“I’ll do whatever you recommend,” said Bethel.

“That’s not ideal, from my perspective,” said Valencia. “I think it’s a bad idea for you personally, and for the group dynamics, but I do think that it might be necessary for these people, who I can’t help but see myself in. If it’s my decision, then I’m absolving you of having to make a moral judgment of your own. It would be saying that it’s better to be guided than to guide yourself, which isn’t what we’ve been trying to do here.”

“Then I’ll go,” said Bethel. “No Juniper?”

“No,” replied Valencia.

“Perhaps for the best,” said Bethel, though there was a bit of sting there which deepened the more she thought about it.

If she talked to Valencia about it, Valencia would undoubtedly say that sting of remorse was a good thing.

Valencia went by herself, with the plan being to leave Bethel alone for no more than two days. It wasn’t entirely clear that the plan for the second generation would actually be required, or that it would go through, because there were lots of variables in play, and conversations that had yet to happen, because this was all apparently quite a recent development. If it was deemed necessary, Bethel would be pulled from Orrangush and spend half a week in Necrolaborem, which she wasn’t particularly looking forward to, for a variety of reasons.

It was Bethel’s first time being alone in quite some time, not including the few times that Valencia had spent an hour or so by herself. This was not to say that Bethel was literally by herself, only that there was no one who actually knew her, just people who visited their candy shop, or who were part of their criminal enterprise. Bethel had added a basement to herself, along with extra doors through which various traffic could flow, and business took place down there, usually not ending until the late hours.

In the stillness of night, a span from roughly two hours after midnight to just before dawn, the city was quiet. Larger cities, it was claimed, never slept, but that simply wasn’t true for Orrangush. Sometimes, in the block that was under Bethel’s full surveillance, there were night owls, or people who were just having trouble sleeping, but for the most part, there was nothing, everyone asleep but her.

Bethel was still ‘spying’, as Valencia termed it. There had never been any real push by Valencia to stop the practice. A dim view of spying was a natural outcome of their discussions though, with condemnation of that behavior implied but not outright stated. Watching people was a form of power, and it was now clear to Bethel that power was one of the most fundamentally important parts of her inner life. Spying was a way to predict people, to make sure that they wouldn’t turn on her, to nail them in place, as it were. It was a defensive position, but one that others largely hated, if they knew, or if they thought about it for long enough.

The spying was, however, a vital part of ‘therapy’, a way to understand people, to model what was going on inside their heads, and thus better understand what it was they should do, and by proxy, what she should do, and how she thought.

At night, when it was dead silent, she watched the people sleeping, and had some thoughts of her own. Sometimes, if the mood struck her, she would read books, or watch movies on Amaryllis’ set up, or otherwise while away the time while waiting for people to rise again. She went into dreams, from time to time, but it wasn’t particularly edifying. Mostly, with Valencia gone, she was left thinking about her anxieties.

On the morning of her first full day alone, Bethel saw, at the very edge of her sensorium, something that she could not account for: a young woman who looked just like Amaryllis, with the exception of a single eye that was a different color, and a minor discoloration of the skin of one hand.

Bethel had pushed tendrils through the ground, and her area of influence encompassed not just the city block that the candy store sat on, but every surrounding block as well. For the most part, she didn’t use her influence, though she had taken to making the lives of the people around her better in subtle ways, and would sometimes act when there was some plausible deniability: within the area of her influence, there were no vermin, diseases would sometimes seem to solve themselves, blankets would be pulled close in the middle of the night, and food would seem to last longer and keep better than it had a right to. Bethel had more power than almost anyone, and she had started making plans for what she might do, once it made sense to take the shackles off, once she could trust herself not to fuck things up.

Her sensorium extended beyond her influence though, quite a bit, in fact, and it was through this periphery, where she wasn’t actually able to affect much of anything, that she spotted the woman. She looked exactly like Amaryllis, but she had a strange signature to her, a magic that wasn’t of any known school, but also not an entad. She was, so far as Bethel could tell, doing nothing more than sitting at a distant cafe and reading a book, The Diffident Empire, which appeared to be nothing particularly special, concerning itself with rather dry accounts of policy failures. The woman was wearing a dress that perfectly matched the styles of Orrangush, with a wool sweater that might have been knitted from the local fleece, and a skirt that was dyed woad-blue, a staple of the region. She had some of Amaryllis’ same expressions, but there was little of the tension that Amaryllis normally carried.

Bethel didn’t know what to do. Her first instinct was to go over there in some way, to eject the patrons that were inside her, leave the body that was interacting with them, and confront this imposter Amaryllis. Bethel wanted to scare her, to dominate her, to hold power, to take control. It would feel good, and it would allay her feelings … for a time. In the long run, if that was Amaryllis, it would contribute to alienating her, to stoking feelings of fear, and while fear was a way to control someone and exert power, it wasn’t a particularly good one.

Bethel decided to wait and watch. It very much looked like Amaryllis was taking a holiday in Orrangush, without a care in the world, but that was obviously impossible, not just because that wasn’t something that Amaryllis would do, but because Amaryllis would certainly be working on the second generation of tuung in Necrolaborem. There was, unfortunately, no way to solve the question of who or what this woman was, not unless she came closer.

In the end, around mid-morning, Bethel was kept from having to make a decision, because the Amaryllis (or whoever she was) packed up her book, paid for the coffee she’d been drinking, and began walking toward the candy shop. Bethel began moving people out, employing a few subtle and not-so-subtle nudges. The temperature dropped a few degrees, the place lost some of its characteristic warm lighting, and as much as possible, the smells were swept away. People began to leave, as though it were their own idea.

By the time Amaryllis arrived, still carrying her book, the shop was empty, and the alterations that Bethel had made were wiped away, making the place once again inviting.

Bethel was nervous, and it was a sign of how far she’d come in relatively short order that she could recognize and name that nervousness. Amaryllis was a Penndraig, and there was still some trace of power, some vestige of command or ownership. Bethel would never admit that out loud, not even to Valencia. It was something that she could and did fight against, successfully, but it was still there, like a tickle at the back of a throat. Amaryllis was also dangerous, so far as her kind went, intelligent and capable of putting petty emotions to the side when she had a mission she wanted to accomplish. Not everyone was capable of killing in cold blood, but Amaryllis definitely was.

When she entered the shop, Bethel was waiting behind the counter. Form was fiction, so far as Bethel was concerned, and where she had typically gone with tall, muscular, darker-skinned women, she had altered herself to be someone less imposing, a shorter woman with a flat chest and a touch of androgyny to her features. It read, she hoped, as less threatening, less certain.

Amaryllis looked at her for a moment. “I got word that Rosa was gone. I thought it might be wise for the two of us to have a chat.”

“Did you talk to her about it?” asked Bethel.

“Of course,” replied Amaryllis. “She didn’t think that it was a conversation that we should have, but she didn’t put her foot down about it, so in my opinion, she’s more worried about fringe outcomes than what she actually expects the average outcome to be.” She looked around the shop for a moment, taking in the bins and jars that had been so artfully arranged. “It’s not a home.” She said this somewhat like a question.

“It is,” said Bethel. “The upstairs is where Valencia sleeps, and during the day, we work here, sometimes making candy in the back room. I never objected to the mix of commerce and residence within me. People use their homes for many things.” She stared at Amaryllis, penetrating her with the full sensorium. Judging by how many eggs were left in her ovaries, it had been six months for Amaryllis, which meant that she had to have been using some kind of other time chamber, or more likely, time chambers. This was to be expected: Amaryllis liked having extra time. “You’re not you.”

“Valencia doesn’t tell you?” asked Amaryllis.

“Valencia tells me what she thinks I need to know,” said Bethel. “There are, of course, newspapers, but the people who live near here get only a small amount of news from Anglecynn, and virtually nothing from a place like Poran. Enough to know that there are things afoot, but not enough to know the specifics.”

Neither of them had mentioned The Incident, but it was hanging over them like a cloud.

“It was a loyalty bonus,” said Amaryllis. “We call them clones, but in reality, they’re more like extensions of myself that sync up every so often to trade memories, knowledge, and experiences. In a few hours, the prime instance of me will know about what transpired here.”

“I see,” said Bethel. The cloud was still hanging over them, and Bethel took a moment to think about why that was. “I’m sorry.”

“Yes?” asked Amaryllis, raising an eyebrow.

“I’m sorry for what I did to Juniper,” said Bethel. “I’m also sorry for the threats and indignities. I was dealing with feelings in ways that were not very good for the people around me. I can list the specific examples, if you’d like, but I don’t want to retread old ground unless you think you would get something from it.”

“Apology accepted,” said Amaryllis, waving away the offer. She gave a small bow of her head.

“Do you feel the desire to twist the knife?” asked Bethel. She was speaking off the cuff, which could be dangerous. “Do you want to extract more from me, to ask about the hundreds of people I’ve murdered, or the things that I’ve done? Do you want to extract promises from me?”

“Of course,” said Amaryllis with a shrug. “What I feel and what I should do are divorced from each other. I can speak plainly about what I want, if that’s what you’d like, but I don’t think it would do any good.”

“Valencia says that unexpressed anger has a way of festering,” replied Bethel. She shifted her imagined weight to her other foot for a moment. “Would you like to sit? I should shut the store down, if you’re visiting. There’s seating upstairs, and I can make some proper food, or you could have some sweets, if you would prefer.”

“I would like that, yes,” said Amaryllis.

They went up together, though Bethel was, of course, already there, in a sense. Amaryllis sat on the chaise lounge, while Bethel took the larger padded chair that was often Valencia’s spot. It was a warm, pleasant place, of the sort that Bethel had come to prefer, large but not cavernous, cozy but not suffocating or cluttered. There were numerous accents that made the place feel more like a home, bits of mementos, various gifts that had been accrued from either their earlier travels or from their time in Orrangush.

“I want to kill you,” said Amaryllis, once she’d settled in place. “I want to make you suffer. I want to put you on trial, to deliver a decisive critique, to inflict pain and cruelty. I’m angry.” She stopped and looked squarely in the eyes of Bethel’s body. “I don’t let that anger rule me though. I don’t spend my time being angry, if I can help it, not unless it works to drive me toward some goal or purpose. Here, anger is the opposite of what I need.”

“Because I’m powerful,” said Bethel.

“Yes,” replied Amaryllis. “But even if you weren’t powerful, the anger would do me no good. Hurting you would give satisfaction, but it would be fleeting, and cost me resources that could best be spent elsewhere. More to the point, it wouldn’t be good in the moral sense. I favor rehabilitation rather than retribution, where possible. So I’ve come here for the purposes of reconciliation.”

“And because you need me,” said Bethel. “You want the second generation of tuung, but you can’t produce them without using me as a facility.”

Amaryllis was silent for a moment. “It was my understanding that you had already agreed.”

“We sometimes do things that we’re not particularly fond of,” said Bethel. “As you said.”

“I came here wanting to understand your state of mind,” said Amaryllis. “I wanted to know your motivation, your thoughts on the matter.”

“People are malleable, and I’m not an exception,” said Bethel. “I’ve known for some time that this might be asked of me, and I’ve been trying to put it into a favorable light. No home holds a hundred thousand people though. It will be an institution, a city, rather than a home.”

“Homes in fractal?” asked Amaryllis. “Or does that not help?”

“A bit, it does,” replied Bethel, thinking for a moment. There would need to be structural changes in a potential facility to make that work. “But I will experience nothing of it, because it will be so incredibly sped up.”

“You said that makes it better, to have it sped up,” said Amaryllis. That was from their earlier discussions, Bethel was fairly sure, when they had been negotiating for the first generation of tuung.

“Better, in a sense,” said Bethel. “I was less forthright, then, less able to articulate.”

“Go ahead,” said Amaryllis.

“It was never the most serious of indignities,” said Bethel. “For a mortal I would compare it to, say, an obnoxious dinner guest, or perhaps someone who won’t stop their boorish behavior at a ball. The uncomfortability is that it happened, rather than the actual duration it took. A handful of days is, naturally, more tolerable than a decade or more, but there’s still an unsavory element there. I’ll have known that it happened.”

“I’m sorry,” said Amaryllis. “We’re still looking into other options. We didn’t listen to you well enough the first time around, and this time I’ll be looking more closely into what your specific needs are. I accept a share of responsibility.” She didn’t say for what, and Bethel wondered if that was out of politeness or a desire for distancing language. Either way, Bethel was grateful that it was left at sentiment.

“You believe there can be a reconciliation?” asked Bethel.

“I don’t know,” replied Amaryllis. “It’s possible. The problem, aside from the obvious interpersonal issues, is that the ways in which we need you are not the ways in which you wish to be needed. You want to provide safety, security, and comfort, but what we are in perennially short supply of is overwhelming firepower and mobile defenses. Even if the interpersonal issues could be solved, which will take some time, effort, and understanding from all involved, the central crux wouldn’t be so easily handled. Bluntly, we don’t need a house, we need a meta-entad to use as a tool and weapon.”

The words hurt. After some time thinking about it, Bethel decided that they were not calculated to hurt, only put bluntly because it was true and necessary, a way of speaking directly about the issue to leave no ambiguity and no ability to shield egos.

“I’m dealing with the same issues with the others,” said Amaryllis. “Juniper fundamentally does not want to be the savior of Aerb, but pushes himself anyway, because he knows it’s right. Unfortunately, his pushing is imperfect, weighted toward what he enjoys. And Grak is very similar, not terribly interested in the awesome power that comes from being the best warder in the world, only willing to push on because it’s expected of him, or because he feels a weight of obligation. That was the state we found him in, and now it’s the state he’s returned to, which I don’t think has been terribly good for him.”

“And yourself?” asked Bethel. “Are you so perfectly content to be a tool toward some purpose, with your feelings cast aside?”

“The idea is never to cast aside feelings,” said Amaryllis. “It’s a matter of understanding your internal self well enough that you can make paths through what needs to happen. Sometimes you trick yourself into being more optimal, but that’s hard to do, and inconsistent. I use my feelings where I can, and try my best to suppress or deal with those feelings when they feel like they might get in the way.”

“It’s what you’re asking of me,” said Bethel. “To turn my desires into assets, or otherwise neglect them.”

“It’s more difficult for you than for damned near anyone on Aerb,” said Amaryllis. “The average citizen of Anglecynn has a great number of things that they could possibly do to improve the world in some way, most of them rather small, in the scheme of things. In fact, their dreams and ambitions might actually be the driving element to placing them within society, because it’s such an important element of producing quality work. But for someone like you, who has so incredibly much potential to change the world, your ideal workload has almost no bearing on what you personally should be doing to enact the most good.”

“You see that this does not please me,” said Bethel, crossing her legs for a moment. There was a bluntness to Amaryllis that nettled.

“Of course I do,” said Amaryllis. “For what it’s worth, it doesn’t please me either. It’s the condition that most of us are operating under though. Juniper is the only one for whom the world might actually bend, such that he can do what he wants without having to worry about what’s necessary, but that’s definitely in question.”

“Will he ever be ready to see me?” asked Bethel. “To accept an apology, to understand that I’ve changed?”

“In the long term?” asked Amaryllis. “Of course. It’s not fair or just that he should have to have anything to do with you, but he has it in his head to rush toward the ending, and I mostly agree, which means that’s what we’re doing. We can’t do that while we have a handicap, down a member, and our most powerful one at that. It’s horribly mercenary, but there’s no other reasonable way to approach it.”

“And in the short term?” asked Bethel.

“We’ll have Valencia give him a psych eval, then have her give you a psych eval, and see where we are,” said Amaryllis. “We’re fortunate, in a sense, that so much shit has been happening all at once. It makes any individual bad thing have a bit less impact.”

“I see,” said Bethel.

“I still don’t understand what you want, in all this,” said Amaryllis. “It would be perfectly possible for you to fuck off and do whatever the hell you liked, without us in the picture at all. You could say your goodbyes and start up a new life with a clean slate. I know that you have your own traumas to deal with, and you think that finding Uther Penndraig is going to be a part of that, but it’s not clear to me that’s your driving purpose, above and beyond being a house.”

Unspoken was the idea that if that really was what was driving Bethel, then she couldn’t possibly be considered properly socialized, let alone good. It was something that Bethel often thought about.

“The idea of forgiving Uther sickens me,” said Bethel. “The idea of you setting him free from whatever trap or scheme has held him in stasis, having him start up a life of adventure without having to account for his actions — if I had blood, it would be pumping hard through my veins. I detest the man, all the more because everyone believed him to be the best, most important being to ever exist.” There, again, that familiar feeling, wanting to do violence, an impulse rooted in panicked helplessness. The violence was a form of ego preservation, the fantasy of violence against Uther, if it were even possible, a way of assuaging her mind. It was remarkably human. Unfortunately, it wasn’t the person that Amaryllis wanted her to be. Bethel would also grudgingly admit, after some reflection, that it wasn’t the sort of person that she wanted to be. “You need me, you’ve said it yourself. I’ll be asked to do things that I don’t want to do. Some other hypothetical family, presumably one that’s more well-adjusted, and perhaps more conventional, would have to be willing to put up with being put in danger at every turn, with wandering this plane and beyond at the whims of greater forces.”

“You want to be a home,” said Amaryllis. “I’m sorry, but I don’t think that’s going to be possible, not with us.”

“Valencia lives here,” said Bethel. “She could probably be encouraged to continue doing so. Plus some of the other members who orbit this ragtag band, perhaps. Those a bit more accustomed to bleakness? I have a bit of fondness for Pallida.”

“She died,” replied Amaryllis. “I’ve already done most of the work in getting her back though. She’s currently incubating in an entad and will be ready to be pulled in another six months. Of course, she’ll still be a baby then, but we’ve removed the nominal mother from the equation, and she’s secured.”

“That would be something that I could help with,” said Bethel. “I could age her up.”

“It’s crossed my mind,” said Amaryllis. “We would need to hire a trustworthy mother for her, and ideally others as well, but yes, it could be done. It’s not something that I would want to push on you, and so far as I know, Pallida didn’t consider a potential reincarnation to be urgent.”

“I do want to help,” said Bethel. She leaned forward. “You can see that, can’t you?”

“I don’t know,” said Amaryllis. “With you, it’s hard to say. I trust in what Valencia tells me, which is precious little most weeks. My worry is that you’re learning the wrong lessons somehow, or that you’re suppressing your impulses in unhealthy ways, or just … lying. I’m hoping that being honest about my feelings here is the right way to go. Most of it isn’t wholly rational, but these concerns do have some grounding in truth. It’s just hard to know how much weight I should give them.”

“Would it help if you could look into my soul?” asked Bethel. “If you could turn me inside out to see who I really was?”

“Yes, of course,” said Amaryllis. “But it would also be such a profound violation of you that it would almost certainly be counterproductive. And so far as I know, such a method doesn’t exist. Does it?”

“No,” replied Bethel. “Just a flight of fancy. I wouldn’t be surprised if it were possible with some entad though, or some combination of entads.”

“It’s not something that I plan to pursue,” said Amaryllis.

“I would do it, if it would help to make things right between us,” said Bethel. “If it would help Juniper to understand.”

“He understands,” said Amaryllis. “He can put himself in your shoes. That’s one of the things that made him a good friend to you, and it hasn’t changed. Understanding only gets him so far though.”

There was bitterness in her voice, the kind of acid that she normally reserved for people who were too lazy to fill out the proper paperwork, or the overwrought bureaucracy of the Third Empire, or her family. She was Amaryllis; the acidity could just as easily have been suppressed, though perhaps she thought that Bethel’s surveillance was good enough to combat any attempt at control. More likely, she was giving voice to that animosity, letting it out so that it might breathe and eventually evaporate. Valencia had much to say on the subject of silently stewing with your emotions and waiting until things were truly unbearable.

“When do you need me to get started?” asked Bethel.

“Not for some time,” said Amaryllis. “Valencia needs time to comb through personnel and get a handle on things, and there are ongoing discussions of what changes we’ll make to societal structure, as well as the internal physical aspects of the space. It’s downtime.”

“Ah,” replied Bethel. “Then know that I’m ready. Valencia has already put everyone here on notice. They know that I’ll disappear soon, not to return for quite some time.”

“Good,” said Amaryllis. “Then we have some downtime.” She hesitated. “I’ve been staying just outside the city, but I would be amenable to sleeping here in the interim, if you would have me.”

“Oh,” said Bethel. “Yes, of course.”